<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Phil Galewitz, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/philgalewitz/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/philgalewitz/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 10:31:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Phil Galewitz, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/philgalewitz/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>9 states, including Virginia, poised to end coverage for millions if Trump cuts Medicaid funding</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/11/9-states-including-virginia-poised-to-end-coverage-for-millions-if-trump-cuts-medicaid-funding/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Galewitz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>pgalewitz@kff.org (Phil Galewitz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 10:28:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Affordable Care Act]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicaid enrollment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicaid expansion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41104</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With Donald Trump’s return to the White House and Republicans taking full control of Congress in 2025, the Affordable Care Act’s Medicaid expansion is back on the chopping block. More than 3 million adults in nine states would be at immediate risk of losing their health coverage should the GOP reduce the extra federal Medicaid [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/mediciad-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">State social services workers signed up homeless residents for Medicaid at a resource fair in Richmond in 2018. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury)</p><p>With Donald Trump’s return to the White House and Republicans taking full control of Congress in 2025, the Affordable Care Act’s Medicaid expansion is back on the chopping block.</p>
<aside class="block--sidebar alignright ">
<div class="wp-block-kaiser-health-news-partner block--partner">
<p class="partner__content">
</div>
</aside>
<p>More than 3 million adults in nine states would be at immediate risk of losing their health coverage should the GOP reduce the extra federal Medicaid funding that’s enabled states to widen eligibility, <a href="https://www.kff.org/medicaid/issue-brief/medicaid-expansion-is-a-red-and-blue-state-issue/" target="_blank">according to KFF</a>, a health information nonprofit that includes KFF Health News, and the Georgetown University <a href="https://ccf.georgetown.edu/2024/11/27/federal-funding-cuts-to-medicaid-may-trigger-automatic-loss-of-health-coverage-for-millions-of-residents-of-certain-states/" target="_blank">Center for Children and Families</a>. That’s because the states have trigger laws that would swiftly end their Medicaid expansions if federal funding falls.</p>
<p>The states are Arizona, Arkansas, Illinois, Indiana, Montana, New Hampshire, North Carolina, Utah, and Virginia.</p>
<div class="datawrapper-embed block--datawrapper-embed "><iframe id="datawrapper-chart-NzypI" title="Which States Have Medicaid-Expansion Trigger Laws?" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/NzypI" height="578" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" aria-label="Interactive DataWrapper Embed" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div>
<p>The 2010 Affordable Care Act encouraged states to expand Medicaid programs to cover more low-income Americans who didn’t get health insurance through their jobs. Forty states and the District of Columbia agreed, extending health insurance since 2014 to an estimated 21 million people and helping drive the U.S. uninsured rate to record lows.</p>
<p>In exchange, the federal government pays 90% of the cost to cover the expanded population. That’s far higher than the federal match for other Medicaid beneficiaries, which averages about 57% nationwide.</p>
<p>Conservative policy groups, which generally have opposed the ACA, say the program costs too much and covers too many people. Democrats say the Medicaid expansion has saved lives and helped communities by widening coverage to people who could not afford private insurance.</p>
<p>If Congress cuts federal funding, Medicaid expansion would be at risk in all states that have opted into it — even those without trigger laws — because state legislatures would be forced to make up the difference, said Renuka Tipirneni, an associate professor at the University of Michigan’s School of Public Health.</p>
<p>Decisions to keep or roll back the expansion “would depend on the politics at the state level,” Tipirneni said.</p>
<p>For instance, Michigan approved a trigger as part of its Medicaid expansion in 2013, when it was controlled by a Republican governor and legislature. Last year, with the government controlled by Democrats, the state eliminated its funding trigger.</p>
<p>Six of the nine states with trigger laws — Arizona, Arkansas, Indiana, Montana, North Carolina, and Utah — went for Trump in the 2024 election.</p>
	<div class="newsroomSidebarContainer ">
	<div class="newsroomSidebar">
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia became the 33rd state to expand Medicaid in the summer of 2018, which allowed more people to be eligible. Following months of legislative debate that year, it passed with bipartisan support. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Medicaid is a state and federal program that provides insurance coverage to low-income people or people with disabilities. Prior to the expansion taking effect in 2019, childless adults were not eligible in Virginia and parents were only eligible for up to 38% of the federal poverty level. According to a 2022 National Library of Medicine </span><a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9134455/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">study</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, Virginia had one of the highest uninsured rates of non-elderly adults below 138% of the federal poverty level. The study also found that people were less likely to delay medical care since the expansions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s the benefits to Virginians that Sen. Jennifer Boysko, D-Fairfax, said she is focused on amid possible changes in the federal landscape. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">She said that the Senate’s finance committee discussed the matter at a recent retreat and she hopes lawmakers with higher concentrations of people who have benefitted from Medicaid in their districts will think about protecting the expansion. Boysko finds it “disturbing” that Medicaid funding could be on the federal “chopping block” and is concerned what a federal GOP trifecta might mean for the Affordable Care Act overall. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, Boysko noted that Virginia’s state health insurance exchange — also made possible by the ACA—  could be a way to “absorb” some patients if need be and said that lawmakers may also need to “get creative” with some of its surplus. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the meantime, Virginia and the nation are also experiencing a Medicaid “unwinding,” as eligibility checks are underway to determine who still meets criteria to remain covered and who does not. In recent months, over 500,000 people have been </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/nearly-500000-virginians-in-medicaid-have-been-disenrolled/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">disenrolled </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">while about 2 million have been </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/va-dept-of-medical-services-to-tap-reserve-fund-to-cover-delayed-payments-amid-medicaid-unwinding/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">redetermined</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, according to data from the Department of Medical Assistance Services.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We will address whatever we have to in the General Assembly to do the best we can to help protect our residents,” Boysko said. “But we&#8217;ve still got to see how this all pans out.” —Charlotte Rene Woods, Virginia Mercury reporter</span></div>
	</div>
	
<p>Most of the nine states’ triggers kick in if federal funding falls below the 90% threshold. Arizona’s trigger would eliminate its expansion if funding falls below 80%.</p>
<p>Montana’s law rolls back expansion below 90% funding but allows it to continue if lawmakers identify additional funding. Under state law, Montana lawmakers <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/news/article/montana-medicaid-expansion-renewal-2025/" target="_blank">must reauthorize its Medicaid expansion</a> in 2025 or the expansion will end.</p>
<p>Across the states with triggers, between 3.1 million and 3.7 million people would swiftly lose their coverage, researchers at KFF and the Georgetown center estimate. The difference depends on how states treat people who were added to Medicaid before the ACA expansion; they may continue to qualify even if the expansion ends.</p>
<p>Three other states — Iowa, Idaho, and New Mexico— have laws that require their governments to mitigate the financial impact of losing federal Medicaid expansion funding but would not automatically end expansions. With those three states included, about 4.3 million Medicaid expansion enrollees would be at risk of losing coverage, according to KFF.</p>
<p>The ACA allowed Medicaid expansions to adults with incomes up to 138% of the federal poverty level, or about $20,783 for an individual in 2024.</p>
<p>Nearly a quarter of the 81 million people enrolled in Medicaid nationally are in the program due to expansions.</p>
<p>“With a reduction in the expansion match rate, it is likely that all states would need to evaluate whether to continue expansion coverage because it would require a significant increase in state spending,” said Robin Rudowitz, vice president and director of the Program on Medicaid and the Uninsured at KFF. “If states drop coverage, it is likely that there would be an increase in the number of uninsured, and that would limit access to care across red and blue states that have adopted expansion.”</p>
<p>States rarely cut eligibility for social programs such as Medicaid once it’s been granted.</p>
<p>The triggers make it politically easier for state lawmakers to end Medicaid expansion because they would not have to take any new action to cut coverage, said Edwin Park, a research professor at the Georgetown University Center for Children and Families.</p>
<p>To see the impact of trigger laws, consider what happened after the Supreme Court in 2022 struck down <em>Roe v. Wade</em> and, with it, the constitutional right to an abortion. Conservative lawmakers in 13 states had crafted trigger laws that would automatically implement bans in the event a national right to abortion were struck down. Those state laws resulted in restrictions taking effect immediately after the court ruling, or shortly thereafter.</p>
<p>States adopted triggers as part of Medicaid expansion to win over lawmakers skeptical of putting state dollars on the hook for a federal program unpopular with most Republicans.</p>
<p>It’s unclear what Trump and congressional Republicans will do with Medicaid after he takes office in January, but one indicator could be a recent recommendation from the Paragon Health Institute, a leading conservative policy organization led by former Trump health adviser Brian Blase.</p>
<p>Paragon has proposed that starting in 2026 the federal government would phase down the 90% federal match for expansion until 2034, when it would reach parity with each state’s federal match for its traditional enrollees. Under that plan, states could still get ACA Medicaid expansion funding but restrict coverage to enrollees with incomes up to the federal poverty level. Currently, to receive expansion funding, states must offer coverage to everyone up to 138% of the poverty level.</p>
<p>Daniel Derksen, director of the Center for Rural Health at the University of Arizona, said it’s unlikely Arizona would move to eliminate its trigger and make up for lost federal funds. “It would be a tough sell right now as it would put a big strain on the budget,” he said.</p>
<p>Medicaid has been in the crosshairs of Republicans in Washington before. Republican congressional leaders in 2017 proposed legislation to cut federal expansion funding, a move that would have shifted billions in costs to states. That plan, part of a strategy to repeal Obamacare, ultimately failed.</p>
<aside class="meta-authors meta">        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        </aside>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Halfway through ‘unwinding,’ Medicaid enrollment is down about 10 million</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/02/15/halfway-through-unwinding-medicaid-enrollment-is-down-about-10-million/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Phil Galewitz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>pgalewitz@kff.org (Phil Galewitz)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>kffhealthnews@kff.org (KFF Health News)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 05:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CHIP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicaid reenrollment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicaid unwinding]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=37832</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This story first appeared on KFF Health News. Halfway through what will be the biggest purge of Medicaid beneficiaries in a one-year span, enrollment in the government-run health insurance program is on track to return to roughly pre-pandemic levels. Medicaid, which covers low-income and disabled people, and the related Children’s Health Insurance Program grew to [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Getty_health_insurance-1024x683.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Getty_health_insurance-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Getty_health_insurance-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Getty_health_insurance-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Getty_health_insurance.jpeg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">(Getty Images) </p><p><em>This <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/news/article/medicaid-unwinding-chip-disenrollments-halfway-through-pandemic/" target="_blank">story</a> first appeared on <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/" target="_blank">KFF Health News</a>.</em></p>
<p>Halfway through what will be the biggest purge of Medicaid beneficiaries in a one-year span, enrollment in the government-run health insurance program is on track to return to roughly pre-pandemic levels.</p>
<p>Medicaid, which covers low-income and disabled people, and the related Children’s Health Insurance Program grew to a record 94 million enrollees as a result of a rule that prohibited states from terminating coverage during the nation’s public health emergency.</p>
<p>But since last April, states have removed <a href="https://www.kff.org/report-section/medicaid-enrollment-and-unwinding-tracker-overview/" target="_blank">more than 16 million people</a> from the programs in a process known as the “unwinding,” according to KFF estimates compiled from state-level data.</p>
<p>While many beneficiaries no longer qualify because their incomes rose, millions of people have been dropped from the rolls for procedural reasons like failing to respond to notices or return paperwork. But at the same time, millions have been re-enrolled or signed up for the first time.</p>
<p>The net result: Enrollment has fallen by about 9.5 million people from the record high reached last April, according to KFF. That puts Medicaid and CHIP enrollment on track to look, by the end of the unwinding later this year, a lot like it did at the start of the coronavirus pandemic: about 71 million people.</p>
<p>“What we are seeing is not dissimilar to what we saw before the pandemic — it is just happening on a bigger scale and more quickly,” said Larry Levitt, executive vice president for health policy at KFF.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8vVRapgeAj"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/10/17/halfway-through-unwinding-15-of-virginia-medicaid-enrollees-have-lost-coverage/">Halfway through unwinding, 15% of Virginia Medicaid enrollees have lost coverage</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Halfway through unwinding, 15% of Virginia Medicaid enrollees have lost coverage&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/10/17/halfway-through-unwinding-15-of-virginia-medicaid-enrollees-have-lost-coverage/embed/#?secret=fnvY6ylkJz#?secret=8vVRapgeAj" data-secret="8vVRapgeAj" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Enrollment churn has long been a feature of Medicaid. Before the pandemic, about 1 million to 1.5 million people nationwide fell off the Medicaid rolls each month — including many who still qualified but failed to renew their coverage, Levitt said.</p>
<p>During the unwinding, many people have been disenrolled in a shorter time. In some ways — and in some states — it’s been worse than expected.</p>
<p>The Biden administration predicted about 15 million people would lose coverage under Medicaid or CHIP during the unwinding period, nearly half due to procedural issues. Both predictions have proven low. Based on data reported so far, disenrollments <a href="https://www.kff.org/policy-watch/halfway-through-the-medicaid-unwinding-what-do-the-data-show/" target="_blank">are likely to exceed 17 million</a>, according to KFF — 70% due to procedural reasons.</p>
<p>But about two-thirds of the 48 million beneficiaries who have had their eligibility reviewed so far got their coverage renewed. About one-third lost it.</p>
<p>The federal government has given most states 12 months to complete their unwinding, starting with the first disenrollments between last April and October.</p>
<p>Timothy McBride, a health economist at Washington University in St. Louis, said the nation’s historically low unemployment rate means people who lose Medicaid coverage are more likely to find job-based coverage or be better able to afford plans on Obamacare marketplaces. “That is one reason why the drop in Medicaid is not a lot worse,” he said.</p>
<p>There are big differences between states. Oregon, for example, has disenrolled just 12% of its beneficiaries. Seventy-five percent have been renewed, according to KFF. The rest are pending.</p>
<p>At the other end of the spectrum, Oklahoma has dumped 43% of its beneficiaries in the unwinding, renewing coverage for just 34%. About 24% are pending.</p>
<p>States have varying eligibility rules, and some make it easier to stay enrolled. For instance, Oregon allows children to stay on Medicaid until age 6 without having to reapply. All other enrollees get up to two years of coverage regardless of changes in income.</p>
<p>Jennifer Harris, senior health policy advocate for Alabama Arise, an advocacy group, said her state’s Medicaid agency and other nonprofit organizations communicated well to enrollees about the need to reapply for coverage and that the state also hired more people to handle the surge. About 29% of beneficiaries in Alabama who’ve had eligibility reviews were disenrolled for procedural reasons, KFF found.</p>
<p>“Things are even keel in Alabama,” she said, noting that about 66% of enrollees have been renewed.</p>
<p>State officials have told the legislature that about a quarter of people disenrolled during the unwinding were re-enrolled within 90 days, she said.</p>
<p>One of a handful of states that have refused to expand Medicaid under the Affordable Care Act, Alabama had about 920,000 enrollees in Medicaid and CHIP in January 2020. That number rose to about 1.2 million in April 2023.</p>
<p>More than halfway into the unwinding, the state is on track for enrollment to return to pre-pandemic levels, Harris said.</p>
<p>Joan Alker, executive director of the Georgetown University Center for Children and Families, said she remains worried the drop in Medicaid enrollment among children is steeper than typical. That’s particularly bothersome because children usually qualify for Medicaid at higher household income levels than their parents or other adults.</p>
<p>During the unwinding 3.8 million children have lost Medicaid coverage, according to the center’s latest data. “Many more kids are falling off now than prior to the pandemic,” Alker said.</p>
<p>And when they’re dropped, many families struggle to get them back on, she said. “The whole system is backlogged and the ability of people to get back on in a timely fashion is more limited,” she said.</p>
<p>The big question, Levitt said, is how many of the millions of people dropped from Medicaid are now uninsured.</p>
<p>The only state to survey those disenrolled — Utah — <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/news/article/utah-medicaid-disenrollment-uninsured-increase/" target="_blank">discovered about 30% were uninsured</a>. Many of the rest found employer health coverage or signed up for subsidized coverage through the Affordable Care Act marketplace.</p>
<p>What’s happened nationwide remains unclear.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/about-us" target="_blank">KFF Health News</a> is a national newsroom that produces in-depth journalism about health issues and is one of the core operating programs at KFF — an independent source of health policy research, polling and journalism.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
