<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Elaine S. Povich, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/elaine-s-povich/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/elaine-s-povich/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 10:13:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Elaine S. Povich, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/elaine-s-povich/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>High school exit exams dwindle to about half a dozen states, including Virginia</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/06/high-school-exit-exams-dwindle-to-about-half-a-dozen-states/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 10:12:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[high school graduation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia students]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41055</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jill Norton, an education policy adviser in Massachusetts, has a teenage son with dyslexia and ADHD. Shelley Scruggs, an electrical engineer in the same state, also has a teenage son with ADHD. Both students go to the same technical high school. But this fall, Norton and Scruggs advocated on opposite sides of a Massachusetts ballot [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/graduates.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/graduates.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/graduates-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/graduates-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">High school graduates walk at their commencement at the Ernest N. Morial Convention Center in New Orleans. Louisiana is among the half dozen states that still require exit exams to graduate from high school. Most states have dropped exit exams, with Massachusetts being the latest. (Mario Tama/Getty Images)</p><p>Jill Norton, an education policy adviser in Massachusetts, has a teenage son with dyslexia and ADHD. Shelley Scruggs, an electrical engineer in the same state, also has a teenage son with ADHD. Both students go to the same technical high school.</p>
<p>But this fall, Norton and Scruggs advocated on opposite sides of a Massachusetts ballot referendum scrapping the requirement that high school kids pass a standardized state test to graduate.</p>
<p>Norton argued that without the high bar of the standard exam, kids like hers won’t have an incentive to strive. But Scruggs maintained that kids with learning disorders also need different types of measurements than standardized tests to qualify for a high school diploma.</p>
<p>Voters last month approved the referendum, 59% to 41%, ending the Massachusetts requirement. There and in most other states, Scruggs’ position against testing is carrying the day.</p>
<p>Just seven states now require students to pass a test to graduate, and one of those — New York — will end its Regents Exam as a requirement by the 2027-28 school year. Florida, Louisiana, New Jersey, Ohio, Texas and Virginia still require testing to graduate, according to the National Center for Fair and Open Testing, a group that opposes such mandates.</p>
<p>In Massachusetts, teachers unions favored getting rid of the exam as a graduation requirement. They argued it forced them to teach certain facts at the expense of in-depth or more practical learning. But many business leaders were in favor of keeping the test, arguing that without it, they will have no guarantee that job applicants with high school diplomas possess basic skills.</p>
<p>State by state, graduation tests have tumbled over the past decade. In 2012, half the states required the tests, but that number fell to 13 states in 2019, <a href="https://www.edweek.org/teaching-learning/why-the-pioneers-of-high-school-exit-exams-are-rolling-them-back/2024/11" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to Education Week</a>. The trend accelerated during the pandemic, when many school districts scrapped the tests during remote learning and some decided to permanently extend test exemptions.</p>
<p>Studies have found that such graduation exams disadvantage students with learning disabilities as well as English language learners, and that they aren’t always a good predictor of success in careers or higher education.</p>
<p>An oft-cited 2010 <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.3102/0034654310383147" target="_blank" rel="noopener">article</a> by researchers at the University of Texas at Austin may have ignited the trend to scrap the tests. Researchers’ review of 46 earlier studies found that high school exit exams “produced few of the expected benefits and have been associated with costs for the most disadvantaged students.”</p>
<p>Some states began to find other ways to assess high school competency, such as grades in mandatory courses, capstone projects or technical milestones.</p>
<p>“Minimum competency tests in the 1980s drove the idea that we need to make sure that students who graduate from high school have the bare minimum of skills,” said John Papay, an associate professor of education at Brown University. “By the mid-2000s, there was a reaction against standardized testing and a movement away from these exams. They disappeared during the pandemic and that led to these tests going away.”</p>
<p>Despite the problems with the tests for English learners and students with learning disabilities, Papay said, the tests are “strong predictors of long-term outcomes. Students who do better on the tests go on to graduate [from] college and they earn more.”</p>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" title="“Computer programs monitor students’ every word in the name of safety” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2024/10/17/computer-programs-monitor-students-every-word-in-the-name-of-safety/embed/#?secret=vOFYyjUPWZ#?secret=k9h6MYFY5j" width="500" height="461" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="k9h6MYFY5j" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>Papay, who remains neutral on whether the tests should be required, pointed out that high school students usually have many opportunities to retake the tests and to appeal their scores.</p>
<p>Anne Hyslop, director of policy development at All4Ed, a think tank and advocacy group for underserved communities, noted that in many states, the testing requirements were replaced by other measures.</p>
<p>The schools “still require some students or all students to demonstrate competency to graduate, but students have many more options on how they could do that. They can pass a dual credit [high school/college] course, pass industry recognized competency tests. …</p>
<p>“A lot of states still have assessments as part of their graduation requirements, but in a much broader form,” she said.</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Massachusetts moves</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Scruggs said her son took Massachusetts’ required exam last spring; he passed the science and math portions but fell 1 point short in English.</p>
<p>“He could do well in his classes, but if he didn’t pass the three tests, he wouldn’t get his regular diploma,” Scruggs said. “How do you go out into the working world, and you went to school every day and passed your classes, but got no diploma?”</p>
<p>Her son has taken the English test again and is awaiting his new score, she said.</p>
<p>Norton, by contrast, said the exam, called the Massachusetts Comprehensive Assessment System, or MCAS, gave her son an incentive to work hard.</p>
<p>“I worry that kids like him … are going to end up graduating from high school without the skills they will need,” Norton said. “Without the test, they will just be passed along. I can’t just trust that my kid is getting the basic level of what he needs. I need a bar set where he will get the level of education he needs.”</p>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" title="“Hotter August days push some schools to delay start dates” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2024/09/10/hotter-august-days-push-some-schools-to-delay-start-dates/embed/#?secret=SY9VDiJCCX#?secret=5ZZuwVgqug" width="500" height="327" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="5ZZuwVgqug" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>Students in Massachusetts still will have to take the MCAS in their sophomore year of high school, and the scores will be used to assess their overall learning. But failing the test won’t be a barrier to graduation beginning with the class of 2025. The state is still debating how — or whether — to replace the MCAS with other types of required courses, evaluations or measurements.</p>
<p>High school students in Massachusetts and most states still have to satisfy other graduation requirements, which usually include four years of English and a number of other core subjects such as mathematics, sciences and social studies. Those requirements vary widely across the country, however, as most are set by individual school districts.</p>
<p>In New York, the State Education Department in 2019 began a multiyear process of rethinking high school graduation requirements and the Regents Exam. The department decided last month to phase out the exit exam and replace it with something called a “Portrait of a Graduate,” including seven areas of study in which a student must establish proficiency. Credit options include capstone projects, work-based learning experiences and internships, as well as academic achievement. Several other states have moved recently to a similar approach.</p>
<p>Harry Feder, executive director of FairTest, an advocacy group that works to limit standardized testing, said course grades do a better job of assessing students’ abilities.</p>
<p>“Standardized tests are poor ways of incentivizing and measuring the kinds of skills and knowledge we should have high school kids focusing on,” Feder said. “You get ‘teaching to the test’ that doesn’t bear much of a relationship to the kinds of things that kids are being asked to do when they go on to college or the workplace.”</p>
<p>Max Page, president of the Massachusetts Teachers Association union, said phrases such as “teaching to the test” disrespect teachers and their ability to know when students have mastered content and competency. The high school tests are first taken in the 10th grade in Massachusetts. If the kids don’t pass, they can retake the exam in the 11th or 12th grade.</p>
<p>“Educators are still evaluating students,” he said. “It’s a mirage to say that everything that a student does in education can be measured by a standardized test in the 10th grade. Education, of course, goes through the 12th grade.”</p>
<p>He added that course grades are still a good predictor of how much a student knows.</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Colorado’s menu</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Several of the experts and groups on both sides of the debate point to Colorado as a blueprint for how to move away from graduation test requirements.</p>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" title="“When ‘universal’ pre-K really isn’t: Barriers to participating abound” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2024/07/03/when-universal-pre-k-really-isnt-barriers-to-participating-abound/embed/#?secret=TCuvlpDPUy#?secret=EjJmLrWSjh" width="500" height="440" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="EjJmLrWSjh" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>Colorado, which made the switch with the graduating class of 2021, now allows school districts to choose from a menu of assessment techniques, such as SAT or ACT scores, or demonstration of workforce readiness in various skill areas.</p>
<p>A state task force created by the legislature recently <a href="https://www.cde.state.co.us/communications/11-8-24-news-release-1241-task-force" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recommended some changes</a> to the education accreditation system to “better reflect diverse student needs and smaller school populations.” They include creating assessments that adapt to student needs, offering multilingual options, and providing quicker results to understand student progress.</p>
<p>The state hopes the menu of assessment options will support local flexibility, said Danielle Ongart, assistant commissioner for student pathways and engagement at the Colorado Department of Education.</p>
<p>“Depending on what the student wants for themselves, they have the ability to show what they know,” she said in an interview. In particular, she said, the menu allows for industry certificates, if a student knows what type of work they want to do. That includes areas such as computer science or quantum computing.</p>
<p>“It allows students to better understand themselves and explain what they can do, what they are good at, and what they want to do,” she said.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Voters in several states support reducing property taxes</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/11/voters-in-several-states-support-reducing-property-taxes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 20:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[property taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax legislation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40799</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Voters in half a dozen states approved ballot issues aimed at lowering property taxes, but a measure in North Dakota that would have completely repealed the property tax proved to be a bridge too far. Ballot measures to cut taxes for some or all property owners passed in Arizona, Florida, Georgia, New Mexico, Virginia and [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="676" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-2024-11-11-at-10.23.34 AM-1024x676.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-2024-11-11-at-10.23.34 AM-1024x676.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-2024-11-11-at-10.23.34 AM-300x198.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-2024-11-11-at-10.23.34 AM-768x507.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-2024-11-11-at-10.23.34 AM-1536x1014.png 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Screenshot-2024-11-11-at-10.23.34 AM.png 1896w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A taxpayer in Virginia gets ready to drop off a property tax payment. Virginia is one of several states that had property tax measures on the ballot this year. (Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)</p><p>Voters in half a dozen states approved ballot issues aimed at lowering property taxes, but a measure in North Dakota that would have completely repealed the property tax proved to be a bridge too far.</p>
<p>Ballot measures to cut taxes for some or all property owners passed in Arizona, Florida, Georgia, New Mexico, Virginia and Wyoming.</p>
<p>But in North Dakota, a coalition made up of police, firefighters, teachers, real estate brokers and many other groups who rely on funding from local governments successfully persuaded voters that scrapping property taxes would cripple local services. The <a href="https://northdakotamonitor.com/2024/11/05/north-dakota-voters-reject-property-tax-ballot-measure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">measure failed</a>.</p>
<p>“North Dakotans are frustrated about property taxes, but Measure 4 was not the way to accomplish reform,” Chad Oban, chair of the Keep It Local coalition, said in a statement. “The coalition’s 113 members were successful in informing North Dakota voters about the dangers of Measure 4. Local officials will continue to work with their constituents to make thoughtful decisions regarding funding and what is best for their communities.”</p>
<p>He suggested the state legislature should take up property tax reform in January.</p>
<p>The proposed constitutional amendment would have prohibited state and local governments from taxing property’s assessed value and required the state legislature to replace the roughly $1.3 billion per year in lost revenue. If it had passed, North Dakota would have become the only state without property taxes, according to the conservative Tax Foundation.</p>
<p>Supporters of the measure had argued that it would restrain government spending and that the legislature had other pots of money to replace the lost revenue.</p>
<p>Former Republican state Rep. Rick Becker, a leader of the referendum drive, told Stateline earlier this year that many residents in his state hate property taxes.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">	<div class="newsroomSidebarContainer ">
	<div class="newsroomSidebar"></span></p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">Property taxes</h4>
<p>States that approved reducing some property taxes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Arizona</li>
<li>Florida</li>
<li>Georgia</li>
<li>New Mexico</li>
<li>Virginia</li>
<li>Wyoming</li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"></div>
	</div>
	</span></p>
<p>“Do you really own your property if the government can take it away?” he said, referring to cases in which people who don’t pay their taxes might face foreclosure on their homes.</p>
<p>Property tax increases across the country have been driven by the increase in home and commercial real estate values, due to inflation and shrinking stock. And experts say because those taxes often arrive in a large lump a couple or so times a year — as opposed to income taxes or sales taxes, which come in dribbles — they tend to leave a bigger impression on taxpayers.</p>
<p>Two proposed property tax initiatives in Colorado — to cut property taxes and to cap the annual growth of the revenue they generate for the state — were withdrawn from the ballot after the legislature, Democratic Gov. Jared Polis and the groups behind the initiatives agreed on compromise legislation. That law reduces property taxes in the next two years by a smaller amount.</p>
<p>In Arizona, the issue was intertwined with homelessness and vagrancy problems. Voters <a href="https://azmirror.com/briefs/ballot-prop-roundup-what-passed-what-failed/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">approved</a> a measure to allow property owners to apply for a property tax refund if their municipality does not enforce laws against illegal camping, loitering, panhandling, public urination, public consumption of alcohol and possession of illegal substances.</p>
<p>Republican supporters argue the measure will force local governments to enforce those bans. But cities objected to the measure, saying it will put them in a difficult legal and fiscal position as they deal with homelessness.</p>
<p>Florida voters backed a measure to give homeowners a bigger tax break as the cost of living increases. It will institute an annual inflation adjustment to the amount of a home’s assessed value eligible for a homestead exemption from the property tax.</p>
<p>Similarly, Georgia voters approved a ballot measure that aims to limit property tax increases when home values rise. It will allow for a statewide homestead exemption that will cap increases in the assessed value of homes, though it allows localities to opt out of the exemption.</p>
<p>New Mexico and Virginia voters overwhelmingly approved ballot measures to extend more property tax breaks to veterans and their surviving spouses.</p>
<p>Wyoming voters passed a measure to set up a new class of property for taxation, allowing the legislature to put owner-occupied primary residences in a separate category from rental property.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some states, including Virginia, want to make it easier to cancel subscriptions</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/23/some-states-including-virginia-want-to-make-it-easier-to-cancel-subscriptions/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 09:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business + Economic Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Federal Trade Commission]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[streaming services]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[subscription services]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40125</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When Tennessee state Rep. Bob Freeman, a Democrat, studied his cable and internet bill last year, he kept seeing recurring charges for app subscriptions he didn’t recognize. Turned out, his 14-year-old daughter had been signing up for subscriptions with introductory rates and never canceling when they rolled over to the full price. “I would question [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/streaming-services.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/streaming-services.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/streaming-services-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/streaming-services-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A screen displays logos for streaming services. States are passing new laws to try to make it harder for companies to automatically renew subscriptions, sometimes at higher prices, without consumers’ knowledge or consent. (Chris McGrath/Getty Images)</p><p>When Tennessee state Rep. Bob Freeman, a Democrat, studied his cable and internet bill last year, he kept seeing recurring charges for app subscriptions he didn’t recognize. Turned out, his 14-year-old daughter had been signing up for subscriptions with introductory rates and never canceling when they rolled over to the full price.</p>
<p>“I would question her bills, and she said, ‘Oh, it’s only $1.99.’ Those were teaser rates,” he said in an interview. To actually cancel, he said, he had to send an email to the company for a follow-up phone call, during which the company representative would try to talk him out of it.</p>
<p>“It was clear it was not meant for convenience. … It was clear it was predatory,” he said.</p>
<p>That experience, plus dealing with his grandmother — who would sign up for apps at $2.99 a month that would then renew for $14 without her knowledge — persuaded him that a new law was needed to ensure greater transparency and consumer protection.</p>
<p>Freeman introduced a bill that would require more notice from companies before subscriptions are automatically renewed.</p>
<p>Originally his bill also would have required companies to get another “yes” from customers — “<a href="https://www.capitol.tn.gov/Bills/113/Bill/HB1832.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">affirmative consent</a>,” in legislative lingo — before charging consumers’ credit or debit cards. But after strong objections from cable and streaming services, Freeman said, the bill was <a href="https://www.capitol.tn.gov/Bills/113/Amend/SA0709.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">amended</a> to eliminate that requirement.</p>
<p>“They got all bent out of shape,” he said of the industry.</p>
<p>In April, Tennessee Republican Gov. Bill Lee signed the <a href="https://publications.tnsosfiles.com/acts/113/pub/pc0835.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">legislation</a>. State law now requires companies to give “clear and conspicuous notice” to consumers if the automatic renewal will occur more than 60 days after the initial sign-up, and mandates that they clearly communicate when they will begin charging for the service.</p>
<p>About half a dozen other states have enacted similar laws this year. Companies that rely on subscriptions say some of the tougher measures will only annoy and confuse consumers.</p>
<p>Navdeep Sahni, an associate professor of marketing at the Stanford Graduate School of Business, said giving consumers more information about automatic renewals and how to cancel is good for business. He said this means consumers would be more open to trying new things and “not get tricked into getting something they don’t want.”</p>
<p>Sahni said businesses only hurt themselves if customers feel burned by the experience.</p>
<p>But earlier this year at a Federal Trade Commission hearing on a proposed federal rule, Michael Powell, president and CEO of NCTA – The Internet &amp; Television Association, warned that many customers might misunderstand the “click to cancel” measures. A customer “may face difficulty and unintended consequences if they want to cancel only one service in the package,” Powell said, because “canceling part of a discounted bundle may increase the price for remaining services.”</p>
<p>Powell added that “three out of four of the cable and broadband customers who called to cancel end up retaining some or all service after speaking with an agent.”</p>
<p>In an email to Stateline, association spokesperson Brian Dietz said the organization would have no further comment on the proposed federal rule or similar state laws.</p>
<p>In Virginia, the <a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?ses=241&amp;typ=bil&amp;val=hb744" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new law</a>, which took effect in July, requires companies to notify consumers of their option to cancel within 30 days of the end of the trial period. The <a href="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/laws/2024/0/Session+Law/Chapter/114/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Minnesota</a> measure, which takes effect Jan. 1, stipulates that companies must give customers the opportunity to cancel via a “simple mechanism,” such as a checkbox or submission button.</p>
<p>And a <a href="https://legiscan.com/CA/text/AB2863/2023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bill</a> sent to California Democratic Gov. Gavin Newsom earlier this month would tighten an already stringent auto-renewal <a href="https://www.dglaw.com/californias-amended-automatic-renewal-law-takes-effect-july-1-2022-what-subscription-based-companies-need-to-know/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">law</a>. Brandon Richards, Newsom’s spokesperson, said the governor has until Sept. 30 to sign or veto the bill.</p>
<p>The laws are designed to help people be more mindful of what they are signing up for. In a March <a href="https://www.cnet.com/personal-finance/subscription-creep-costs-us-consumers-more-than-1000-a-year-cnet-survey-finds/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey</a> by CNET, a consumer-focused website, 48% of respondents said they had signed up for a free trial of a paid subscription and then forgotten to cancel it.</p>
<p>“I’m sure a lot of the time people just don’t get around to [canceling] it,” said Steve Baker, an attorney and former regional director at the Federal Trade Commission. “And they make it hard to cancel. It’s not something you necessarily file a complaint about it. It’s more of a minor annoyance.”</p>
<p>Freeman, the Tennessee lawmaker, said businesses with good products shouldn’t fear the new rules. “If you have a good product, when the teaser rate burns off, [I can subscribe],” he said.</p>
<p>Like Freeman, Utah Republican state Sen. Todd Weiler, who sponsored the auto-renewal bill in his state, was motivated by personal experience. Weiler said he makes a point to record the date when a discounted or free offer expires and full charges kick in.</p>
<p>“I consider myself an intelligent person,” he said. “It’s usually easier to find the cancellation information when you sign up, so I go there and paste it into my calendar. I try to be diligent. But sometimes I still get caught.”</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nearly half the states now allow in-state tuition for immigrant students</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/08/17/nearly-half-the-states-now-allow-in-state-tuition-for-immigrant-students/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2023 04:01:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[higher education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigrants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[in-state tuition]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=36006</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When Cristian Dubon Solis was getting ready to graduate from a Boston high school in 2020, he started planning to apply to college. It was only then he realized that as an immigrant lacking permanent legal status, he wouldn’t qualify for in-state tuition at Massachusetts state universities, nor for state-sponsored financial aid. With no way to [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="742" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Wren_building-scaled-e1692221229229-1024x742.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Wren_building-scaled-e1692221229229-1024x742.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Wren_building-scaled-e1692221229229-300x217.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Wren_building-scaled-e1692221229229-768x557.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Wren_building-scaled-e1692221229229-1536x1114.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Wren_building-scaled-e1692221229229-2048x1485.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Wren building at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. (Sarah Vogelsong / Virginia Mercury)</p><p>When Cristian Dubon Solis was getting ready to graduate from a Boston high school in 2020, he started planning to apply to college. It was only then he realized that as an immigrant lacking permanent legal status, he wouldn’t qualify for in-state tuition at Massachusetts state universities, nor for state-sponsored financial aid.</p>
<p>With no way to afford a four-year school to pursue his dream major, environmental science, he put those plans on hold.</p>
<p>“I took a few gap years afterward,” said the now 21-year-old from East Boston, a community where about half the residents are Hispanic or Latino. Solis now advocates for young immigrants as a student coordinator for a nonprofit group called SIM, which formerly stood for Student Immigration Movement.</p>
<p><i></i>One of four siblings, Solis came to the United States from El Salvador at age 3. His three younger sisters were born in the U.S., he said. Family and friends didn’t discuss their immigration status, so he never heard about the tuition restrictions.</p>
<p>“In families of the immigrant community it’s very hush-hush, you don’t talk about it,” he said. “It’s hard to figure out what options I had or didn’t have, because nobody talked about it.”</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="kSswmiNyrM"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2020/02/12/house-senate-pass-long-anticipated-immigrants-rights-bills/">Virginia House, Senate pass long-anticipated immigrants&#8217; rights bills</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia House, Senate pass long-anticipated immigrants&#8217; rights bills&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2020/02/12/house-senate-pass-long-anticipated-immigrants-rights-bills/embed/#?secret=HlXkcfaRye#?secret=kSswmiNyrM" data-secret="kSswmiNyrM" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>But now Solis is about to apply to colleges in Massachusetts, including UMass-Boston.</p>
<p>Democratic Gov. Maura Healey signed the state budget this month with a provision that will allow certain immigrants without permanent legal status — those who have attended high school in Massachusetts for at least three years or who have earned a GED certificate — to pay in-state tuition rates at public universities. The law takes effect immediately.</p>
<p>The idea has bipartisan appeal, with some conservative supporters this year saying it helps reduce workforce shortages and boost tax revenue.</p>
<p>In June, Nevada Republican Gov. Joe Lombardo enacted <a href="https://www.leg.state.nv.us/App/NELIS/REL/82nd2023/Bill/9961/Overview" target="_blank">a law</a> allowing immigrants who have been granted status under the federal Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals Act, or DACA program, to qualify for in-state tuition after living in Nevada for 12 months. That action expanded on a law that allowed high school graduates lacking permanent legal status to do so.</p>
<p>And in Florida this year, state lawmakers rejected a proposal from Republican Gov. Ron DeSantis to scrap in-state tuition for students without permanent legal status. He had wanted to include it in a bill to <a href="https://floridaphoenix.com/2023/05/02/fl-legislature-approves-anti-immigrant-bill-with-some-of-the-toughest-restrictions-in-decades/" target="_blank">tighten restrictions</a> on immigrants living in the country illegally.</p>
<p>But critics of the in-state tuition changes argue states are facing an influx of immigrants and already are stretched thin to pay for needed housing and services. Missouri Gov. Mike Parson, a Republican, in June signed a 2024 budget that included a boost for higher education funding but prohibited students without permanent legal status from getting in-state tuition or state scholarships.</p>
<p>Massachusetts became the 24th state to grant immigrants without legal status access to in-state tuition, according to the <a href="https://www.higheredimmigrationportal.org/states/" target="_blank">Higher Ed Immigration Portal</a>, a website run by a coalition of 18 higher education and immigration organizations to provide information and resources to immigrant students.</p>
<p>In-state tuition is generally thousands of dollars less per year than for out-of-state students. For example, the undergraduate tuition and fees at Massachusetts state schools averaged $10,036 for state residents and $28,813 for out-of-state residents in the 2022-23 school year, according to College Tuition Compare, a nationwide college evaluation website.</p>
<p>Seventeen of the states granting in-state tuition also allow the students to be eligible for financial aid, as does the District of Columbia, according to the <a href="https://www.higheredimmigrationportal.org/states/" target="_blank">Higher Ed Immigration Portal</a>.</p>
<p>Four states — Delaware, Iowa, Michigan and Pennsylvania — restrict the number of public universities at which immigrants without permanent legal status are eligible for in-state tuition, according to the portal.</p>
<p>Five states — Arkansas, Idaho, Maine, Mississippi and Ohio — provide that tuition discount only to young immigrants who have DACA status. The Obama-era DACA program allows immigrants who were brought to the United States as children and who meet other qualifications to avoid deportation and obtain work permits. New applications for the program are on hold while long-running court battles play out.</p>
    <div class="snrsInfobox">
		<div class="snrsInfoboxContainer">
			<div class="snrsInfoboxSubContainer" style="padding-top:24px;">
				
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Virginia laws </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?201+sum+HB1547" target="_blank">House Bill 1547</a> and <a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?201+sum+SB935" target="_blank">Senate Bill 935</a>, passed in 2020, extend in-state tuition to students in Virginia &#8220;regardless of their citizenship or immigration status&#8221; as long as they meet certain criteria, including attending high school in the state for at least two years and submitting evidence that they or their parent or guardian has filed income tax returns at least two years prior to registration or enrollment.</p>
<p><a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?212+sum+HB2123" target="_blank">House Bill 2123</a> and <a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?212+sum+SB1387" target="_blank">Senate Bill 1387</a>, passed in 2021, allow students who meet the criteria for in-state tuition regardless of immigration or citizenship status to also be eligible for financial assistance.</p>
			</div>
		</div>
    </div>

	
<p>By contrast, nine states specifically block access to in-state tuition or state financial aid for residents lacking permanent legal status, the immigration portal found. They are: Indiana, Missouri, New Hampshire, North Carolina, Tennessee, Wisconsin, Alabama, Georgia and South Carolina. The last three have laws that prevent students without permanent legal status from even enrolling in all or some public colleges, though there may be some exceptions for students with DACA status, according to the portal.</p>
<p>Opponents of extending in-state tuition argue that scarce state resources should not be spent on immigrants living in the country illegally, particularly when states are dealing with a wave of new immigrant families that strains the states’ safety net.</p>
<p>While the Massachusetts law garnered wide support in the Democratic-controlled state, some Republican opponents pointed out that the Healey administration recently called for the federal government to speed funding to provide shelter and services for immigrants in the state and encouraged state residents to take families into their homes.</p>
<p>“It’s the wrong priority at this date and time,” said Republican state Sen. Ryan Fattman in an interview with Stateline. “The governor declared a state of emergency for migrant influx into the state. We have a lot of shelters that are overrun. [At the same time,] we are providing a lot of benefits to people who are not lawfully in Massachusetts, in-state tuition being one of them.</p>
<p>“The question is can we continue to afford this?” Fattman said.</p>
<p>But advocates for granting in-state tuition say the state must educate young immigrants if it wants to make up for the number of residents who are leaving the state and taking tax revenue with them. Massachusetts lost 110,900 people to out-migration from April 2020 to July 2022, according to the Massachusetts Taxpayers Foundation, a nonpartisan research group. In-migration in 2022 was about 43,000, the organization found.</p>
<p>“What Massachusetts did is good for the people of Massachusetts, it’s good for the ‘Dreamers’ who get a chance to go to school and pay in-state tuition,” said Don Graham, a founder of TheDream.Us, an organization that gives scholarships to students who came to the U.S. illegally before age 16 and before Nov. 1, 2017. (“Dreamers” refers to young people brought to the United States illegally as children by family; the term stems from never-passed congressional legislation called the DREAM Act.)</p>
<p>“They become a health care worker, they become a teacher, they become a computer programmer. Seems to me that’s good for the ‘Dreamers’ and good for the state,” said Graham, who also is chair of the board of the Graham Holdings Company and former publisher of The Washington Post.</p>
<p>Miriam Feldblum, co-founder and executive director of the Presidents’ Alliance on Higher Education and Immigration, a group comprised of university leaders, said consideration of in-state tuition for students without legal status has become increasingly important in light of the U.S. Supreme Court’s recent decision to end affirmative action programs on campuses.</p>
<p>“As colleges and universities look at how to attract diverse populations, it is incumbent upon all institutions to look at immigrant students,” she said in an interview with Stateline. “It is one important strategy to attract a diverse and talented crop of students.”</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Virginia Mercury within States Newsroom, a nonprofit news network supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott S. Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a>. Follow Stateline on <a href="https://facebook.com/statelinenewsroom" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" target="_blank">Twitter</a>.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Students blocked from campus when COVID hit want money back. Some are getting refunds.</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/08/10/students-blocked-from-campus-when-covid-hit-want-money-back-some-are-getting-refunds/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 20:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[college closures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COVID litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covid-19]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=35961</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thousands of college students will get hundreds of dollars in compensation as colleges and universities move this summer to settle multimillion-dollar lawsuits stemming from canceled classes and activities during COVID-19 pandemic shutdowns. While some of the class-action suits against the colleges and universities are still in litigation, and still others dismissed, several major cases have [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/0903_vm_vcu_masks_05-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">People wear masks on the VCU campus in Richmond, Va., September 3, 2020. Parker Michels-Boyce for the Virginia Mercury</p><p>Thousands of college students will get hundreds of dollars in compensation as colleges and universities move this summer to settle multimillion-dollar lawsuits stemming from canceled classes and activities during COVID-19 pandemic shutdowns.</p>
<p>While some of the class-action suits against the colleges and universities are still in litigation, and still others dismissed, several major cases have been settled in recent weeks.</p>
<p>The settlements mean students who were charged tuition and fees but weren’t able to use in-person services during the pandemic shutdowns will receive some compensation, though they won’t be refunded for all the on-campus amenities they lost.</p>
<p>The amounts depend on the total settlement figure, minus legal fees and other court expenses. Each case has a different timeline.</p>
<p>Most recently, the University of Delaware agreed in June to set up a $6.3 million fund to partially reimburse tuition and fees that the students paid for classes, housing and activities in 2020. The students argued that they did not receive the full benefit of in-person participation in academics and extracurricular activities. Each student is expected to receive <a href="https://www.delawareonline.com/story/news/local/2023/06/14/university-of-delaware-students-covid19-lawsuit-payments-settlement-remote-learning/70317763007/" target="_blank">several hundred dollars in cash</a> as part of the agreement.</p>
<p>But the university did not admit wrongdoing and maintained that extenuating circumstances of the pandemic, and the lack of an official contract between the school and each student, meant it was justified in taking the tuition and fees — an argument made by many other schools.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="GzhrSvjH5B"><p><a href="https://stateline.org/2020/06/02/college-students-want-their-money-back-itll-be-tough-to-get-it/" target="_blank">College Students Want Their Money Back. It&#8217;ll Be Tough to Get It.</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;College Students Want Their Money Back. It&#8217;ll Be Tough to Get It.&#8221; &#8212; Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2020/06/02/college-students-want-their-money-back-itll-be-tough-to-get-it/embed/#?secret=0wLIPbB3vl#?secret=GzhrSvjH5B" data-secret="GzhrSvjH5B" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Many universities also have argued that they incurred significant expense in making the almost immediate transition to online classes. In interviews with Stateline, attorneys for some schools argued that the students’ argument was undercut by the fact that many chose to remain in remote classes after the campuses reopened, for convenience or health concerns.</p>
<p>Florida attorney Mendy Halberstam, who was not involved in the Delaware case but who represents other universities that have been similarly sued, said in an interview that the schools feel compelled to defend themselves against cases they believe “are lacking in merit.”</p>
<p>“They are not looking to make life difficult for their students,” he said, “but they also have to make sure of their [lack of] liability.”</p>
<p>There have been about 300 such lawsuits, according to <a href="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/leading-us-universities-settle-covid-online-teaching-lawsuits" target="_blank">Times Higher Education,</a> a British publication that partners with The Wall Street Journal on rankings and evaluations of U.S. schools.</p>
<p>The University of Colorado, for example, <a href="https://www.denverpost.com/2023/04/19/university-of-colorado-class-action-lawsuit-2020-5-million/" target="_blank">settled a similar class-action case</a> in April for $5 million.</p>
<p>Attorney Igor Raykin, who represented the Colorado students, said the settlement was “a reasonable offer given the challenges of the suit itself and the legal landscape in general.”</p>
<p>Among the challenges, Raykin said, is the fact that these were precedent-setting cases and that a lengthy legal process meant many of the students have already graduated and gotten on with their lives.</p>
<p>“We wanted to make sure the students would be getting something that would benefit them.” Individual awards will vary, he said, but typically will be in the hundreds of dollars.</p>
<p>In May, the University of Minnesota <a href="https://www.twincities.com/2023/06/01/umn-students-to-get-bigger-refunds-from-pandemic-semester-as-class-action-lawsuit-settles/" target="_blank">also settled a class-action lawsuit</a> allowing students to get bigger refunds of tuition and fees than the school initially allowed. And in June, a judge <a href="https://www.hbsslaw.com/sites/default/files/case-downloads/tuition-university-of-washington/2023-06-28-order-granting-class-certification.PDF" target="_blank">certified</a> a group of students in a class-action suit against the University of Washington.</p>
<p>However, early this year a judge in Rhode Island <a href="https://www.providencejournal.com/story/news/courts/2023/02/04/judge-dismisses-students-covid-claims-against-university-of-rhode-island/69870262007/" target="_blank">dismissed a case</a> against the University of Rhode Island and several other schools in that state, <a href="https://www.brown.edu/sites/default/files/order-03-04-21-web-small.pdf" target="_blank">ruling</a> that there were no enforceable contracts breached in the shutdowns. The plaintiffs argued that the shutdowns denied them university experiences they expected, based on the schools’ marketing materials, websites, course catalogs, student handbooks and the like.</p>
<p>But U.S. District Judge John McConnell Jr. ruled that, “unfortunately for [the] plaintiffs, these general advertisements and distinctions do not create obligations on the part of the university — they are vague and more akin to puffery, rather than enforceable promises.”</p>
<p>Two weeks ago, the Florida Supreme Court <a href="https://acis-api.flcourts.gov/courts/68f021c4-6a44-4735-9a76-5360b2e8af13/cms/case/0cbc501c-e5e1-44a0-9b8b-0781e2a31586/docketentrydocuments/2c17d27a-4160-48cf-a0fd-8bd31d9ec0aa" target="_blank">announced</a> it would consider a class-action suit from University of Florida students asking for compensation for being denied services during the COVID-19 shutdown.</p>
<p>But in another Florida case, the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals <a href="https://media.ca11.uscourts.gov/opinions/pub/files/202310299.pdf" target="_blank">upheld</a> a ruling from a lower court dismissing a student’s lawsuit against the University of Miami, a private school.</p>
<p>The university refunded pro-rated fees for housing, dining, student centers and gyms. The student argued that wasn’t enough, but the court ruled that she was “not entitled to damages stemming from any alleged breach of contract, unjust enrichment, or inadequate refunds on the part of Miami.”</p>
<p>“The pandemic forced students of all ages to learn from behind their computer screens for a period of time, and we certainly harbor a great deal of sympathy for those students whose educations and relationships were affected by the transition,” the court wrote. “We hope that some comfort can be found, however, in our certainty that despite enduring the hardships created by the pandemic, any student who has earned a degree from a school like the University of Miami retains the unspoiled potential for a fulfilling and prosperous future.”</p>
<p>Florida attorney Jeffrey Ostrow, who represented students in a lawsuit against Barry University, a private school in Miami, said the cases have been “a mixed bag all over the place.” In one of the earliest settlements, Barry University in September 2021 <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.flsd.570668/gov.uscourts.flsd.570668.84.0.pdf" target="_blank">agreed to set up a $2.4 million</a> compensation fund for students.</p>
<p>Ostrow maintains that universities did enter contracts for in-person learning and campus activities.</p>
<p>“All these students signed up for a program in class,” he said, noting that schools often charged less for online classes before the pandemic. “Whether [the university] was forced to, or decided unilaterally to shut those things down, it’s not fair for them to keep the [in-class payments].”</p>
<p>He also noted that many schools got pandemic relief payments from the federal government to help them weather the pandemic.</p>
<p>“There was federal money that a lot of the schools were able to get,” Ostrow said. “And we believe that money should have gone back to the students.”</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Virginia Mercury within States Newsroom, a nonprofit news network supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott S. Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a>. Follow Stateline on <a href="https://facebook.com/statelinenewsroom" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" target="_blank">Twitter</a>.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Plagued by teacher shortages, some states turn to fast-track credentialing</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/07/24/plagued-by-teacher-shortages-some-states-turn-to-fast-track-credentialing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 19:48:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fast-track credentials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[iteach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[teacher licensure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[teacher shortages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[virginia board of education]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=35794</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Faced with alarming teacher shortages, Virginia last month agreed to partner with a for-profit online teacher credentialing company, hoping to get more teachers into classrooms faster and without the higher tuition costs of traditional colleges and universities. While some of the Virginia education board members had qualms about the process, they agreed to give it [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="680" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/teacher-training_Stateline_AP-1024x680.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/teacher-training_Stateline_AP-1024x680.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/teacher-training_Stateline_AP-300x199.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/teacher-training_Stateline_AP-768x510.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/teacher-training_Stateline_AP.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">First grade teacher, Lindsey Land, center, instructs her students during classes at Chimborazo Elementary School Thursday, Nov. 17, 2022, in Richmond, Va. (AP Photo/Steve Helber)</p><p>Faced with alarming teacher shortages, Virginia last month agreed to partner with a for-profit online teacher credentialing company, hoping to get more teachers into classrooms faster and without the higher tuition costs of traditional colleges and universities.</p>
<p>While some of the Virginia education board members had qualms about the process, they agreed to give it a try due to the nagging high teacher vacancy rate. The board unanimously approved a three-year pilot program and partnered with one of the bigger companies in the fast-track credentialing business, iteach.</p>
<p>Such companies pledge they will get a candidate teacher-ready in about a year. The iteach program includes online courses, after which candidates are placed in classrooms, with some supervision and the agreement of the school districts.</p>
<p>According to state statistics, Virginia had more than 3,500 full-time teacher vacancies for the 2022-23 school year, which is about a 4.5% rate, though vacancies in some specialties are higher. The situation was worse than the year before, the statistics showed.</p>
<p>Daniel Gecker, a then-member of the state board of education who voted for the online certification plan, said he agreed only because the program is a three-year pilot and an “opportunity to gather data.”</p>
<p>“We are in the middle of a fairly significant teacher shortage,” Gecker said in an interview. “Having the online-trained teachers is better than having the untrained subs we’ve been having.”</p>
<p>He said that before the COVID-19 pandemic, it probably would have been possible to make up the teacher gap with better retention. “Post-pandemic, the gulf is just too wide; we can’t fill it with better retention and people coming out of school.”</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">We are in the middle of a fairly significant teacher shortage. Having the online-trained teachers is better than having the untrained subs we've been having.</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– Former Virginia Board of Education member Daniel Gecker</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>Virginia is just the latest state to turn to for-profit teacher certification companies in an urgent effort to recruit and train more teachers. The states hope the new paths to certification will help ease the shortages, but critics argue those who take the programs are not as well trained as traditionally credentialed teachers and will do a disservice to young students.</p>
<p>States have other options to address the teacher shortage, including lowering standards to try to bring in more recruits.</p>
<p>Education Week <a href="https://www.edweek.org/teaching-learning/states-relax-teacher-certification-rules-to-combat-shortages/2022/06" target="_blank">reported last year</a> that about a dozen states had relaxed credentialing standards for teachers or were considering doing so. California lawmakers <a href="https://www.ctc.ca.gov/commission/briefing-room/default/press-releases/2021/2021-02" target="_blank">decided in 2021</a> to allow aspiring teachers to eliminate two different exams as long as they had taken courses to address basic skills and the subject matter they intend to teach. Oklahoma enacted <a href="http://www.oklegislature.gov/BillInfo.aspx?Bill=HB3658&amp;Session=2200" target="_blank">a law</a> last year to remove the requirement for a general education exam.</p>
<p>Some states are pressing “temporary” teachers into service. Arizona last year <a href="https://azsbe.az.gov/sites/default/files/1-24-22%20Highlights%20of%20Recent%20State%20Board%20Meeting.pdf" target="_blank">allowed substitute teachers</a> to take full-time positions to address the teacher shortage in that state. In addition, <a href="https://www.azleg.gov/legtext/55leg/2R/laws/0337.htm" target="_blank">a law</a> passed last year allows Arizona teacher candidates working toward a college degree to teach at the same time.</p>
<p>Iteach is working in 11 states, according to its website: Arkansas, Arizona, Florida, Hawaii, Indiana, Louisiana, Nevada, Tennessee, Texas, Virginia and West Virginia. The Mississippi Teacher Licensure Commission, a panel created to evaluate such programs for that state, unanimously recommended iteach as a certification provider at the commission’s meeting July 7. That recommendation now goes to the state board of education.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="390xJmCHYH"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/04/04/virginia-relying-more-heavily-on-provisional-licenses-to-fill-teacher-shortages/">Virginia relying more heavily on provisional licenses to fill teacher shortages</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia relying more heavily on provisional licenses to fill teacher shortages&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/04/04/virginia-relying-more-heavily-on-provisional-licenses-to-fill-teacher-shortages/embed/#?secret=dDW17vxhuA#?secret=390xJmCHYH" data-secret="390xJmCHYH" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Another large company, Teachers of Tomorrow, is working in nine states, though its credentials may be in jeopardy in Texas, where the company has been placed on probation after state regulators found the company misled potential teachers in its advertising, and hadn’t shown that its training was based in research.</p>
<p>Iteach has been accredited by the Council for the Accreditation of Educator Preparation, which credentials traditional educator training colleges. Andrew Rozell, president of certification at iteach, said it is the only for-profit program of its kind so credentialed.</p>
<p>The for-profit companies are separate and different from online university programs, such as Western Governors University or the Southern New Hampshire University, which also have teacher education courses but are not focused on quick credentialing. The for-profit credentialing firms tout their ability to get people into classrooms within a year or 18 months, depending on when they begin.</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Serious need</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Nationwide, teacher shortages are just as bad as in Virginia, particularly in very rural or low-income inner-city school districts. A working paper from Brown University “conservatively” estimated that as of August 2022, there were 36,000 teacher vacancies across the United States.</p>
<p>And the paper noted that those vacancies are not distributed equally. “The vacancy rate per 10,000 students is more than 159 times as high in Mississippi as it is in Missouri,” the authors wrote. The paper <a href="https://www.teachershortages.com/" target="_blank">found a shortage</a> of 0.43 teachers per 10,000 students in Missouri and 68.59 teachers per 10,000 in Mississippi.</p>
<p>By taking the step to help fill the vacancies, the Virginia state education board was following Republican Gov. Glenn Youngkin’s Executive Directive No. 3 to address the teacher shortage, in part by reducing “red tape associated with teacher licensure, while assuring high standards.”</p>
<p>Iteach fills that criteria, according to Youngkin spokesperson Macaulay Porter, in an email to Stateline. “Governor Youngkin fully supports high-quality alternative pathways to becoming a teacher. The State Board of Education rigorously reviewed iteach data to ensure that iteach will provide school divisions with another effective and efficient option for recruiting and preparing new teachers,” Porter wrote.</p>
<p>The iteach method counts on reducing barriers to time and cost, according to Rozell, “without reducing rigor.” It is designed to take about a year to get candidates ready for initial teaching, if they pass state exams.</p>
<p>Then, the newly trained teachers are granted temporary licenses and teach under intermittent observation by iteach professionals who drop into classes, sometimes unannounced. All this occurs with the knowledge of school administrators, who can provide their own support.</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Critics question fast-track credentialing</h4>

	</h4>
<p>But critics contend that iteach and the other programs that turn out teachers quickly are not subject to the same requirements and depth of instruction as teachers who go the traditional path of four undergraduate years, sometimes at least a year getting a master’s degree, and many months of student teaching under nearly constant supervision by a trained teacher.</p>
<p>Heather Peske, president of the National Council on Teacher Quality, a research and advocacy group, said in a phone interview that for-profit online teaching programs are a “blunt instrument” to address teacher shortages. The programs, she said, don’t take into account whether the teachers are qualified for the subjects they will be teaching or whether they will be satisfied with their jobs and stay in the profession or leave after a year or two.</p>
<p>“If you have a fast-track program and your model is entirely online, it begs the question of how they are assuring aspiring teachers get a place to practice … content knowledge and clinical practice,” she said. School districts should tailor recruiting and educating new teachers to the vacancies and needs, she said, which are most often “specialized teachers” such as special education or multi-language learners.</p>
<p>Iteach advertises that its cost for a complete program is $4,399, plus a $99 enrollment fee. Teachers of Tomorrow’s program costs about $5,000.</p>
<p>By contrast, annual average tuition at a four-year institution in education can range from $9,193 at an in-state school to $26,543 at an out-of-state school, according to the website College Tuition Compare, an independent college evaluation site. Elite institutions are higher. Graduate tuition ranges from $10,806 annually to $19,796, the site found.</p>
<p>Iteach’s Rozell said many of the students in his company’s programs are already working in classrooms, as paraprofessionals, aides for special needs kids or in other non-teaching capacities, and already have some idea of classroom management and other skills needed to be a teacher.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="rHpOaCRHHe"><p><a href="https://stateline.org/2022/01/31/teachers-beaten-down-by-staff-shortages-covid/" target="_blank">Teachers &#8216;Beaten Down&#8217; By Staff Shortages, COVID</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Teachers &#8216;Beaten Down&#8217; By Staff Shortages, COVID&#8221; &#8212; Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2022/01/31/teachers-beaten-down-by-staff-shortages-covid/embed/#?secret=GqPdD7t8tf#?secret=rHpOaCRHHe" data-secret="rHpOaCRHHe" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>But Peske said the “grow your own” movement, which takes paraprofessionals or other employees and turns them into teachers, while a good idea, still requires “thoughtful clinical experience to prepare them. The notion that you would rely on candidates themselves to already be in the classrooms or already working with students, that concerns me,” she said.</p>
<p>“Someone could have been a paraprofessional working as an aide to a student with disabilities, but may never have had the experience [learning] about neuro-differences in those students or who may never had had a mentor.”</p>
<p>The American Federation of Teachers, the nation’s largest teachers union, in a <a href="https://www.aft.org/sites/default/files/media/2022/taskforcereport0722.pdf" target="_blank">2022 report</a> called for more rigor in teacher training, not less, criticizing state efforts to lower the qualifications needed to be a teacher.</p>
<p>“[T]here are more alternative and nontraditional ways to become a teacher in the U.S. than ever before, and unfortunately many of them are low quality,” the report said.</p>
<p>The teachers union stressed methods that are reflected in traditional training, saying aspiring teachers should get “extensive” classroom experiences “alongside a skilled practitioner over a significant period,” and “a strong foundation in subject-area content.”</p>
<p>“We cannot put a bandage on the teacher and school staff shortage by cutting corners and lowering the bar for entry,” the report said.</p>
<p>The biggest knock on the swift accreditation companies came in Texas, where Texas Teachers of Tomorrow, also known as A+ Texas Teachers, has been put on probation. The Texas Education Agency <a href="https://tea.texas.gov/about-tea/leadership/state-board-for-educator-certification/sbec-meetings/sbec-2022/dec22-agenda-item-18.pdf" target="_blank">found</a> that the company failed to address numerous deficiencies, including the number of content hours required for teacher candidates, and whether they are evaluated regarding whether their existing skills are “appropriate for the certification sought.” The audit came after complaints from school districts and teacher candidates who utilized the firm, The Dallas Morning News <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/news/education/2023/06/12/how-texas-largest-teacher-prep-company-sought-to-avoid-a-lengthy-legal-battle/" target="_blank">reported</a>.</p>
<p>Attempts to reach Texas Teachers of Tomorrow were unsuccessful.</p>
<p>A University of Texas at Austin College of Education 2021 <a href="https://education.utexas.edu/service-state/texas-educator-preparation-pathways-study/" target="_blank">study</a> of teacher preparation nationally found that in every tested subject, “students do better if they have university-certified teachers,” and that for low-income students, “having a university-certified teacher can offset half or more of the disadvantages that comes from living in poverty.”</p>
<p>In addition, the study showed that university-certified teachers had a 73% retention rate over nine years, while only 59% of “alternatively certified” teachers remained teaching.</p>
<p>But Rozell said that study was skewed because of the problems with Teachers of Tomorrow. He said an internal survey of his company’s students showed that after the first year in the classroom, 93% said “they were excited to be back next year,” and that they planned to be a teacher for at least five years.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Mercury within States Newsroom, a network of news bureaus supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a>. Follow Stateline on <a href="https://facebook.com/stateline_newsroom" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" target="_blank">Twitter</a>.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Campus diversity will be a struggle without race-based admissions, history shows</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/07/10/campus-diversity-will-be-a-struggle-without-race-based-admissions-history-shows/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 04:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Affirmative action]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[affirmative action bans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[higher education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[racial representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=35698</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[States that have tried to enroll more Black and Hispanic students in state universities without using race-based admissions policies have seen the numbers of those students slip — especially at elite institutions. Nine states had affirmative action bans before last week’s U.S. Supreme Court ruling striking it down nationwide. Those states and others have tried [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="912" height="600" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/UVA_rotunda.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/UVA_rotunda.jpg 912w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/UVA_rotunda-300x197.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/UVA_rotunda-768x505.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/UVA_rotunda-696x458.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/UVA_rotunda-638x420.jpg 638w" sizes="(max-width: 912px) 100vw, 912px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Rotunda at the University of Virginia. (Style Weekly)</p><p>States that have tried to enroll more Black and Hispanic students in state universities without using race-based admissions policies have seen the numbers of those students slip — especially at elite institutions.</p>
<p>Nine states had affirmative action bans before last week’s U.S. Supreme Court ruling striking it down nationwide. Those states and others have tried various strategies to maintain diversity without using race-based admissions. They include costly recruitment drives, guaranteed admission to high-ranking high school students and the elimination of preferences for relatives of alumni.</p>
<p>Those strategies have had an impact. But overall, they haven’t been as effective as more explicit race-based preferences, illustrating how difficult it will be to maintain diverse campuses in the wake of last week’s decision.</p>
<p>Arizona, California, Florida, Idaho, Michigan, Nebraska, New Hampshire, Oklahoma and Washington had affirmative action bans in place before the high court ruled.</p>
<p>California, the nation’s largest state and one of its most diverse, has received the most attention.</p>
<p>Shortly after affirmative action ended in California in 1998, state universities began guaranteeing admission to most UC campuses to the top-performing students from most California high schools. The state university system also shifted to a more holistic admissions review process that considered students’ academic achievements “<a href="https://admission.universityofcalifornia.edu/how-to-apply/applying-as-a-freshman/how-applications-are-reviewed.html" target="_blank">in light of the opportunities available to [them].”</a></p>
<p>And California also began spending more on recruitment. In total, the state has spent about a half-billion dollars on more comprehensive reviews and recruiting since the ban was put in place, according to <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/20/20-1199/232355/20220801134931730_20-1199%20bsac%20University%20of%20California.pdf" target="_blank">an amicus brief</a> UC filed in the Supreme Court case. “But funding for these programs has declined over time, and resource constraints limit UC’s ability to expand these programs,” according to the brief.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="KJM02hxV9u"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/06/29/virginia-gop-leaders-praise-affirmative-action-ruling-schools-vow-to-keep-pursuing-diversity/">Virginia GOP leaders praise affirmative action ruling, schools vow to keep pursuing diversity</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia GOP leaders praise affirmative action ruling, schools vow to keep pursuing diversity&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/06/29/virginia-gop-leaders-praise-affirmative-action-ruling-schools-vow-to-keep-pursuing-diversity/embed/#?secret=4e4pk9ATdR#?secret=KJM02hxV9u" data-secret="KJM02hxV9u" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>At the state’s most elite campuses, Berkeley and UCLA, Black and Hispanic enrollment plummeted in the first years after the ban. But Black and Hispanic enrollment fell less dramatically, and recovered more quickly, in the rest of the UC system.</p>
<p>Today, <a href="https://www.universityofcalifornia.edu/about-us/information-center/fall-enrollment-glance" target="_blank">Black enrollment</a> in the UC system as a whole is 4.5%, compared with a statewide population of about 5%. Hispanics are 22.5% of UC students, compared with about 40% of the statewide population.</p>
<p>At Berkeley, Black students were 3.6% of new undergraduates <a href="https://opa.berkeley.edu/uc-berkeley-fall-enrollment-data-new-undergraduates" target="_blank">last fall</a>, while Hispanic students were 21%. <a href="https://admission.ucla.edu/apply/freshman/freshman-profile" target="_blank">At UCLA</a>, 8% percent of new undergraduates were Black, while 22% were Hispanic.</p>
<p>“California has not identified a silver bullet that maintains racial diversity at the same level as race-based affirmative action,” said Zachary Bleemer<a href="https://zacharybleemer.com/" target="_blank">,</a> an assistant professor of economics at Princeton University, who has extensively studied California’s experience.</p>
<p>Bleemer estimates that California’s automatic admission program and its more holistic review process “tend to increase Black and Hispanic enrollment by about a third of what race-based affirmative action would be.”</p>
<p>He added that while states with less-selective schools, such as Oklahoma and Nebraska, have reported that ending affirmative action didn’t have much of an effect on minority enrollment, that’s because “most students were getting in already.”</p>
<p>The Supreme Court ruling will have the greatest impact at “quite selective schools with robust affirmative action programs,” Bleemer said, citing schools such as the University of Virginia, the University of North Carolina, Georgia Tech and the Ohio State University.</p>
<p>Like California, some other states, such as <a href="http://www.collegeforalltexans.com/index.cfm?objectid=24937C2A-D8B0-34EB-1FC5AF875A28C616#:~:text=Top%2010%25%20Rule&amp;text=To%20meet%20the%20requirements%2C%20you,eligible%20to%20pay%20resident%20tuition." target="_blank">Texas</a> and <a href="https://www.fldoe.org/core/fileparse.php/7754/urlt/Talented-Twenty-Presentation-PDF.pdf" target="_blank">Florida</a>, have implemented automatic admission programs for top-performing students.</p>
<p>Texas implemented its Top 10% Plan after the 5th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in 1996 banned affirmative action in college admissions in Louisiana, Mississippi and Texas. In 2003, the Supreme Court nullified that decision, freeing Texas universities to consider race again. But Texas kept its plan in place.</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">The Supreme Court ruling will have the greatest impact at “quite selective schools with robust affirmative action programs,” Bleemer said, citing schools such as the University of Virginia, the University of North Carolina, Georgia Tech and the Ohio State University.</p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>The idea behind the plan is that since many Texas high schools are mostly Black or Hispanic, offering automatic admission to many state universities for the top 10% of students from every Texas high school would boost diversity at those schools.</p>
<p>But <a href="https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w28280/w28280.pdf" target="_blank">a 2020 working paper </a>examining 18 years of data from Texas found that the program “did not result in meaningful changes” in which high schools in the state sent students to the flagship state universities, the University of Texas at Austin and Texas A&amp;M. As a result, it had little impact on the racial diversity of the two schools.</p>
<p>“The purported high school representation benefits of the policy appear to be overstated and may not go as far as advocates might have hoped in terms of generating equity of access to the flagship campuses in the state,” the paper concluded.</p>
<p>In 2020, the <a href="https://data.highered.texas.gov/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/08/2021-Texas-Public-Higher-Education-Almanac.pdf" target="_blank">student population</a> at UT-Austin was 24.2% Hispanic, compared with 40% of the <a href="https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/TX/RHI225222" target="_blank">state population</a>. The Black student percentage was 5.3%, compared with a Black state population of 13.4%.</p>
<div class="halfwidth">
<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer ">
<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">Florida’s <a href="https://www.fldoe.org/core/fileparse.php/7754/urlt/Talented-Twenty-Presentation-PDF.pdf" target="_blank">Talented Twenty program</a>, launched in 1999, grants automatic admission to one of a dozen state institutions to students who graduate in the top 20% of their class, regardless of SAT or ACT scores. The data on the success of the program is mixed.</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>From 1999 to 2007, the share of Black freshmen at the University of Florida increased from 11% to 14%, and the overall percentage of Black undergraduates increased from 7% to 10%. But at Florida State University, the percentage of Black students declined from 11% to 9%, and it dropped from 13% to 12% at the University of South Florida, according to statistics <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/news/education/2023/06/29/florida-race-college-admissions-supreme-court-jeb-bush-affirmative-action/" target="_blank">cited recently by the Tampa Bay Times</a>.</p>
<p>In 1999, Hispanics made up 16% of public high school seniors and 14% of university freshmen. In 2008, those numbers were 22% and 18%, respectively.</p>
<p>But in past decades, Black and Hispanic students have become increasingly underrepresented at state universities.</p>
<p>In the spring of 2021, 20% of seniors in Florida public high schools were Black. That fall, they made up 10% of freshmen at Florida’s 12 public universities. From 2010 to 2021, the share of Black freshmen at the University of Florida fell from 9% to under 5%. The percentage fell from 11.5% to 7.2% at the University of South Florida, the Times said.</p>
<p>Michigan voters in 2006 approved <a href="https://www.michigan.gov/-/media/Project/Websites/sos/01luck/ED138_State_Prop_1106.pdf?rev=b0ec6267905e4406b42e9f8fc582d729" target="_blank">a constitutional amendment</a> prohibiting state colleges and universities from granting “preferential treatment to groups or individuals based on their race, gender, color, ethnicity or national origin.” In an <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/20/20-1199/232447/20220801155455154_Nos.%2020-1199%2021-707%20U-M%20amicus%20ISO%20resps..pdf" target="_blank">amicus brief</a> filed in the Supreme Court case, the University of Michigan said that since then it has “discontinued even the limited consideration of race in holistic admissions programs.”</p>
<p>Instead, the university has employed what it described as “persistent, vigorous, and varied efforts to increase student-body racial and ethnic diversity by race-neutral means” — with limited success.</p>
<div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer"></div>
<p>Michigan did not pursue a percentage plan like California, Florida and Texas; except for the Detroit area, there are relatively few majority-minority schools in the state. But it did continue to give a leg up to applicants from socioeconomically disadvantaged backgrounds and those who were the first in their family to go to college. It also bolstered recruiting and outreach by, among other things, hosting workshops for high-school counselors, maintaining a recruiting office in Detroit and coordinating campus visits.</p>
<p>Before the ban took effect, underrepresented minorities were about 13% of Michigan undergraduates. That percentage declined to less than 11% in 2014. The current share is about 13.5%, slightly above the pre-ban percentage. However, it is a different story for specific groups, including African Americans.</p>
<p>Black enrollment has declined from 7% in 2006 to roughly 4% in 2021, a reduction of 44%. During the same period, the total percentage of college-aged Black people in Michigan increased from 16% to 19%. And Native American enrollment is down by 90%, according to the university.</p>
<p>“The University’s persistent efforts have not been sufficient to create the racial diversity necessary to provide significant opportunities for personal interaction to dispel stereotypes and to ensure that minority students do not feel isolated or that they must act as spokespersons for their race,” the brief stated.</p>
<p>While affirmative action opponents are cheering last week’s ruling, advocates are now focused on how to boost minority enrollment without it.</p>
<p>Jessie Ryan, executive vice president at the Campaign for College Opportunity, an advocacy group that aims to give all Californians the opportunity to go to college, said the focus must now be on high school preparation for higher learning.</p>
<p>“We will continue to advocate for scaling high-impact practices that result in greater racial equity,” she said in an email, including access to college preparation curriculum, universal completion of financial aid forms, and test-optional admissions policies.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Mercury within States Newsroom, a network of news bureaus supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a>. Follow Stateline on <a href="https://facebook.com/stateline_newsroom" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" target="_blank">Twitter</a>.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More states use taxpayer dollars to help people pay for private school</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/06/16/more-states-use-taxpayer-dollars-to-help-people-pay-for-private-school/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elaine S. Povich]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>epovich@stateline.org (Elaine S. Povich)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 04:07:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EdChoice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education legislation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education vouchers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lab schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[private schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia students]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=35532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic, during which parents and educators reevaluated their relationship with public schools, lawmakers across the country have eagerly embraced state-funded voucher programs, giving public money to students to attend private schools. So far this year, at least 10 states have implemented or expanded programs for vouchers and other state [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Reynolds-scaled-e1686818076677-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Reynolds-scaled-e1686818076677-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Reynolds-scaled-e1686818076677-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Reynolds-scaled-e1686818076677-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Reynolds-scaled-e1686818076677.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Iowa Gov. Kim Reynolds greets school children before signing a bill that creates education savings accounts, Tuesday, Jan. 24, 2023, at the Statehouse in Des Moines, Iowa. Any Iowa student who wants to attend a private school could use public money to pay for tuition or other expenses under the plan approved early Tuesday by the Legislature, making the state the third to pass a measure that allows such spending with few restrictions. (AP Photo/Charlie Neibergall)</p><p>In the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic, during which parents and educators reevaluated their relationship with public schools, lawmakers across the country have eagerly embraced state-funded voucher programs, giving public money to students to attend private schools.</p>
<p>So far this year, at least 10 states have implemented or expanded programs for vouchers and other state private education subsidies, according to <a href="https://chalkboardreview.com/school-choice-measures-state-law-education/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chalkboard Review</a>, an education-focused website. The states are: Arizona, Florida, Idaho, Indiana, Montana, Nebraska, Oklahoma, South Carolina and Utah, along with a pilot program in Tennessee.</p>
<p>But in North Dakota, the Republican governor vetoed such a plan, and bills failed in California, Georgia, Illinois, Kansas, Texas and Virginia.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="Nl9BUvtbsl"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/02/07/education-savings-account-bills-fail-in-both-house-and-senate/">Education savings account bills fail in both House and Senate</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Education savings account bills fail in both House and Senate&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/02/07/education-savings-account-bills-fail-in-both-house-and-senate/embed/#?secret=K2tTvAhGwY#?secret=Nl9BUvtbsl" data-secret="Nl9BUvtbsl" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>There are currently voucher and similar programs in 32 states and the District of Columbia, according to EdChoice, a free-market organization that promotes public money for private education. Voucher programs often are characterized in state legislation as “scholarship programs,” but whatever the name, the policies result in a transfer of public money to private institutions. Some even subsidize home-schooling.</p>
<p>Some states are establishing what they call “education savings accounts.” The state puts money in such accounts for every student under 18, allowing parents to spend it on public, private, religious or home-schooling costs.</p>
<p>Some programs have seen extensive growth: Indiana’s private school voucher program <a href="https://indianacapitalchronicle.com/2023/06/14/indianas-school-choice-program-grew-20-percent-last-year-with-more-growth-coming/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-stringify-link="https://indianacapitalchronicle.com/2023/06/14/indianas-school-choice-program-grew-20-percent-last-year-with-more-growth-coming/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">grew by 20%</a> in the past school year, its largest boost in a decade. And in Arizona, a voucher program projected to cost $65 million in the coming school year <a href="https://www.azmirror.com/2023/06/01/arizona-school-voucher-program-growth-explodes-to-900-million-for-the-upcoming-school-year/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-stringify-link="https://www.azmirror.com/2023/06/01/arizona-school-voucher-program-growth-explodes-to-900-million-for-the-upcoming-school-year/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">is now estimated</a> at more than $900 million because of an expected spike in applicants.</p>
<p>Some of the Republicans pushing the programs claim broad public support for them. But recent polls suggest that people’s opinions shift depending on the specific details of the program, the phrasing of the questions and who is asking them.</p>
<p>Polls funded by pro-voucher advocacy groups or state Republican parties show the public in many states favoring them. Polls commissioned by Democratic-leaning teachers unions often show the public opposed.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, a Reuters/Ipsos poll <a href="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2023-03/Reuters%20Ipsos%20Large%20Sample%20Survey%20Issues%20Poll%20March%202023%20Topline%2003%2024%202023.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-stringify-link="https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2023-03/Reuters%20Ipsos%20Large%20Sample%20Survey%20Issues%20Poll%20March%202023%20Topline%2003%2024%202023.pdf" data-sk="tooltip_parent">in March</a> found that 36% of respondents supported vouchers and 51% opposed them when they were asked if they supported “[l]aws allowing government money to send students to private and religious schools, even if it reduces money for public schools.”</p>
<p>“It’s going to continue to be a real focus in the legislative process in a lot of places for some time to come,” said Norín Dollard, senior policy analyst at the Florida Policy Institute, a progressive think tank that opposes vouchers.</p>
<p>Several Republican-dominated states pushed ahead with voucher programs this year.</p>
<p>Florida Republican Gov. Ron DeSantis, who is running for president, signed a bill in March establishing a voucher program for any family, regardless of income. The allocation per student is expected to be about $8,000 a year — more than some private schools were charging for annual tuition.</p>
<p>As a result, some private schools raised their prices. At least one Catholic school, after deciding to raise tuition, reversed course in the face of parents’ objections when the <em>Tampa Bay Times</em> <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/news/education/2023/05/30/floridas-new-voucher-law-allows-private-schools-boost-revenue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported</a> the decision. The newspaper reported some other schools are sticking with the decision to raise tuition, but did not name them.</p>
<p>Dollard said she did not know which schools in Florida were moving forward with plans to increase their rates.</p>
<p>But she said in a phone interview that her group would continue to oppose the voucher system because, she argues, many schools in Florida don’t have enough money now. According to one recent analysis, Florida <a href="https://worldpopulationreview.com/state-rankings/per-pupil-spending-by-state" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ranks 44th</a> among the states in per-pupil spending.</p>
<p>“If those schools had been properly funded to begin with, we might not be in the situation where students are inclined to leave public schools,” she said. “Public schools serve the public good.”</p>
<p>An annual Gallup poll on education trends <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/1612/education.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shows</a> 55% of respondents last year were unhappy with K-12 education in the United States, up from 48% in 2020.</p>
<p>Robert Enlow, president of EdChoice, said the organization thinks it’s “fair and more equitable for money to follow families than to have the money follow one type of school. [Families] shouldn’t have to pay twice, once in taxes and once in tuition. Why is that fair?”</p>
<p>In Iowa, more than 17,500 parents already have applied to join the state’s new education savings accounts, thousands more than state officials had budgeted for, <a href="https://www.desmoinesregister.com/story/news/politics/2023/06/14/education-savings-account-iowa-private-schools-scholarships-tuition-fees-not-all-approved/70317629007/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according</a> to the <em>Des Moines Register</em>. Families have until the end of June to sign up; it’s unclear how the state will fund all the applicants.</p>
<p>Republican Gov. Kim Reynolds’ success in pushing the school choice program through the legislature came arguably as a result of her work last fall to elect new, pro-voucher Republican lawmakers after a voucher bill had previously failed. As was the case in Florida, several private religious schools in Iowa <a href="https://www.kcrg.com/2023/04/20/amid-efforts-make-private-schools-affordable-handful-schools-increase-tuition-prices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raised their tuition</a> after the measure there passed.</p>
<p>In Utah, Republican Gov. Spencer Cox in January signed into law a measure that will spend $42 million to set up a statewide universal voucher program. The law gives out $8,000 per student to pay private school tuition. The state’s largest teachers union, the Utah Education Association, said it would challenge the law in court.</p>
<p>Most of the efforts to set up or expand voucher programs have come in conservative-led states. But some supporters are liberal groups representing underserved communities who are fed up with low-performing public schools.</p>
<p>In Maryland, Gov. Wes Moore, a Democrat and the state’s first Black governor, faced a barrage of criticism earlier this year when he called for cutting back the state’s small voucher program for some underprivileged kids. Some of the criticism came from liberal Black organizations in Baltimore upset over decades of public school deficiencies in the city and parents who wanted their kids to be afforded something different.</p>
<p>Writing in the <em>Baltimore Afro-American</em>, Ralph E. Moore Jr., a longtime Baltimore educator and activist, supported students and others who descended on Annapolis to protest the governor’s proposal.</p>
<p>“Wouldn’t it be fair to continue to let some low-income children have an otherwise unreachable private school experience?” he wrote. “And even though private educational institutions do not pay state (property or sales) taxes, their operations reduce the number of children that state government would be responsible for educating by federal and state law.”</p>
<p>Rather than cut the program by $2 million as Gov. Moore proposed, the Maryland legislature, in a compromise, added $1 million back as part of the state’s budget.</p>
<p>Despite the defeat, Gov. Moore is not giving up on his plan to cut back on the program.</p>
<p>“I still believe that public funding should go to public education,” he said in an email to <em>Stateline</em>. “I respect the General Assembly’s position on providing more funding for the program in the FY23 budget.”</p>
<p>American Federation of Teachers-Maryland President Kenya Campbell, in an email to <em>Stateline</em>, supported the governor’s efforts, calling the voucher program, known as BOOST, “unproven, discriminatory and wasteful.”</p>
<p><i data-stringify-type="italic">This story </i><i data-stringify-type="italic"><a class="c-link c-link--underline" href="https://stateline.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://stateline.org/" data-sk="tooltip_parent">first appeared in Stateline</a></i><i data-stringify-type="italic">, which along with the Virginia Mercury is part of States Newsroom, a network of news bureaus supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott Greenberger for questions: </i><i data-stringify-type="italic"><a class="c-link c-link--underline" href="mailto:info@stateline.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="mailto:info@stateline.org" data-sk="tooltip_parent" aria-haspopup="menu" aria-expanded="false">info@stateline.org</a></i><i data-stringify-type="italic">. Follow Stateline on </i><i data-stringify-type="italic"><a class="c-link c-link--underline" href="https://facebook.com/stateline_newsroom" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://facebook.com/stateline_newsroom" data-sk="tooltip_parent">Facebook</a></i><i data-stringify-type="italic"> and </i><i data-stringify-type="italic"><a class="c-link c-link--underline" href="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" data-sk="tooltip_parent">Twitter</a></i><i data-stringify-type="italic">.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
