<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Waynesboro Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/place/waynesboro/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/place/waynesboro/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 13:56:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Waynesboro Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/place/waynesboro/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Waynesboro voters sue to block election board’s potential refusal to certify 2024 results</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/waynesboro-voters-sue-to-block-election-boards-potential-refusal-to-certify-2024-results/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 13:56:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Courts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elections and Voting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lawsuit]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=40507</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Five Waynesboro voters have filed a lawsuit to prevent the majority of the Waynesboro Board of Elections from following through on their controversial pledge to refuse certification of the November 2024 election results, a move they argue would violate Virginia state law.  The plaintiffs — Jennifer Lewis, Ann Criser-Shedd, Greg Fife, Chris Graham and Andrea [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0005.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Voters at a polling station in Buckingham County, Nov. 3, 2020. (Parker Michels-Boyce/For the Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Five Waynesboro voters have filed a lawsuit to prevent the majority of the Waynesboro Board of Elections from following through on their controversial pledge to refuse certification of the November 2024 election results, a move they argue would violate Virginia state law. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The plaintiffs — Jennifer Lewis, Ann Criser-Shedd, Greg Fife, Chris Graham and Andrea Jackson — are seeking a court order to compel the election officials to certify the city’s votes.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://advancementproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/2024.10.21-Waynesboro-Complaint-File-Stamped.pdf" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The lawsuit</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, filed in Waynesboro Circuit Court on Oct. 21, comes after two GOP officials from Waynesboro  filed </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/15/waynesboro-gop-officials-sue-over-va-s-voting-system-threaten-to-block-election-certification/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">their own lawsuit</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> challenging Virginia’s voting system ahead of the Nov. 5 presidential election while threatening to not certify the results.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In their complaint, Curtis Lilly, the chairman of the Waynesboro Electoral Board, and Scott Mares, the board’s vice chair, expressed their concerns over the reliability of electronic voting systems, which they argue are prone to inaccuracies. Instead, they demanded that all ballots be counted by hand. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, state law does not currently require a mandatory hand-count unless irregularities are proven, and all paper ballots are required to be counted by optical scanning machines, which help speed up the counting process and reduce the risk of human error. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Before each election, the scanners undergo rigorous testing using a predetermined sample of votes to ensure accurate tallying before any real votes are counted. Additionally, it is illegal to connect ballot scanning machines to the Internet at any point, further safeguarding the integrity of the voting process.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All of the scanners used in Virginia’s elections are certified to meet both state and federal standards and are handled under a strict chain of custody to ensure security and accuracy.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In their counter-suit, the five Waynesboro voters ask the court to require the election officials to certify the election results unless they prevail in their own suit. The plaintiffs further argue that the election officials’ stance violates the Virginia Constitution, which mandates that election results be certified in accordance with established procedures, including the use of legally authorized voting equipment.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The chairman and vice chairman should do their job; instead they are purposely misinterpreting what they are charged to do. I cast my vote and have every right to expect that it will be counted on Election Day,” said Lewis, one of the plaintiffs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jackson, another plaintiff, said that voting in the 2024 election was “very important” to her. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I am frustrated that the election officials are not doing what they take an oath to do, which is to make sure the election runs smoothly and every vote counts. Instead they are distracting us from our local elections by filing nonsensical court cases,” Jackson said. </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Waynesboro GOP officials sue over Va.’s voting system, threaten to block election certification</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/15/waynesboro-gop-officials-sue-over-va-s-voting-system-threaten-to-block-election-certification/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 21:02:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Courts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elections and Voting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ballot scanners]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia Department of Elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia State Board of Elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[voting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[voting machines]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40411</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two GOP officials from Waynesboro have filed a lawsuit challenging Virginia&#8217;s voting system ahead of the Nov. 5 presidential election while threatening to not certify the results. In their complaint, Curtis Lilly, the chairman of the Waynesboro Electoral Board, and Scott Mares, the board’s vice chair, are raising concerns about the validity of future results [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1107-va-election-08-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1107-va-election-08-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1107-va-election-08-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1107-va-election-08-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1107-va-election-08-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/1107-va-election-08-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Voters fill out their ballots at Nuckols Farm Elementary School in Henrico County, Va., November 7, 2023. (Parker Michels-Boyce for the Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Two GOP officials from Waynesboro have filed a lawsuit challenging Virginia&#8217;s voting system ahead of the Nov. 5 presidential election while threatening to not certify the results.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In their complaint, Curtis Lilly, the chairman of the Waynesboro Electoral Board, and Scott Mares, the board’s vice chair, are raising concerns about the validity of future results while echoing unmerited claims that the 2020 election, in which Democrat Joe Biden defeated then-President Donald Trump with more than 7 million votes, was stolen.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Filed on Oct. 4 at the Waynesboro Circuit Court against Virginia Department of Elections Commissioner Susan Beals and State Board of Elections Chairman John O’Bannon, the suit alleges that the voting machines used in the state are unverifiable and could potentially be manipulated. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The plaintiffs further claim the machines may be connected to the internet, allowing for external tampering, though this is illegal under state law and no evidence has been provided to support this allegation.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When reached by phone Tuesday, Lilly declined to be interviewed for this story. Mares did not respond to several calls seeking comment. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lilly and Mares argue that under the current legal regime, local electoral board members are unable to personally review and verify that the voting machine program being used to count the ballots “is keeping and recording a true and accurate count,” and that the device’s record tape accurately represents the ballots cast.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Consequently, the plaintiffs believe that the voting machine is counting the votes in secret, because neither the program counting the votes recorded on the ballots nor the ballots themselves can be examined,” the complaint says. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lilly further stated in an affidavit attached to the complaint that he “cannot ensure that the machines do not connect to the internet, allowing for vote counting algorithm manipulation, nor can I ensure with any certainty that the electronic ballot scanners are presenting results which are consistent with the contents of the ballot box.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Henry Chambers, a professor for constitutional law at the University of Richmond School of Law, said in a phone interview Tuesday that the lawsuit appears to be based on long debunked conspiracy theories circulating after the 2020 presidential election that claimed vote counting machines had been programmed to get votes wrong and to flip votes.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“That’s not really a serious thing, but some people have bought into it and it sounds like these folks have bought into it, too,” Chambers said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Their notion is that vote counting that is done by a machine is done in secret, and therefore you have to hand-count the votes, presumably in public, in order to have a real tally of the actual vote count,” Chamber continued. “That would suggest that voting that is not done by hand and in public qualifies as counting in secret, which in theory would violate the state Constitution.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Virginia, voters cast paper ballots, which are then counted by optical scanning machines — as required </span><a href="https://law.lis.virginia.gov/vacode/title24.2/chapter6/section24.2-626/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">by state law</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> — to expedite the process and avoid human error. Ballot scanning machines are certified to meet both state and federal standards and are maintained under a controlled chain of custody.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Before every election, the scanners are tested using a predetermined sample of votes to ensure they are tallied accurately before any actual votes are cast, and it is against the law to connect a ballot scanning machine to the Internet at any point. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beals, who was appointed as Virginia’s top elections official in March 2022, did not respond to text messages seeking comment Tuesday, and a spokeswoman for the Department of the Elections said in an email that the department does not comment on pending litigation.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But in </span><a href="https://cardinalnews.org/2024/08/08/virginias-top-elections-official-says-shes-confident-about-the-accuracy-of-results/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">an interview</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in July, Beals said that hacking the scanning machines was impossible. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Period. They cannot be,” she said, adding that after the testing of the devices ahead of the election and on Election Day, officials also conduct risk-eliminating audits, which she called the back-end check.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“So we have three different checks throughout the system just to make sure that the machines are reporting accurately.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chambers, the UR professor, called the plaintiffs’ argument that the machine counting of ballots happened in secrecy “an odd thing,” because the machine itself is doing the counting in a public space, supervised by election officials. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The problem with counting being done in public is that one can’t necessarily explicitly see what’s going on. But the fact is, we have lots of things that count things and we just agree that it’s being counted correctly, like ATM machines,” Chambers said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“No one would say that the ATM machine is spitting out money in secret, but it’s spitting out money in response to a request. Here, a voting machine is counting votes in response to a ballot being fed through a machine.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By asking for ballots to be hand-counted instead of being tabulated by machines, the plaintiffs could really be asking for a slow-down of the count, Chambers added, which “can introduce additional problems with a valid count — and that is the whole point of feeding the ballots through during the day and having a continuous count is so that you can have results in a reasonable and fair time. Hand counting is used only when necessary when you&#8217;re talking about things like absentee ballots or ballots that can’t be read by the machine.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It also remains unclear why the GOP election officials who filed the suit would threaten to not certify the presidential election, in a county that leans Republican and where Trump won with 51-46% in 2020. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Rich Anderson, the chairman of the Republican Party of Virginia, underscored that the lawsuit was a lone effort by a small group of GOP officials from one locality. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“As far as I know it’s only happening in this one jurisdiction out of 133, but it’s all going to get settled in the courts anyway,” Anderson said in a phone interview. “What they’re asking is the court to render its opinion, which it will do, and the opinion will likely be on the side of Virginia law, which says that ballots are counted through the optical scanners, not by hand.”</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="LC7yMtQx2P"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/28/outcome-of-5th-district-gop-primary-unchanged-after-further-review-of-ballots/">Outcome of 5th District GOP primary unchanged after further review of ballots</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Outcome of 5th District GOP primary unchanged after further review of ballots&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/28/outcome-of-5th-district-gop-primary-unchanged-after-further-review-of-ballots/embed/#?secret=7ntY49GRJi#?secret=LC7yMtQx2P" data-secret="LC7yMtQx2P" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The counting of ballots by optical scanning machines has been proven as safe and reliable, Anderson said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We vote by paper, the votes are rendered and are fed through the machines. And then if there’s a recount, they go through the whole process again, as we recently saw in the </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/28/outcome-of-5th-district-gop-primary-unchanged-after-further-review-of-ballots/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">5th Congressional District</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">,” Anderson said. “And it comes out pretty much dead accurate.”</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
