<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>General Assembly 2025 Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/category/governmentpolitics/general-assembly-2025/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/category/governmentpolitics/general-assembly-2025/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 10:33:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>General Assembly 2025 Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/category/governmentpolitics/general-assembly-2025/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Georgia, Rhode Island repealed car taxes. Could Youngkin’s plan lead to an elimination in Virginia?</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/30/georgia-rhode-island-repealed-car-taxes-could-youngkins-plan-lead-to-an-elimination-in-virginia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nathaniel Cline]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>ncline@virginiamercury.com (Nathaniel Cline)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 10:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gov. Glenn Youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transportation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41611</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As lawmakers consider Gov. Glenn Youngkin’s proposal to provide vehicle tax relief for Virginians and ultimately eliminate the property tax, policymakers can find comfort after repeals in Rhode Island and Georgia.  All of Virginia&#8217;s cities, counties and towns are subject to a personal property tax, which helps fund their respective governments. Municipalities are likely to [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/IMG_2005-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/IMG_2005-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/IMG_2005-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/IMG_2005-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/IMG_2005-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/IMG_2005-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Virginia Gov. Glenn Youngkin speaking with reporters on April 8, 2024. (Nathaniel Cline/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As lawmakers consider Gov. Glenn Youngkin’s proposal to provide vehicle tax relief for Virginians and ultimately eliminate the property tax, policymakers can find comfort after repeals in Rhode Island and Georgia. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All of Virginia&#8217;s cities, counties and towns are subject to a personal property tax, which helps fund their respective governments. Municipalities are likely to be impacted by such a relief or repeal proposal, including some, like Chesapeake, that have been grappling with reforming vehicle-related taxes.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="71W6SzRqck"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/18/youngkin-unveils-ambitious-budget-proposal-for-his-final-year-as-governor/">Youngkin unveils ambitious budget proposal for his final year as governor</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Youngkin unveils ambitious budget proposal for his final year as governor&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/18/youngkin-unveils-ambitious-budget-proposal-for-his-final-year-as-governor/embed/#?secret=iLC32GfACP#?secret=71W6SzRqck" data-secret="71W6SzRqck" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On Dec. 18, Youngkin said a family of four in Virginia pays about $290 on their vehicle taxes annually during his address to lawmakers and cabinet members.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Let&#8217;s give Virginia families relief on the most hated tax in America since the tax on tea &#8211; the local car tax,” Youngkin said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the governor did not include a plan to repeal the tax when he first raised the idea last December, this year he proposed an amendment to the current biennium budget to allocate $1.1 billion into a car tax credit fund to provide income tax rebates to nearly 1.9 billion taxpayers earning up to $50,000 in adjusted gross income for individuals or $100,000 for couples filing jointly. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eligible taxpayers would receive up to $150 for individual returns or $300 for joint returns annually for the next three years. After the fund is exhausted, the state would see a permanent reduction of $360 million in tax revenues each year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If successful, Virginia would join several states and jurisdictions that do not impose a vehicle tax including the District of Columbia, Georgia, Maryland and Rhode Island.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to a Nov. 7, 2023 </span><a href="https://www.cga.ct.gov/2023/rpt/pdf/2023-R-0196.pdf" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">legislative report</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> completed in Connecticut, which was studying tax repeals, Rhode Island and Georgia over the past seven years repealed their vehicle property tax either by adjusting tax calculation factors by an increasing amount over a number of years, or enacting it only for taxpayers that perform a triggering action, such as applying for a vehicle title.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Georgia and Rhode Island took different approaches to address local governments’ revenue losses. Rhode Island reimbursed revenue losses from general appropriations and adjusted reimbursements based on sales tax revenues. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Georgia replaced its state and local annual property and sales taxes with a one-time per owner tax, divided between the state and municipalities.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Last year, West Virginia </span><a href="https://www.wvnews.com/mountainstatesman/news/taylor-county-west-virginia-assessor-explains-hb2526-and-the-motor-vehicle-property-tax-adjustment-credit/article_182eafb2-257e-11ee-afe4-8ba9d7735e92.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">created</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> a fully refundable tax credit to eliminate the tax’s impact on residents while holding municipalities harmless, which took effect in 2024.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In 1998, Virginia developed a vehicle tax </span><a href="https://law.lis.virginia.gov/vacodefull/title58.1/chapter35.1/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">relief program</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, but the reimbursement rate starting at 12.5% was frozen at 70% in 2021, below the anticipated 100%, due to unforeseen costs as new car values increased substantially faster than inflation.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia lawmakers will start their 45-day session discussing proposed bills and budget amendments on Jan. 8.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Youngkin touts ‘tailwinds’ from Washington, sparks debate on state impact</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/19/youngkin-touts-tailwinds-from-washington-sparks-debate-on-state-impact/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Paullin]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 10:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gov. Glenn Youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President-Elect Donald Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Secretary of Finance Stephen Cummings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia General Assembly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[workforce cuts]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=41569</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With a new presidential administration taking office in January, Gov. Glenn Youngkin expressed optimism about potential fiscal benefits for Virginia, even as Democratic lawmakers voiced concerns about looming challenges.  “I am so looking forward to having a period of tailwinds that will come out of Washington,” Youngkin said Wednesday following his budget proposal presentation in [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="670" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-18-at-4.04.56 PM-1024x670.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-18-at-4.04.56 PM-1024x670.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-18-at-4.04.56 PM-300x196.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-18-at-4.04.56 PM-768x502.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-18-at-4.04.56 PM-1536x1005.png 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-18-at-4.04.56 PM.png 1682w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Virginia's Secretary of Finance Stephen Cummings speaks to the legislative money committees in Richmond Wednesday as Senate Finance Chair Louise Lucas, D-Portsmouth, looks on. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury) </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With a new presidential administration taking office in January, Gov. Glenn Youngkin expressed optimism about potential fiscal benefits for Virginia, even as Democratic lawmakers voiced concerns about looming challenges. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I am so looking forward to having a period of tailwinds that will come out of Washington,” Youngkin said Wednesday following his budget proposal presentation in Richmond, signaling confidence in President-elect Donald Trump’s economic agenda.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trump has indicated plans to bring back the 2017 corporate tax cuts, raise tariffs on imported goods, and cut federal jobs, sparking debate among Virginia lawmakers over potential impacts. Discussions also touched on federal Medicaid cuts, which could significantly affect the state’s healthcare funding.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Speaking during a joint session of the General Assembly’s money committees, Virginia’s Secretary of Finance Stephen Cummings mixed corporate income tax trends, noting that while refunds tied to corporate tax payments were slightly up, corporate tax revenues are down by $177.4 million compared to the same time last year. Cummings cited an uptick in </span><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2024/08/15/youngkin-taxes-corporation-refunds/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">corporate tax refunds</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as a contributing factor. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’ve actually built in on corporate income tax a very conservative corporate tax view, reflecting some of the things that have taken place to date,” Cummings said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin defended tariffs as a way to ensure “America gets good deals first with our adversaries,” noting that the policy, first implemented by Trump during his first term, has continued under President Joe Biden.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“What I am seeing as a result of the discussion around tariffs is a literal line of businesses that want to invest in America, and particularly in Virginia,” Youngkin said, though he did not provide specific examples. “I think we’re going to see another level of growth here in the commonwealth as a result.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, the </span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tax Foundation</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, a nonprofit think tank, projects that while tariffs </span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/blog/trump-tariffs-revenue-estimates/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">could raise</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> between $2 billion and $3.3 trillion from 2025 through 2034, they would also increase the cost of goods. This could result in an average annual tax burden of $1,253 to $2,045 per U.S. household over the same period.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Del. Cliff Hayes, D-Chesapeake, expressed concerns over the broader application of tariffs compared to previous policies, which were more focused on China. “That’s a distinct difference from 2016 when it was more targeted on certain countries,” Hayes said. “Now we’re hearing about a more broad application.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cummings defended the previous tariffs, arguing that they contributed to economic growth despite targeting basic goods like steel and aluminum, which have widespread effects on manufacturing. “I don’t think you can really separate the two,” Cummings said, referring to the different types of tariffs being proposed.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nationally, Democrats have touted improvements in the economy, pointing to a steady decline in inflation since its pandemic-era peak. On Wednesday, the Federal Reserve lowered interest rates by another 0.25%, attributing the move to favorable economic conditions resulting from current policies. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Del. Candi Mundon-King, D-Prince William, raised concerns about the potential economic impact of federal job cuts, which would disproportionately affect Northern Virginia, home to a significant portion of the state’s federal workforce. A George Mason University analysis released before the election </span><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/08/30/trump-government-cuts-could-cost-house-republicans-majority-.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">estimated</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> that eliminating 100,000 positions could result in an annual loss of $27-28 billion for Virginia’s economy.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“That’s very definitely on the radar screen,” Cummings said, acknowledging the potential effects of such “very aggressive actions” on Virginia’s more than 200,000 federal workers. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cummings noted that while federal jobs represent a small percentage of Virginia’s 4.2 million workers, their loss would still be felt. ”It’s not insignificant, but it’s not huge,” he said, adding that the private sector could potentially absorb displaced workers, given Virginia’s low 2.9% unemployment rate.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sen. Barbara Favola, D-Arlington, expressed concerns about the potential for </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/11/9-states-including-virginia-poised-to-end-coverage-for-millions-if-trump-cuts-medicaid-funding/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">federal cuts</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to the Medicaid expansion program’s funding match, emphasizing the importance of maintaining coverage for Virginians. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“There’s an incredible benefit to having all Virginians insured,” Favola said, noting the link between health insurance and workforce participation. “I would hope the administration would be very amenable to continuing, at a minimum, our policy of insurance remains as many Virginians need insurance.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cummings assured lawmakers that the state is prepared for potential Medicaid funding challenges. “We have fully provided for all the liabilities that we know of around Medicaid, and built in growth in our five-year plan.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democratic leaders, who control the House of Delegates and the state Senate, said Wednesday they are still reviewing Youngkin’s budget proposals ahead of negotiations set to begin when the legislative session starts on Jan. 8.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Youngkin unveils ambitious budget proposal for his final year as governor</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/18/youngkin-unveils-ambitious-budget-proposal-for-his-final-year-as-governor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>cwoods@virginiamercury.com (Charlotte Rene Woods)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 19:21:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[car tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gov. Glenn Youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[House Appropriations Committee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senate Finance Committee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia General Assembly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia House of Delegates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia Senate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41557</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the cusp of his last full year in office, Gov. Glenn Youngkin on Wednesday unveiled a sweeping budget proposal that he hopes will define his legacy as Virginia’s 74th governor. Focused on tax cuts, infrastructure, education, and public health, the plan sets the stage for what could be a high-stakes 2025 legislative session as [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_4684-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="Gov. Glenn Youngkin" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_4684-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_4684-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_4684-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_4684-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_4684-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Gov. Glenn Youngkin presents his proposed amendments to the state's biennial budget before a joint meeting of the Virginia General Assembly's money committees in Richmond on Wednesday. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury) </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the cusp of his last full year in office, Gov. Glenn Youngkin on Wednesday unveiled a sweeping budget proposal that he hopes will define his legacy as Virginia’s 74th governor. Focused on tax cuts, infrastructure, education, and public health, the plan sets the stage for what could be a high-stakes 2025 legislative session as lawmakers weigh his ambitious priorities.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We reopened Virginia’s economy after a global pandemic all while delivering surplus after surplus,” Youngkin said during a joint meeting of the General Assembly’s money committees in Richmond. “Virginia is growing, Virginia is leading, and Virginia is winning. And this morning I ask you to join me in continuing that work together.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin emphasized the state’s strong economic performance, pointing to job growth, corporate investment, and robust revenue increases. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The stock market is strong, and the Federal Reserve appears poised to reduce interest rates over the next year,” he said. “This backdrop further supports Virginia’s ongoing strong performance, with year-to-date revenues up 7.3% over 2024.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Highlighting more than $5 billion in tax cuts already delivered to Virginians over the last three years, Youngkin proposed additional measures to lower the cost of living. “Together, the commonwealth can make a clear statement that reducing tax burdens so Virginians can keep more of their hard-earned money in their pockets is not a Republican idea, it’s not a Democrat idea, it’s just common sense,” he said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A cornerstone in Youngkin’s proposed revisions to the two-year budget is a renewed push to eliminate the locally imposed personal car tax, an issue that he first came to embrace earlier this year after two Democrats campaigning for legislative seats in Southwest Virginia </span><a href="https://cardinalnews.org/2023/10/13/two-virginia-democrats-embrace-a-former-republican-governors-signature-policy-eliminate-the-car-tax/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">adopted it</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as part of their platforms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The car tax has been a Republican rallying point since 1997, when GOP gubernatorial nominee Jim Gilmore successfully campaigned on repealing the unpopular levy. However, without a clear plan during the 2024 legislative session, the proposal quickly fizzled. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On Wednesday, Youngkin once again urged the General Assembly to abolish what he called Virginia’s “most hated tax since the tax on tea” that he said cost the average Virginia family of four about $290 annually. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Standing here today, I will renew my call for us to work to fully eliminate the car tax, but recognizing that this might not be possible in this short session, there is an incremental step that we should take together to provide additional car tax relief,” Youngkin said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Under the new proposal, the state would deposit $1.1 billion into a car tax credit fund to provide income tax rebates to nearly 1.9 million taxpayers earning up to $50,000 in adjusted gross income for individuals or $100,000 for couples filing jointly. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eligible taxpayers would receive up to $150 for individual returns or $300 for joint returns annually for the next three years. After the fund is exhausted, the state would see a permanent reduction of $360 million in tax revenues each year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin also is asking the legislature to extend the standard deductions for state income tax returns — currently set at  $8,500 for individuals and $17,000 for joint filers — that are set to expire at the end of next year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Failure to make the standard deduction permanent before Jan. 1, 2026, would result in tax increases of $57 million in fiscal year 2026 and $1.2 billion in fiscal year 2027, the governor said. “My friends, there is no reason to raise taxes on Virginians. We are running surplus after surplus after surplus.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democratic lawmakers responded cautiously to Youngkin’s budget plan Wednesday, emphasizing the need to review the details before committing to any initiatives. With the legislative session set to begin in January, both the House and Senate are preparing to roll out their own budget amendment proposals, signaling potential negotiations ahead.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our focus will remain on targeted investments that benefit all Virginians,” said House Appropriations Chair Del. Luke Torian, D-Prince William. “We will explore how we can work across the aisle to ensure K-12 schools are fully funded, higher education is accessible, and affordable housing becomes a reality for more families. These are areas where we can and should find common ground.”</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40738" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/06/virginia-leaders-react-to-trump-win-as-harris-keeps-the-commonwealth-blue/img_3713/" rel="attachment wp-att-40738"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-40738" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Virginia House Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, speaks to members of the media on Nov. 6, 2024. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">House Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, in a statement thanked Youngkin for presenting his budget and for “initiating this important conversation.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Now, our responsibility is to evaluate these proposals thoughtfully and collaboratively to ensure they reflect the priorities of all Virginians. We can craft a budget that strengthens our schools, supports our communities, and provides real solutions for working families,” Scott said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And Sen. Louise Lucas, D-Portsmouth, the Senate’s president pro tempore, said that while her chamber will consider his proposal, the Democrats’ amendments will look different. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The Senate budget will provide relief to working families and individuals and invest in their education and well-being, while maintaining the commonwealth&#8217;s long-term fiscal health,” Lucas said. “Here in the Senate, we look beyond elections and talk-show appearances and budget for the long-haul.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other key initiatives in Youngkin’s proposed budget amendments:</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">‘No tax on tips’</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The administration is also proposing </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/16/youngkin-pitches-tax-relief-for-tipped-workers-in-budget-plan/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">to eliminate</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> state taxes on tips for service industry workers, a policy similar to one championed by President-elect Donald Trump. If approved, the measure would allow tipped workers to claim a deduction on their state tax returns, with compliance monitored through IRS data and employer-reported W-2 forms. The proposal could benefit an estimated 250,000 Virginians. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Virginia has an incredible hospitality, restaurant and service industry, and hardworking Virginians should keep every penny of the tips they earn through their exceptional service. My proposal is very simple — no more taxes on tips,” Youngkin said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the move is being framed as a win for workers, its broader implications remain unclear. Economists warn that some employers might exploit the policy by shifting more of a worker’s compensation to tips rather than wages, a concern </span><a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/economy/trump-and-harris-say-theyll-kill-taxes-on-tips-how-would-that-work" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">also raised</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> around similar federal legislation. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Education </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin is proposing nearly $1 billion in new education funding, including a $50-million Virginia Opportunity Scholarship Program to provide $5,000 annual grants for private school expenses like tuition and transportation. About 10,000 K-12 students from families earning up to twice the federal poverty limit to qualify for free school meals would qualify, with funding coming from revenue growth, not existing education budgets.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The plan includes $25 million for lab school partnerships with historically Black colleges and universities and nearly $500 for higher education capital projects. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, there is no new funding for college operating expenses, and Youngkin is pushing for a 2.5% cap on tuition increases. “It’s time for our colleges to cut administrative bloat and handle costs without asking taxpayers for more,” he said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Additional proposals include $290 million for school construction, $550 million in direct aid, $6.8 million for school resource officers, and $50 million to support underperforming schools. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">VMSDEP</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Virginia Military Survivors and Dependents Education Program </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/07/jlarc-review-of-vmsdep-no-evidence-of-peak-or-decline-in-participation-levels/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">(VMSDEP)</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, which provides tuition waivers to spouses and children of military members killed or permanently disabled in service, would receive $60 million from a surplus in the state’s 529 college savings program to address a funding shortfall.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lawmakers scrutinized the program last year after it was initially excluded from budget negotiations. Concerns over its sustainability arose as participation surged by nearly 350%, growing from about 1,400 participants in 2019 to about 6,400 in 2023. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The allocation would come without any new policy proposals.</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Withholding funds to quash ‘sanctuary cities’ </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin further echored national Republican rhetoric by declaring that “every state has become a border state” as he unveiled plans to </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/youngkin-wants-to-restrict-funding-for-localities-that-dont-comply-with-immigration-enforcement/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">cut funding</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to localities that limit or refuse compliance with U.S. Customs and Immigration Enforcement (ICE). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The proposal aligns with a broader GOP push against “sanctuary city” policies, which vary but often involve local governments choosing not to inquire about immigration status or declining full cooperation with ICE. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But with Virginia’s legislature under Democratic control, this proposal is expected to face significant opposition during the upcoming budget negotiations.</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Boosting maternal health outcomes</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin and Democratic lawmakers are prioritizing </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/momnibus-package-aims-to-close-maternal-health-gaps-across-virginia/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">maternal health</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in their legislative and budget </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/17/in-bipartisan-push-virginia-lawmakers-target-rural-healthcare-crisis/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">proposals</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, increasing the chances that some measures will make it through budget negotiations. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin’s plan </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/youngkin-unveils-plan-to-improve-maternal-health-in-virginia/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">includes $2.5 million</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for perinatal health hubs, expanded funding for OB-GYN residencies, and a $500,000 education campaign to help parents recognize life threatening conditions like heart attacks or eclampsia. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">He also proposes $1 million to support workforce development for midwives and doulas, both crucial professions in addressing care gaps and advocating for patients, particularly those of color impacted by racial health disparities. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Mental health support</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As Virginia enters its third year of its Right Help, Right Now initiative, Youngkin’s latest budget request includes </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/13/meet-people-where-they-are-special-teams-aid-va-s-efforts-to-expand-mental-health-care-services/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">$35 million</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to improve crisis response involving law enforcement. The funding would support hiring </span><a href="https://www.dcjs.virginia.gov/licensure-and-regulatory-affairs/special-conservators-peace" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">special conservators of the peace</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, or “s-cops,” as Youngkin calls them.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These intermediaries would assist with individuals awaiting hospital admissions after mental health crises, aiming to de-escalate situations where people in crisis might unintentionally harm  officers and face jail time. Youngkin envisions the “s-cops” fostering better outcomes for those in crisis while allowing law enforcement officers to focus on their regular duties.</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Disaster relief</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The administration proposes allocating $127 million toward a permanent </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/09/20/after-hurley-and-whitewood-floods-virginia-considers-state-relief-fund/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">disaster relief fund</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to aid victims of natural disasters beyond what the federal assistance, insurance and private donations cover. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Southwest Virginia has faced repeated flooding in recent years, most recently from Hurricane Helene in September, which claimed three lives and caused $4.4 billion in </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/03/va-dept-of-transportation-estimates-hurricane-helene-debris-cleanup-will-take-3-to-6-months/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">damage</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Youngkin said $25 million could come from the general fund, with $102 million sourced from the latest round of revenues of the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative (RGGI). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin had previously </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/20/judge-deems-youngkins-actions-to-withdraw-virginia-from-rggi-unlawful/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">sought to withdraw</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Virginia from RGGI, despite praise from environmental groups for its funding for flood resilience and energy efficiency programs. “I fully expect that the General Assembly will work constructively together in this next short session to appropriate funds specifically for Hurricane Helene relief,” he said on Wednesday.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sen. Mamie Locke, D-Hampton, questioned the governor’s proposal, pointing to his approach of using RGGI revenues. “Why not just put us back in RGGI?” she asked, while noting uncertainty about the fund’s legislative support.   </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Don’t know yet,” she said in an interview. </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Momnibus’ package aims to close maternal health gaps across Virginia</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/momnibus-package-aims-to-close-maternal-health-gaps-across-virginia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlotte Rene Woods]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cwoods@virginiamercury.com (Charlotte Rene Woods)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 23:53:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Black maternal health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maternal health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=41529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Virginia lawmakers are gearing up for a renewed push to tackle maternal health disparities in the 2025 session, with a slate of bills and budget amendments focused on improving outcomes for parents across the state.  A key proposal is a bipartisan effort to mandate unconscious bias training for nursing license renewals, which previously passed the [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_3785-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_3785-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_3785-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_3785-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_3785-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/IMG_3785-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Del. Candi Mundon King, D-Prince William, speaks during a press conference about a package of maternal health bills ahead of Virginia's 2025 legislative session. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia lawmakers are gearing up for a renewed push to tackle maternal health disparities in the 2025 session, with a slate of bills and budget amendments focused on improving outcomes for parents across the state. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A key proposal is a bipartisan effort to mandate </span><a href="https://richmond.com/news/local/government-politics/virginia-black-maternal-health-carroll-foy-youngkin/article_4608fd84-d1ae-11ee-8379-138efdfc34c7.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">unconscious bias training</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for nursing license renewals, which previously passed the legislature but </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/20/youngkin-vetoes-bills-on-contraception-access-skill-games-confederate-heritage-rollbacks/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">was vetoed </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">by Gov. Glenn Youngkin. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lawmakers say that targeted training is critical in addressing preventable deaths and complications during childbirth, marking it as a vital step in the broader push for maternal health reform. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Data from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reveals a stark disparity in maternal health: Black women are significantly </span><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/hestat/maternal-mortality/2021/maternal-mortality-rates-2021.htm" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">more likely to die</span> </a><span style="font-weight: 400;">from pregnancy-related complications than white women. Research also highlights that women of color often face worse  health outcomes, partly due to </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7384760" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">racial bias</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in healthcare settings.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">House Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, emphasized the urgency of addressing these inequities, stating that the proposed legislation aims to tackle the “broken systems and lack of resources” contributing to poor maternal health outcomes, particularly for Black parents. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The “momnibus” package — a play on the term omnibus — also includes proposals to enhance healthcare monitoring and expanded Medicaid coverage to improve maternal health outcomes.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One key initiative by Del. Amy Laufer, D-Charlottesville, seeks to pilot remote monitoring for conditions like hypertension and diabetes. This approach is designed to assist expectant parents, particularly those in rural areas with limited access to hospitals or healthcare providers, by ensuring their conditions are closely monitored during pregnancy. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">About 30% of Virginia counties lack a birthing center within a 30-minute drive, according to the March of Dimes, a non-profit that works to enhance the health of mothers and babies. In Southwest and Southside Virginia, recent years have seen the </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/17/virginias-state-budget-will-fund-ob-gyn-medical-residencies-amid-obstetrics-closures"><span style="font-weight: 400;">closure of several obstetrics units</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> However, the latest state budget includes funding to support OB-GYN residencies in hospitals, aiming to bolster care in underserved areas. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The momnibus package also includes proposals to expand Medicaid coverage to include diapers and limited baby supplies, as well as legislation to establish a women’s health commission focused on developing targeted maternal health policies.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lawmakers and maternal health experts first previewed the momnibus package during a Black Maternal Health </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/18/momnibus-bill-plans-announced-at-virginias-black-maternal-health-summit/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Summit</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in Richmond in October, where public health professionals and legislators from around the country gathered to collaborate on solutions to improve maternal health outcomes. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Del. Candi Mundon King, D-Prince William, on Monday expressed optimism about bipartisan support for the upcoming maternal health proposals, noting that Republicans have previously supported and even co-sponsored some Democrat-led maternal health initiatives. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’re hoping that when these bills get before them, they will continue that support,” Mundon King said.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cifers triumphs in multi-round vote to represent GOP in state Senate District 10 special election</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/cifers-triumphs-in-multi-round-vote-to-represent-gop-in-state-senate-district-10-special-election/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 06:55:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McGuire]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Luther Cifers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia General Assembly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia Senate District 10]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia state Senate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=41493</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, emerged victorious in the Republican nomination contest for Virginia’s 10th Senate District during a mass meeting at the Goochland Rec Center. The meeting, which drew hundreds of Republican voters, began Friday evening and stretched into the early hours of Saturday as participants navigated a lengthy multi-ballot process [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="818" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-1024x818.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-1024x818.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-300x240.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-768x614.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM.png 1094w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, won the Republican nomination in Virginia's Senate District 10 at a mass meeting in Goochland County early Saturday morning. (Courtesy of Luther Cifers campaign). </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, emerged victorious in the Republican nomination contest for Virginia’s 10th Senate District during a mass meeting at the Goochland Rec Center.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The meeting, which drew hundreds of Republican voters, began Friday evening and stretched into the early hours of Saturday as participants navigated a lengthy multi-ballot process to select a nominee from a crowded field of seven candidates. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cifers secured the majority needed to clinch the nomination, defeating a mix of seasoned politicians and newcomers in three rounds of voting.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cifers will now face Democrat Jack Trammel in the Jan. 7 special election to fill the vacancy left by Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland, who resigned after his recent election to Congress. The winner of the special election will serve the remainder of McGuire’s term, which runs until 2027.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other contenders included runner-up Duane Adams, the chairman of the Louisa County Board of Supervisors who previously ran for the Republican nomination in the district in 2023 but was defeated by McGuire​, and Amanda Chase, a former state senator from Chesterfield County who served in the Virginia Senate for eight years. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There were four other bids for the seat by Shayne Snavely, a veteran and former Chase aide, Jean Gannon, a Powhatan County real estate appraiser, Alex Cheatham, a recent college graduate, and Bryan Hamlet.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Luther emerged from a field of seven outstanding candidates who sought the nomination. The Republican Party of Virginia and I look forward to marching in lockstep with Luther and his team over the next three weeks in ensuring that he is victorious on January 7th and takes the oath of office on January 8th,” said Rich Anderson, the chairman of the Republican Party of Virginia.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the district’s strong Republican lean — with 62.8% of voters supporting former President Donald Trump and 67.8% backing Gov. Glenn Youngkin — Cifers is seen as the favorite in the upcoming election.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Republicans to choose Senate District 10 nominee to succeed McGuire</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/12/republicans-to-choose-senate-district-10-nominee-to-succeed-mcguire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 10:32:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2024 congressional elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mass meeting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sen. John McGuire]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senate District 10]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41471</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Republicans in Virginia’s 10th state Senate District will convene for a mass meeting on Friday to select their nominee in an upcoming special election. The vacancy was prompted by the resignation of Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland, who is set to leave his post after being elected to Congress​.  The meeting will take place at the [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Rep.-elect John McGuire, R-Goochland, formally resigned his state Senate seat on Wednesday, clearing the way for a special election in Virginia's Senate District 10. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury) </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republicans in Virginia’s 10th state Senate District will convene for a mass meeting on Friday to select their nominee in an upcoming special election. The vacancy was prompted by the resignation of Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland, who is set to leave his post after being elected to Congress​. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The meeting will take place at the Goochland Rec Center, with registration running from 4:30 p.m. to 6:30 p.m., and proceedings beginning at 6:30 p.m. A total of seven candidates are vying to succeed McGuire. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Organized by local party committees, mass meetings require party members to gather at a designated time and place to publicly select a candidate. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Unlike secret ballots, voting is often conducted through a show of hands, voice vote, or other public method. Participants must remain present for multiple rounds of voting until one candidate secures a majority — typically more than 50% of the votes — to be declared the winner. This process can be lengthy, especially in races with a crowded field of candidates.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Once the GOP nominee is selected, they will face Democrat Jack Trammel in a special election on Jan. 7 set by Sen. Louise Lucas, D-Portsmouth, the Senate president pro tempore. The winner will serve out the remainder of McGuire’s term in the Senate, which ends in 2027.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Among the first Republicans to declare their candidacy for McGuire’s seat was Amanda Chase, a former state senator from Chesterfield County who served in the Virginia Senate for eight years. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chase previously ran for re-election in 2023 but lost the GOP primary for her Chesterfield-based seat to Sen. Glen Sturtevant. To qualify for the 10th District race, Chase moved to Appomattox County, as Virginia law requires state legislators to live in the district they represent.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Joining the race is Shayne Snavely, an Amelia-based entrepreneur, veteran who was a former aide to Chase and worked on her failed 2021 gubernatorial campaign. Jean Gannon, a Powhatan County real estate appraiser and long-time Republican activist, has also thrown her hat into the ring. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Duane Adams, the chairman of the Louisa County Board of Supervisors, is making a bid for the seat as well. Adams previously ran for the Republican nomination in the district in 2023 but was defeated by McGuire​.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other contenders include Alex Cheatham, a recent college graduate aiming to make his political debut, and two late entrants: Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, and Bryan Hamlet, chairman of the Cumberland County Board of Supervisors​.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We have a pretty good selection among the group there. I don’t know everybody, but I think that they will all be competitive candidates in that district,” Rich Anderson, chairman of the Republican Party of Virginia, said in a phone interview. “Obviously as a conservative Republican leading the conservative party, I want to get a conservative Republican nominated.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anderson said that the mass meeting could last late into the evening.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The process will probably require multiple ballots with that many people on the docket, so we’ll just see how it all turns out. I can’t predict who will walk away with all the marbles, but one of them will.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">David Richards, a political science professor at the University of Lynchburg, said that of the Republicans who have thrown their names in the ring for the special election to replace McGuire, “Chase is perhaps the best known or most notorious.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But Richards doubts that Chase will get her party’s nod. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The mass meeting nomination process caters to party members, and Chase has little credibility with the local party after being expelled by the Chesterfield GOP and being noticeably absent from the one candidates forum already held. And she has little credibility with local Republicans, which will hurt her chances.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Among the remaining six candidates, Adams has been very active beginning with his unsuccessful bid for the nomination in 2023, which McGuire won, Richards said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The key to these mass meetings is name recognition in a positive way. Aside from the candidate forum held in late November, there has not been much opportunity or time for candidates to get their message out. Their pre-existing connections will tip the scale, which is why I expect Adams to win the nomination.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Adams will still “get a run for his money” from Snavely, who also has a lot of party experience working for Chase earlier in his career, Richards added. “The other candidates have very low profiles, but Jean Gannon has been active in local GOP politics, which might help her.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">McGuire, who in June defeated incumbent U.S. Rep. Bob Good, R-Farmville, in one of the most viciously fought and expensive GOP primary battles nationwide this year, had kept Republicans </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/25/mcguire-still-hasnt-resigned-his-state-senate-seat-weeks-after-congressional-win/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">on edge for weeks</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> after winning his election against Democrat Gloria Witt on Nov. 5. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Typically, elected officials who win a new position resign from their current office within days to allow for a special election to be called promptly, ensuring the seat isn’t left vacant when the next legislative session begins in early January. However, McGuire delayed his departure, formally stepping down on Wednesday​.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In his official resignation letter, McGuire called his brief stint in the state Senate “the privilege of a lifetime” and said he hoped voters would choose “a strong candidate who loves We The People,” works well with others and who has “never wavered on our core Republican values.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, McGuire stopped short from publicly backing one of the seven candidates vying to succeed him. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I was not too surprised that McGuire has not endorsed anyone, especially Adams,” said Richards. “When McGuire announced he was primarying Bob Good, Adams was very vocal about McGuire’s decision, calling him a liar, so there does not seem to be much love lost there.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The 10th Senate District, which spans 11 localities from Lynchburg in the west to the suburbs of Richmond in the east, leans heavily Republican. The district backed President-elect Donald Trump with 62.8% of the vote last month and gave Republican Glenn Youngkin an even stronger 67.8% support during his successful 2021 gubernatorial campaign.</span></p>
<p><em>Editor&#8217;s note: This story has been updated to include the date for the special election set for Jan. 7.</em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Youngkin seeks additional $290 million boost for school construction</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/10/youngkin-seeks-additional-290-million-boost-for-school-construction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 20:09:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Assembly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gov. Glenn Youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School construction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia school construction]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41106</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Gov. Glenn Youngkin on Tuesday announced that he is asking the legislature for an additional $290 million to support school construction and modernization efforts across Virginia. This latest investment would bring the total funding for the current biennium to $700 million and raise the state’s overall contribution under Youngkin’s administration to nearly $2 billion. Youngkin’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="Lawmakers are set to consider Gov. Glenn Youngkin&#039;s proposal to invest another $290 million for school construction needs during the upcoming legislative session which begins in January. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Lawmakers are set to consider Gov. Glenn Youngkin's proposal to invest another $290 million for school construction needs during the upcoming legislative session which begins in January. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Gov. Glenn Youngkin on Tuesday announced that he is asking the legislature for an additional $290 million to support school construction and modernization efforts across Virginia. This latest investment would bring the total funding for the current biennium to $700 million and raise the state’s overall contribution under Youngkin’s administration to nearly $2 billion.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin’s funding request is included in his proposed budget amendments, which he plans to present next week at a joint meeting of the General Assembly’s money committees.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to the governor’s office, the state’s financial commitments have spurred an estimated $3.4 billion in total funding for school construction. The additional support would be made possible through a combination of local government contributions and federal matching funds.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Over the last three years, we have invested historic amounts in our education system, including our public school facilities,” Youngkin said in a statement. “Our record economic growth and the resulting surplus allows us to make this critical investment to ensure every Virginia student has access to high-quality school facilities that support academic success.” </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_38057" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/03/07/bill-to-allow-marijuana-sales-in-peril-after-breakdown-on-virginia-arena-deal/img_1875/" rel="attachment wp-att-38057"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-38057" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/IMG_1875-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/IMG_1875-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/IMG_1875-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/IMG_1875-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/IMG_1875-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/IMG_1875-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Gov. Glenn Youngkin speaking with reporters outside the Capitol Building on March 7, 2024. (Nathaniel Cline/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin plans to use the newly announced $290 million in non-general funds to expand competitive grant opportunities for school divisions, particularly in high-need areas. The money would also address critical infrastructure issues, supporting the construction and renovation of schools in urgent need of repair.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">State officials say the increased funding will provide K-12 students with safer, more conducive learning spaces, a move that has been welcomed by educators and community leaders alike. Local school divisions will be able to apply for grant support to fast-track modernization projects that may have been delayed due to funding shortfalls.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Youngkin administration has framed the initiative as part of a broader effort to support Virginia&#8217;s educational system and improve outcomes for students. As schools across the state face aging infrastructure and capacity challenges, this investment aims to reduce disparities in facility quality, especially in underserved areas.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of our guiding principles since day one of the Youngkin Administration has been to provide safe, vibrant, and healthy learning environments for all of our students,” said Secretary of Education Aimee Guidera. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This investment in supporting new and refurbished school buildings makes it possible for every community in the commonwealth to have the means to provide a best-in-class education that prepares every student for success in our increasingly demanding knowledge- and skills-based economy.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Del. Candi Mundon King, D-Prince William, a member of the Commission on School Construction and Modernization, said that while she welcomed Youngkin’s proposal, she needed more information. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We have been screaming from the rooftops about more money for school construction and ensuring that localities have what they need, so I’m glad to see that he&#8217;s trying to get on board,” Mundon King said. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_41173" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:280px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/10/youngkin-seeks-additional-290-million-boost-for-school-construction/screenshot-2024-12-10-at-3-02-35-pm/" rel="attachment wp-att-41173"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-41173" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-10-at-3.02.35 PM-280x300.png" alt="" width="280" height="300" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-10-at-3.02.35 PM-280x300.png 280w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-10-at-3.02.35 PM-957x1024.png 957w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-10-at-3.02.35 PM-768x822.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-10-at-3.02.35 PM.png 1032w" sizes="(max-width: 280px) 100vw, 280px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Del. Candi Mundon King, D-Prince William, is a member of the Commission on School Construction and Modernization (Courtesy Candi Mundon King).</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It is clear that we need to put more money into school construction, but I can’t say more without seeing a fully fleshed out plan. So I’m looking forward to his presentation next week with the joint money committees so we can fully evaluate what this proposal actually is, and not just some slick press release that doesn’t go into detail.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In 2022, Youngkin’s first year in office, the General Assembly in a bipartisan effort approved a historic $1.2 billion investment in school construction, aiming to modernize aging facilities and reduce funding disparities among school divisions. The sweeping plan combined grants and loans to support renovations, new construction, and capacity expansion for K-12 schools across the commonwealth.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Of the $1.2 billion, about $850 million was allocated for grants. This included $400 million in formula-based grants, which provided each of Virginia’s 134 school divisions with a $1 million base allocation. The remaining $266 million was distributed based on the Local Composite Index (LCI) — a state funding formula that considers factors like property values, taxable sales and population data to assess a locality’s financial ability to support its schools.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another $450 million was funneled into the newly created School Construction Fund and Program, a competitive grant program designed to assist divisions with the most critical infrastructure needs. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">School systems with poor building conditions and limited financial capacity could apply for these funds to support construction, renovation, or expansion projects. This program is primarily funded by 98% of gaming revenue from Virginia’s four new casinos in Bristol, Danville, Portsmouth, and Norfolk. The fund is administered by the Virginia Board of Education.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia faces a mounting crisis with school infrastructure. Data released by the Virginia Department of Education in 2022 revealed that nearly 1,000 school buildings across the state are at least 50 years old. Replacing these facilities would cost more than $25 billion — a figure far beyond the capacity of most localities.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Traditionally, local governments have shouldered the financial burden of school construction, relying on local tax revenue. But for economically distressed areas, particularly in Southwest Virginia and Southside, this has become an increasingly difficult challenge due to population decline and economic hardship.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But in April, Youngkin </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/04/11/youngkin-vetoes-measure-to-let-va-localities-increase-sales-tax-to-pay-for-school-construction/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">vetoed a bill</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> lawmakers sent to his desk that would have allowed localities to implement a 1% sales tax to help cover the costs of school construction and modernization.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The </span><a href="https://legacylis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?241+sum+SB14" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">proposal</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> required voter approval through a referendum before the tax could be enacted by local governments.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin acknowledged that school construction is a “worthy cause” but argued that Virginia has already taken substantial steps to address those costs. He contended that citizens should not face additional taxes, particularly the $1.5 billion annually that would have been raised by the 1% sales tax.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The commonwealth should pursue a tax policy that unleashes economic development and prioritizes job and wage growth through innovative reforms,” Youngkin said in his </span><a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?241+amd+SB14AG" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">veto</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. “These reforms must allow hardworking Virginians to keep more of their money, not less; any proposal that increases the cost of living and the cost of business is not a policy we should pursue.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Prior to 2022, state assistance for school construction was limited, with much of it coming from the Literary Fund, a state-managed pool of money established in Virginia’s Constitution. Funded by sources such as unclaimed lottery winnings, criminal fines, and unclaimed property, the Literary Fund historically provided low-interest loans to support school construction and debt service for technology. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, in recent years, much of the fund’s revenue was redirected to cover teacher retirement costs, leaving fewer resources for school building projects.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The 2022 legislative session retooled the Literary Fund’s loan program, significantly increasing its impact. Lawmakers raised the maximum loan amount from $7.5 million to $25 million and capped the interest rate at 2%. These changes made it more feasible for school divisions to finance major construction projects at a lower cost.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the state’s total contribution now approaching $2 billion, education advocates are hopeful the increased funding will lead to long-term improvements in school facilities and better learning conditions for students throughout the commonwealth.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia Board of Education President Grace Creasey said Tuesday that the panel will prioritize “those school divisions in greatest need that have missed out on prior grant opportunities,” especially rural divisions. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We also know that school divisions are eager to adopt seat time flexibility and competency-based models which requires us to design learning environments and spaces differently. This new investment will make this possible,” Creasey said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
         </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
