<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Chesterfield County Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/place/chesterfield-county/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/place/chesterfield-county/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 16:58:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Chesterfield County Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/place/chesterfield-county/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Virginia to host world’s first fusion power plant</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/18/virginia-to-host-worlds-first-fusion-power-plant/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Paullin]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 10:28:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dominion energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fusion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Glenn youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nuclear energy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Virginia could soon make history as the home of the world’s first nuclear fusion power plant, state officials and private sector leaders announced Tuesday. Commonwealth Fusion Systems (CFS), a fusion power company founded in 2018 in Cambridge, Mass., unveiled plans to build the groundbreaking facility on a 100-acre site at James River Industrial Park in [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="576" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-aerial-2000px-1024x576.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-aerial-2000px-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-aerial-2000px-300x169.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-aerial-2000px-768x432.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-aerial-2000px-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-aerial-2000px.jpg 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A rendering of the Commonwealth Fusion Systems proposal for Chesterfield County. (Courtesy of Commonwealth Fusion Systems)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia could soon make history as the home of the world’s first nuclear fusion power plant, state officials and private sector leaders announced Tuesday.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Commonwealth Fusion Systems (CFS), a fusion power company founded in 2018 in Cambridge, Mass., unveiled plans to build the groundbreaking facility on a 100-acre site at James River Industrial Park in Chesterfield County. The plant, expected to generate 400 megawatts of electricity — enough to power 150,000 homes — could be operational by the early 2030s.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Commonwealth Fusion Systems plans on building the world’s first grid scale commercial fusion power plant in the world, full stop, and it’s going to be right here in the commonwealth of Virginia,” Gov. Glenn Youngkin said at a presentation of the undertaking at Richmond’s Patrick Henry Building.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Unlike traditional nuclear power plants that rely on fission, fusion replicates the energy-producing process of the sun, offering a cleaner and more sustainable power source. The project, which would occupy about 25 acres of the site, signals Virginia’s growing role in shaping future energy solutions. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The announcement comes as Virginia’s energy needs are surging, driven by the rapid growth of data centers that power big tech operations. These facilities consume enormous amounts of  electricity and water to process and cool computer systems.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_41549" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2204px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/20241217_141031-1/"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-41549" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286.jpg" alt="" width="2204" height="1391" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286.jpg 2204w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286-300x189.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286-1024x646.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286-768x485.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286-1536x969.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/20241217_141031-1-scaled-e1734476114286-2048x1293.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2204px) 100vw, 2204px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Republican Gov. Glenn Youngkin speaks during an announcement with Commonwealth Fusion Systems Tuesday. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A report from the nonpartisan Joint Legislative Audit Review Commission (JLARC) released last week found that energy demand from data centers could triple from about 10,000 megawatts today to about 30,000 megawatts by 2040 if infrastructure, like new transmission lines, were already available.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia’s two largest utilities, Dominion Energy and Appalachian Power Company, are already exploring small modular nuclear reactors to meet rising  energy demands, with Dominion also investing in offshore wind, solar and natural gas. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fusion power offers another path to clean energy, avoiding emissions that scientists link to  climate change and its increasingly intense and frequent storms. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fusion technology works by combining hydrogen isotopes — deuterium extracted from water and tritium from lithium — under extreme heat and pressure, using powerful magnets to fuse the elements. The process generates heat, which boils water to create steam that spins a turbine, producing electricity. The byproduct is helium.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our customers’ growing needs for reliable, carbon-free power benefits from as diverse a menu of power generation options as possible, and in that spirit, we are delighted to assist CFS in their efforts,” </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">said Dominion Energy Virginia President Edward H. Baine, in a statement.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">CFS selected the Chesterfield site after conducting a global search. The company will lease the land from Dominion Energy. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To secure the project, Virginia offered $1 million from the Virginia Energy Clean Energy Innovation Bank, $1 million from Chesterfield County, and a sales and use tax exemption for the plant’s equipment. The company has also received U.S. Department of Energy funding. Youngkin said the project would bring “billions” in economic development and create “hundreds” of jobs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">CFS is currently building its </span><a href="https://cfs.energy/technology/sparc" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">SPARC demonstration plant</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in Massachusetts, a project that will pave the way for the ARC technology planned for Chesterfield. While the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California achieved a major milestone in 2022 by demonstrating fusion using lasers, CFS employs a different approach. Their technology relies on a donut-shaped device called a tokamak to confine and fuse molecules.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_41547" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2000px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/cfs-arc-powerplant-2000px/"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-41547" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-powerplant-2000px.jpg" alt="" width="2000" height="1125" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-powerplant-2000px.jpg 2000w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-powerplant-2000px-300x169.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-powerplant-2000px-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-powerplant-2000px-768x432.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-powerplant-2000px-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  A rendering of the ARC donut shaped tokamak technology. (Courtesy of Commonwealth Fusion Systems)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“You won’t need a pipeline to bring the fuel in, or a smokestack for the exhaust,” said CFS co-founder and Chief Executive Officer Bob Mumgaard.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Unlike fission, which splits heavy atoms like uranium to produce energy — and leaves behind radioactive waste — fusion creates energy by fusing light atoms, explained Alex Creely, CFS director of tokamak operations.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of the big advantages of fusion is that it doesn’t produce any long lived waste material, and there’s no risk of some kind of meltdown event,” Creely said. “It&#8217;s a very safe energy source — something that you can live right next to and feel very comfortable with.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Del. Rip Sullivan, D-Fairfax, said in a statement Tuesday that he will introduce legislation to define fusion energy in state code. The energy source would be allowed as &#8220;zero-carbon electricity&#8221; under the Virginia Clean Economy Act, a 2020 law aimed at  decarbonizing the state’s electric grid. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Since the VCEA’s passage, we have succeeded in driving energy innovation in the commonwealth, and today marks another important step in what has been a remarkably successful effort — a step that would not have been possible had Virginia declined or abandoned the opportunity and responsibility it took to lead in clean energy,” Sullivan said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin emphasized that the project will be financed entirely by CFS, with no cost passed on to Dominion Energy ratepayers. The facility will operate as an independent l power producer, selling its electricity to specific customers through power purchase agreements or directly into the regional PJM Interconnection market.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It’s a reasonable hypothesis that the growth in data centers in Virginia will very happily take the power that is generated at this plant,” Youngkin said.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_41546" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2000px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/cfs-arc-facility-front-2000px/"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-41546" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-front-2000px.jpg" alt="" width="2000" height="1125" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-front-2000px.jpg 2000w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-front-2000px-300x169.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-front-2000px-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-front-2000px-768x432.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/CFS-ARC-facility-front-2000px-1536x864.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Another rendering of the Commonwealth Fusion Systems proposal for Chesterfield County. (Courtesy of Commonwealth Fusion Systems)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Preston Bryant, senior vice president at McGuireWoods Consulting, which was involved in the site selection process, said Virginia was chosen in part because the Nuclear Regulatory Commission determined  months ago that fusion technology does not require a federal license like fission and can instead be approved at the state level.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The project will still need several state permits, including a radioactive materials license from the Virginia Department of Health, and a </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">certificate of convenience and public necessity from the State Corporation Commission. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kristen Cullen, vice president of global policy and public affairs at CFS, said additional approvals may include an air permit from the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality for backup generators during emergencies and potentially a storm water discharge permit, depending on the site-design.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bryant noted that it was “a coincidence” that the selected site was initially chosen by Dominion for a proposed natural gas plant before the utility relocated that project to the nearby, former coal-fired Chesterfield Power Station. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The announcement followed discussions with  local environmental groups, which expressed some support for the project, but also raised questions about its impact.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Considering rising energy demand in Virginia driven by data centers and that most folks in the environmental world are not in support of more gas infrastructure, SMRs or hydrogen energy, this seems like a promising solution, if and when it actually comes online,” said Melissa Thomas, senior organizer with Mothers out Front, a climate advocacy group. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thomas also raised questions about whether the plant’s backup power would rely on gas-powered systems or electric alternatives.</span></p>
<p><em>Editor&#8217;s note:</em> This story was corrected to explain the upcoming legislation from Del. Rip Sullivan, D-Fairfax, and how fusion is allowed under the Virginia Clean Economy Act.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>FEMA’s disaster recovery centers have closed and more Virginia headlines</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/femas-disaster-recovery-centers-have-closed-and-more-virginia-headlines/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Staff Report]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>staffreport@virginiamercury.com (Staff Report)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 10:05:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News to Know]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news to know]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=41474</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[• “For now, ‘Dreamers’ will be shut out of the health care marketplace in Virginia and 18 other states.”— The Associated Press • “FEMA’s disaster recovery centers have closed, but SBA center remains open.”— Cardinal News • “Pedestrian and cyclist fatalities have doubled in Fairfax County this year, study finds.”— FFXnow • “Chesterfield School leaders [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic-300x200.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic-768x512.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The state Capitol. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury) </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">• “For now, ‘Dreamers’ will be shut out of the health care marketplace in Virginia and 18 other states.”— </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/migrant-health-care-dreamers-lawsuit-504c8f05b3d93538cb7292318c267441" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Associated Press</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">• “FEMA’s disaster recovery centers have closed, but SBA center remains open.”— </span><a href="https://cardinalnews.org/2024/12/11/femas-disaster-recovery-centers-have-closed-but-sba-center-remains-open/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cardinal News</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">• “Pedestrian and cyclist fatalities have doubled in Fairfax County this year, study finds.”— </span><a href="https://www.ffxnow.com/2024/12/11/pedestrian-and-cyclist-fatalities-have-doubled-in-fairfax-county-this-year-study-finds/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">FFXnow</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">• “Chesterfield School leaders pass revised transgender policy after debate.”— </span><a href="https://www.wtvr.com/news/local-news/chesterfield-transgender-policy-dec-10-2024" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">CBS6</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">• “Guides defy administration to offer student-led tours of UVA.”— </span><a href="https://www.wvtf.org/news/2024-12-11/guides-defy-administration-to-offer-student-led-tours-of-uva" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">WVTF</span></a></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Youngkin shares update on Helene damage in Virginia, urges to not be “distracted” by climate change</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/04/youngkin-shares-update-on-helene-damage-in-virginia-urges-to-not-be-distracted-by-climate-change/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Paullin]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 20:16:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[emissions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[flooding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hurricane helene]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Southwest Virginia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40310</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Restoration efforts in Southwest Virginia continue after Hurricane Helene’s deadly impact, as Republican Gov. Glenn Youngkin asserted that blaming the intense storm and the future unpredictability of weather on climate change was a distraction. While giving an update on damage assessments from the storm that made landfall in Florida last week and dumped several inches [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="680" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/unnamed-4-1024x680.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/unnamed-4-1024x680.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/unnamed-4-300x199.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/unnamed-4-768x510.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/unnamed-4.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Gov. Glenn Youngkin, in blue jeans, assesses storm damage caused by Hurricane Helene in Grayson County on Sept. 29, 2024. (Courtesy of Christian Martinez, Office of Governor Glenn Youngkin)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Restoration efforts in Southwest Virginia continue after Hurricane Helene’s deadly impact, as Republican Gov. Glenn Youngkin asserted that blaming the intense storm and the future unpredictability of weather on climate change was a distraction.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While giving an update on damage assessments from the storm that made landfall in Florida last week and dumped several inches of rain, with two confirmed tornados, in the mountainous regions of Virginia, Youngkin urged people to call 1-800-621-3362, go to FEMA.gov or use a FEMA app download to seek help and start documenting the application process for federal recovery funding.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Also, there are regional centers that are being established by FEMA and (partner)with the Virginia Department of Emergency Management in the area,” Youngkin said, adding people are going door-to-door to help people fill out forms as part of the Major Disaster Declaration the state </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/02/post-helene-virginia-granted-major-disaster-declaration-access-to-federal-funding-for-recovery/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">received</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This is a really important process,” Youngkin said. “Many people don’t know how to fill out these forms. Getting them the help that they need is critically important.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">During the update from federal, state and local officials at the Virginia Department of Emergency Management Emergency Operations Center in North Chesterfield Friday morning, VDEM spokesman John Elmore reported that 519 homes had been counted as damaged so far, with 44 destroyed, and 475 damaged or affected. The total number of impacted businesses, ranging from small ones to large manufacturers, had climbed to 83. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These counts, which don’t include damages to local government buildings, are expected to go up. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Two people died in the immediate wake of the storm, and Youngkin said that everybody has been accounted for. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">About 13,700 people are still without power in the region, Youngkin said, after about 96% of outages had been restored. Crews are using helicopters to deliver telephone poles to the hard to reach areas that remain. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Out of the 287 cell-phone service towers that were knocked out, 14 still needed to be fixed, the governor added.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Furthermore, 28 water systems are under a boil advisory, and Youngkin urged everyone in the region to flush systems and seek replacement pumps, particularly for well users that comprise a vast majority of residents in the area.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Schools in “many counties” remained closed Friday, while others were having delays, Youngkin said. Waivers have been requested by the federal government so meal services for disadvantaged families could be extended to all school children. About 40,000 meals had been given out, in addition to grassroots efforts, as a medical reserve corps of professionals from other regions in the states have trekked to the impacted area to help with medication, oxygen tanks and wheelchairs that “have been just washed away.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Two primary roads remain impassible, and 52 secondary rods are closed, and U.S. Route 58 has about a 1.5 mile stretch that is “absolutely impossible,” Youngkin added.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This is going to be a long restoration rebuild process, but I am confident that if we can just keep focus, and not allow the standard ‘it’s been two weeks now and we’re moving on to the next issue’ to settle in, because I will not allow that to happen,” Youngkin said, adding that Southwest Virginia will rebuild “stronger than it was before.”</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40312" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2560px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/20241004_090424-1/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-40312" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="2560" height="1441" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241004_090424-1-2048x1153.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Republican Gov. Glenn Youngkin speaks to the staff at the Virginia Department of Emergency Management. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While taking questions from reporters, Youngkin declined to share his thoughts about climate change’s influence when a Virginia Mercury reporter asked about it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Nobody get distracted by that question,” said Youngkin, who in 2022 acknowledged climate change was a “</span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/business-virginia-utilities-nuclear-power-generation-df7fa2571b5d875ac1fe9af1e0b52c35" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">threat</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">” in an interview about his energy plan, which called for a re-evaluation of the state’s Virginia Clean Economy Act. The landmark 2020 VCEA seeks to decarbonize the grid by mid-century to halt human-caused </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/06/12/as-smoke-from-canada-enters-virginia-research-links-climate-change-with-more-frequent-wildfires/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">climate change</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We are right now in a moment of providing people a pathway back to hope,” Youngkin continued, before talking about the gratitude he received for his visits, including an afternoon visit by U.S. Sen. JD Vance, R-Ohio, the Republican vice presidential nominee, on Thursday. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Yesterday, when Senator Vance was there and everyone was saying ‘thank you for coming,’ this is a region of Virginia and America that has historically been forgotten,” Youngkin said. “I just have no time for folks who are trying to politicize this moment.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">FEMA administrator Deanne Criswell said on the CBS news program </span><a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/deanne-criswell-fema-administrator-face-the-nation-transcript-09-29-2024/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Face the Nation</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> on Sunday that  “In the past, when we would look at damage from hurricanes, it was primarily wind damage, with some water damage.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“But now we’re seeing so much more water damage, and I think that is a result of the warm waters, which is a result of climate change,” Criswell said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After FEMA had denied relief requests from residents in the region in 2022 and 2021, the state dipped into $830 million in revenues from a carbon-market that requires electricity producers to purchase allowances for carbon emissions as another attempt to halt climate change.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The state directed $29 million of the funds, which were initially intended to increase flood protections and make homes energy efficient, to provide relief to residents. Youngkin pulled Virginia out of the market — the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative — calling it a “hidden tax,” since utilities can recover the costs of allowances from </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/05/regulators-approve-request-from-dominion-to-drop-rggi-fee-on-customer-bills/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">ratepayers</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Legislators used a budget amendment to appropriate any unused funds, which amounted to about $40 million at the start of the year, according to a </span><a href="https://www.wvtf.org/news/2024-10-03/youngkin-virginia-legislators-mull-legislative-steps-in-helene-recovery" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">report </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">by Radio IQ. A special session would be needed to pass a similar budget amendment or legislation to support the region ahead of the regular session scheduled to start in January.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I’ve got to assess what we need,” Youngkin said when asked if he would call one.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Virginia is the third loneliest state in the country and more headlines</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/virginia-is-the-third-loneliest-state-in-the-country-and-more-headlines/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Staff Report]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>staffreport@virginiamercury.com (Staff Report)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 09:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News to Know]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news to know]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=40251</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[• “Virginia is the third loneliest state in the country.” — Axios  • “Virginia Department of Health says to avoid natural water bodies after Helene.” — 8News • “Is Amanda Chase still in the GOP? Intraparty feud risks her state Senate ambitions.” — The Daily Progress • “Judge: State shakeup of Loudoun juvenile court unit [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic-300x200.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/NewsToKnowgraphic-768x512.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The state Capitol. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury) </p><p>• <span style="font-weight: 400;">“Virginia is the third loneliest state in the country.” — </span><a href="https://www.axios.com/local/washington-dc/2024/10/01/virginia-is-the-third-loneliest-state-in-the-country" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Axios</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p>• <span style="font-weight: 400;">“Virginia Department of Health says to avoid natural water bodies after Helene.” — </span><a href="https://www.wric.com/news/virginia-news/virginia-department-of-health-says-to-avoid-natural-water-bodies-after-helene/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">8News</span></a></p>
<p>• <span style="font-weight: 400;">“Is Amanda Chase still in the GOP? Intraparty feud risks her state Senate ambitions.” — </span><a href="https://dailyprogress.com/news/local/government-politics/is-amanda-chase-still-in-the-gop-intraparty-feud-risks-her-state-senate-ambitions/article_e36769a4-7f54-11ef-87ee-57ebfcd982f3.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Daily Progress</span></a></p>
<p>• <span style="font-weight: 400;">“Judge: State shakeup of Loudoun juvenile court unit will have &#8216;potentially devastating effect.&#8217;” — </span><a href="https://www.loudountimes.com/0local-or-not/1local/judge-state-shakeup-of-loudoun-juvenile-court-unit-will-have-potentially-devastating-effect/article_47a1683e-60a1-11ef-9136-13d85add76a1.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Loudoun Times</span></a></p>
<p>• <span style="font-weight: 400;">“Georgia requires ballots to be hand-counted in November. Why Virginia won’t be next.” — </span><a href="https://cardinalnews.org/2024/10/01/georgia-requires-ballots-to-be-hand-counted-in-november-why-virginia-wont-be-next/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cardinal News</span></a></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>As early voting starts in Virginia, political parties rally their bases</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/20/as-early-voting-starts-in-virginia-political-parties-rally-their-bases/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>cwoods@virginiamercury.com (Charlotte Rene Woods)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 09:30:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[early voting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40098</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Starting Friday, voters across Virginia can begin casting their ballots in this year’s critical elections for the White House, a U.S. Senate seat, and  the state’s 11 congressional districts that will not only impact the future of the commonwealth but also help shape next year’s gubernatorial race.  An amendment to the Constitution of Virginia and [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/201103_5th_dist_voting-0022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Voters at the Agricultural Service Center in Buckingham, Va., Nov. 3, 2020. (Parker Michels-Boyce / For the Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Starting Friday, voters across Virginia can begin casting their ballots in this year’s critical elections for the White House, a U.S. Senate seat, and  the state’s 11 congressional districts that will not only impact the future of the commonwealth but also help shape next year’s gubernatorial race. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An </span><a href="https://www.elections.virginia.gov/election-law/proposed-amendments-for-2024/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">amendment</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to the Constitution of Virginia and a variety of local offices are also on the ballot. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the Sep. 20 kick-off of the 45-day early voting period, Virginians have the option to vote in person until Nov. 2 at their local election offices or send absentee ballots by mail. This marks a turning point in campaign season, as both parties ramp up rallies and events to energize their bases.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Just south of Richmond, Gov. Glenn Youngkin will attend a rally at Chesterfield County Airport Saturday. He will be joined by U.S. Rep. Rob Wittman, R-Westmoreland, Bill Moher, the Republican nominee in Virginia’s 4th Congressional District, and Hung Cao, who is seeking to oust U.S. Sen. Tim Kaine, D-Va. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin in a statement Thursday encouraged “every Virginia citizen to make a plan and vote early” to ensure that each vote is counted.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“You can trust that Virginia’s elections are secure with clean voter rolls, secure paper ballots, certified counting machines and well-trained election officials,” he said. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_36382" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/09/22/with-start-of-early-voting-virginia-begins-high-stakes-election-season/img_5764/" rel="attachment wp-att-36382"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-36382" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/IMG_5764-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/IMG_5764-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/IMG_5764-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/IMG_5764-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/IMG_5764-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/IMG_5764-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Gov. Glenn Youngkin at an early voting rally in Henrico County in 2023. (Graham Moomaw/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Later on Saturday, Youngkin will join Derrick Anderson, the Republican nominee in the 7th District, at an Early Voting Rally at the Professional Building Maintenance in Fredericksburg. The event is set to begin at 1:30 p.m.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Former President Donald Trump has yet to return to the </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/28/trump-rallies-in-chesapeake-backed-by-virginia-governor-gop-leaders/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">campaign trail in Virginia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, a state where he trails Vice President Kamala Harris, his Democratic opponent, by several percentage points </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/new-polling-finds-harris-ahead-of-trump-by-a-comfortable-margin-in-virginia/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">according to recent polling</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But Rally Virginia is hosting a Women’s Rally for the Republican presidential nominee at the Trump Winery in Charlottesville on Saturday. The event  starts at 2 p.m., featuring guest speaker U.S. Rep. Elise Stefanik, R-NY.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Team Trump Virginia has been working diligently to ensure an impressive  — and winning — performance in Virginia’s early vote. Across the commonwealth, we have been priming our voters to turn out in record numbers. Trump Force 47 will be mobilizing our supporters to vote,” said Jeff Ryer, a campaign spokesman. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While much of Southwest Virginia leans Republican, Democrats are firing up their bases there with some events, like an early voting kickoff event in Roanoke Friday to support Democratic candidates for city council and mayor, a canvassing kickoff on Saturday in Bristol with local elected officials, ad a Sunday gathering in Montgomery County with 9th District Democratic nominee Karen Baker.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Urging citizens of the Southwest region of the state to take advantage of early voting, Bristol city councilor Neil Osborne said, “Don’t risk having something unexpected come up on Election Day.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kaine will jaunt around the state for various early voting events over the weekend to support Democratic congressional candidates in competitive races — such as Eugene Vindman in the 7th District, Suhas Subramanyam in the 10th and Missy Cotter Smasal in the 2nd — and to boost his own re-election campaign. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_38296" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/17/what-to-watch-in-virginias-congressional-primaries-this-week/8a748f58-b6e5-45fd-accd-13f3812a0875-9043-0000032d6f9cb752/" rel="attachment wp-att-38296"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-38296" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/8A748F58-B6E5-45FD-ACCD-13F3812A0875-9043-0000032D6F9CB752-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/8A748F58-B6E5-45FD-ACCD-13F3812A0875-9043-0000032D6F9CB752-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/8A748F58-B6E5-45FD-ACCD-13F3812A0875-9043-0000032D6F9CB752-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/8A748F58-B6E5-45FD-ACCD-13F3812A0875-9043-0000032D6F9CB752-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/8A748F58-B6E5-45FD-ACCD-13F3812A0875-9043-0000032D6F9CB752-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/8A748F58-B6E5-45FD-ACCD-13F3812A0875-9043-0000032D6F9CB752.jpg 1776w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  U.S. Sen Tim Kaine, D-Va., will jaunt around the state for various early voting events over the weekend. (Graham Moomaw/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Friday gatherings will also be hosted with Democratic challengers Leslie Mehta in Chesterfield County, who wants to unseat Wittman and 5th District candidate Gloria Witt. The 5th District election </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/16/amid-internal-gop-feud-in-the-5th-district-democrat-gloria-witt-sees-her-chance/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">could test the effect</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> of GOP infighting over nominee John McGuire, a state senator from Goochland, and Rep. Bob Good, R-Farmville, whose supporters have mounted a write-in campaign after the incumbent lost his primary this summer. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I think we’ve already held over 1,000 events across the Commonwealth, but (there’s) more to come,” said </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democratic Party of Virginia chairwoman Susan Swecker. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This is a big week with the kickoff for early voting.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On boosting awareness of the different campaigns and to encourage early voting, Swecker said that Democrats have opened 25 campaign offices around the state and hired 150 people.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As election seasons become increasingly competitive, early voting has emerged as a vital part of the electoral process, and Virginia is no exception.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Early voting allows voters to participate on their own schedules, whether by visiting local election offices or mailing in absentee ballots. In recent elections, both parties have recognized its significance — a shift that is reshaping the strategies of political campaigns.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Voters like the convenience of early voting options,” said Mark Rozell, a political scientist at George Mason University. “Importantly, Republicans have adjusted to the reality that early voting is here to stay.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Last year, Youngkin’s political action committee </span><a href="https://richmond.com/news/state-regional/government-politics/glenn-youngkin-virginia-politics-election-day/article_f250116c-6936-11ee-9bad-2b7f054e466e.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">invested millions</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> into the promotion of early voting initiatives, following years of GOP opposition to the expanded options. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Past GOP leadership claims that early voting leads to fraud likely had some negative impact on Republican turnout,” Rozell said. “The smart strategy now is to embrace the reality and use flexible voting options as a means to mobilize core supporters.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But opponents of early voting are not devoid of credible arguments, Rozell added. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“A lot can happen in October that might affect the viewpoints of those who voted in Virginia in late September. You can’t take it back once you’ve voted, so you better be sure when you vote that your opinion will not change under any circumstance.”</span></p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Ways to vote early</h4>

	
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To vote early in-person, registered voters may go to the general registrar’s office for the jurisdiction in which they are registered, present their ID and cast a ballot. The location of the general registrar’s offices for all jurisdictions can be found on the Virginia Department of Elections’ </span><a href="https://vote.elections.virginia.gov/VoterInformation/PublicContactLookup" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">website</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, in addition to </span><a href="https://www.elections.virginia.gov/registration/voterid/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">a list</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> of acceptable forms of identification. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Requested absentee ballots will also be mailed beginning Friday, including ballots to registered military and overseas voters. Any registered voter can request an absentee ballot either in person, by mail, </span><a href="https://vote.elections.virginia.gov/VoterInformation" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">online</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> or by contacting their general registrar’s office. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Registered voters do not need a reason to request an absentee ballot, which can be dropped off at the general registrar’s office or polling location on Election Day. Absentee ballots returned by mail must be postmarked no later than Nov. 5 and received by noon on Nov. 8.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The deadline to request a mailed absentee ballot is Oct. 25, but amid national U.S. Postal Service delays, state officials suggest those voting by mail </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/05/virginias-top-elections-official-warns-of-possible-delays-in-mail-in-voting-this-year/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">do so as soon as possible</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The deadline to register to vote and cast a regular ballot is Oct. 15. After that date, voters can still register and vote on Election Day using same-day registration, but they will cast a provisional ballot. Same-day registration must be done in person, either at an early voting location within the voter’s jurisdiction or at their polling place.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some jurisdictions offer early in-person voting at satellite locations in addition to the general registrar’s office. Dates and times vary by j</span><a href="https://www.elections.virginia.gov/casting-a-ballot/early-voting-office-locations/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">urisdiction</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Curbside voting is available for voters with disabilities and those 65 and older who prefer to vote in person. For details on voting hours, additional locations, and ballot drop boxes, contact your local registrar&#8217;s office.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For more information on the races and candidates, visit The Mercury’s </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/voter-guide/2024-virginia-voter-guide/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">2024 Voter Guide</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
