<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Election 2025 Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/category/election-2025/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/category/election-2025/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 06:58:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Election 2025 Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/category/election-2025/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Cifers triumphs in multi-round vote to represent GOP in state Senate District 10 special election</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/cifers-triumphs-in-multi-round-vote-to-represent-gop-in-state-senate-district-10-special-election/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 06:55:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McGuire]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Luther Cifers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia General Assembly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia Senate District 10]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia state Senate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=41493</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, emerged victorious in the Republican nomination contest for Virginia’s 10th Senate District during a mass meeting at the Goochland Rec Center. The meeting, which drew hundreds of Republican voters, began Friday evening and stretched into the early hours of Saturday as participants navigated a lengthy multi-ballot process [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="818" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-1024x818.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-1024x818.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-300x240.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM-768x614.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Screenshot-2024-12-14-at-1.48.00 AM.png 1094w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, won the Republican nomination in Virginia's Senate District 10 at a mass meeting in Goochland County early Saturday morning. (Courtesy of Luther Cifers campaign). </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, emerged victorious in the Republican nomination contest for Virginia’s 10th Senate District during a mass meeting at the Goochland Rec Center.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The meeting, which drew hundreds of Republican voters, began Friday evening and stretched into the early hours of Saturday as participants navigated a lengthy multi-ballot process to select a nominee from a crowded field of seven candidates. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cifers secured the majority needed to clinch the nomination, defeating a mix of seasoned politicians and newcomers in three rounds of voting.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cifers will now face Democrat Jack Trammel in the Jan. 7 special election to fill the vacancy left by Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland, who resigned after his recent election to Congress. The winner of the special election will serve the remainder of McGuire’s term, which runs until 2027.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other contenders included runner-up Duane Adams, the chairman of the Louisa County Board of Supervisors who previously ran for the Republican nomination in the district in 2023 but was defeated by McGuire​, and Amanda Chase, a former state senator from Chesterfield County who served in the Virginia Senate for eight years. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There were four other bids for the seat by Shayne Snavely, a veteran and former Chase aide, Jean Gannon, a Powhatan County real estate appraiser, Alex Cheatham, a recent college graduate, and Bryan Hamlet.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Luther emerged from a field of seven outstanding candidates who sought the nomination. The Republican Party of Virginia and I look forward to marching in lockstep with Luther and his team over the next three weeks in ensuring that he is victorious on January 7th and takes the oath of office on January 8th,” said Rich Anderson, the chairman of the Republican Party of Virginia.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the district’s strong Republican lean — with 62.8% of voters supporting former President Donald Trump and 67.8% backing Gov. Glenn Youngkin — Cifers is seen as the favorite in the upcoming election.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Republicans to choose Senate District 10 nominee to succeed McGuire</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/12/republicans-to-choose-senate-district-10-nominee-to-succeed-mcguire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 10:32:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Assembly 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2024 congressional elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mass meeting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sen. John McGuire]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senate District 10]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41471</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Republicans in Virginia’s 10th state Senate District will convene for a mass meeting on Friday to select their nominee in an upcoming special election. The vacancy was prompted by the resignation of Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland, who is set to leave his post after being elected to Congress​.  The meeting will take place at the [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/McGuire-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Rep.-elect John McGuire, R-Goochland, formally resigned his state Senate seat on Wednesday, clearing the way for a special election in Virginia's Senate District 10. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury) </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republicans in Virginia’s 10th state Senate District will convene for a mass meeting on Friday to select their nominee in an upcoming special election. The vacancy was prompted by the resignation of Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland, who is set to leave his post after being elected to Congress​. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The meeting will take place at the Goochland Rec Center, with registration running from 4:30 p.m. to 6:30 p.m., and proceedings beginning at 6:30 p.m. A total of seven candidates are vying to succeed McGuire. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Organized by local party committees, mass meetings require party members to gather at a designated time and place to publicly select a candidate. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Unlike secret ballots, voting is often conducted through a show of hands, voice vote, or other public method. Participants must remain present for multiple rounds of voting until one candidate secures a majority — typically more than 50% of the votes — to be declared the winner. This process can be lengthy, especially in races with a crowded field of candidates.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Once the GOP nominee is selected, they will face Democrat Jack Trammel in a special election on Jan. 7 set by Sen. Louise Lucas, D-Portsmouth, the Senate president pro tempore. The winner will serve out the remainder of McGuire’s term in the Senate, which ends in 2027.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Among the first Republicans to declare their candidacy for McGuire’s seat was Amanda Chase, a former state senator from Chesterfield County who served in the Virginia Senate for eight years. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Chase previously ran for re-election in 2023 but lost the GOP primary for her Chesterfield-based seat to Sen. Glen Sturtevant. To qualify for the 10th District race, Chase moved to Appomattox County, as Virginia law requires state legislators to live in the district they represent.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Joining the race is Shayne Snavely, an Amelia-based entrepreneur, veteran who was a former aide to Chase and worked on her failed 2021 gubernatorial campaign. Jean Gannon, a Powhatan County real estate appraiser and long-time Republican activist, has also thrown her hat into the ring. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Duane Adams, the chairman of the Louisa County Board of Supervisors, is making a bid for the seat as well. Adams previously ran for the Republican nomination in the district in 2023 but was defeated by McGuire​.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other contenders include Alex Cheatham, a recent college graduate aiming to make his political debut, and two late entrants: Luther Cifers, a businessman from Prince Edward County, and Bryan Hamlet, chairman of the Cumberland County Board of Supervisors​.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We have a pretty good selection among the group there. I don’t know everybody, but I think that they will all be competitive candidates in that district,” Rich Anderson, chairman of the Republican Party of Virginia, said in a phone interview. “Obviously as a conservative Republican leading the conservative party, I want to get a conservative Republican nominated.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Anderson said that the mass meeting could last late into the evening.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The process will probably require multiple ballots with that many people on the docket, so we’ll just see how it all turns out. I can’t predict who will walk away with all the marbles, but one of them will.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">David Richards, a political science professor at the University of Lynchburg, said that of the Republicans who have thrown their names in the ring for the special election to replace McGuire, “Chase is perhaps the best known or most notorious.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But Richards doubts that Chase will get her party’s nod. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The mass meeting nomination process caters to party members, and Chase has little credibility with the local party after being expelled by the Chesterfield GOP and being noticeably absent from the one candidates forum already held. And she has little credibility with local Republicans, which will hurt her chances.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Among the remaining six candidates, Adams has been very active beginning with his unsuccessful bid for the nomination in 2023, which McGuire won, Richards said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The key to these mass meetings is name recognition in a positive way. Aside from the candidate forum held in late November, there has not been much opportunity or time for candidates to get their message out. Their pre-existing connections will tip the scale, which is why I expect Adams to win the nomination.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Adams will still “get a run for his money” from Snavely, who also has a lot of party experience working for Chase earlier in his career, Richards added. “The other candidates have very low profiles, but Jean Gannon has been active in local GOP politics, which might help her.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">McGuire, who in June defeated incumbent U.S. Rep. Bob Good, R-Farmville, in one of the most viciously fought and expensive GOP primary battles nationwide this year, had kept Republicans </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/25/mcguire-still-hasnt-resigned-his-state-senate-seat-weeks-after-congressional-win/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">on edge for weeks</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> after winning his election against Democrat Gloria Witt on Nov. 5. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Typically, elected officials who win a new position resign from their current office within days to allow for a special election to be called promptly, ensuring the seat isn’t left vacant when the next legislative session begins in early January. However, McGuire delayed his departure, formally stepping down on Wednesday​.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In his official resignation letter, McGuire called his brief stint in the state Senate “the privilege of a lifetime” and said he hoped voters would choose “a strong candidate who loves We The People,” works well with others and who has “never wavered on our core Republican values.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">However, McGuire stopped short from publicly backing one of the seven candidates vying to succeed him. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I was not too surprised that McGuire has not endorsed anyone, especially Adams,” said Richards. “When McGuire announced he was primarying Bob Good, Adams was very vocal about McGuire’s decision, calling him a liar, so there does not seem to be much love lost there.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The 10th Senate District, which spans 11 localities from Lynchburg in the west to the suburbs of Richmond in the east, leans heavily Republican. The district backed President-elect Donald Trump with 62.8% of the vote last month and gave Republican Glenn Youngkin an even stronger 67.8% support during his successful 2021 gubernatorial campaign.</span></p>
<p><em>Editor&#8217;s note: This story has been updated to include the date for the special election set for Jan. 7.</em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Democratic group boosts Srinivasan, Singh in upcoming Virginia special elections</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/06/national-democratic-group-boosts-srinivassan-singh-in-upcoming-virginia-special-elections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlotte Rene Woods]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cwoods@virginiamercury.com (Charlotte Rene Woods)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 10:19:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Abortion Policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elections and Voting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Constitutional amendments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[special elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41051</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With a Republican-controlled White House, U.S. House and Senate on the horizon, some special elections in Virginia next month are the first opportunity for voters to challenge or reinforce Democratic majorities in the state legislature.   That’s why the Democratic Legislative Campaign Committee is putting a spotlight on Senate District 32 and House District 26.  After [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="Lawmakers are set to consider Gov. Glenn Youngkin&#039;s proposal to invest another $290 million for school construction needs during the upcoming legislative session which begins in January. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3697-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Lawmakers are set to consider Gov. Glenn Youngkin's proposal to invest another $290 million for school construction needs during the upcoming legislative session which begins in January. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With a Republican-controlled White House, U.S. House and Senate on the horizon, some special elections in Virginia next month are the first opportunity for voters to challenge or reinforce Democratic majorities in the state legislature.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That’s why the Democratic Legislative Campaign Committee is putting a spotlight on Senate District 32 and House District 26. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After winning a Democratic primary, Del. Kannan Srinivasan, D-Loudoun, will face off against Republican Tumay Harding to be elected to the Virginia Senate. He could succeed Sen. Suhas Subramanyam, who was elected to the U.S. Congress last month.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="Qvdt5FXd2u"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/08/virginia-prepares-for-special-elections-as-mcguire-subramanyam-head-to-congress-leaving-senate-seats-up-for-grabs/">Virginia prepares for special elections as McGuire, Subramanyam head to Congress</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia prepares for special elections as McGuire, Subramanyam head to Congress&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/08/virginia-prepares-for-special-elections-as-mcguire-subramanyam-head-to-congress-leaving-senate-seats-up-for-grabs/embed/#?secret=IIQqPK5bxX#?secret=Qvdt5FXd2u" data-secret="Qvdt5FXd2u" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Then, J.J. Singh, who won a Democratic primary for Loudoun County-based House District 26, could potentially succeed Srinivasan’s House seat. He faces Republican Ram Venkatachalam. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">DLCC director Heather Williams issued a statement noting that protecting Democrats’ slim majorities will “position us to be competitive in November when the entire House of Delegates is on the ballot alongside a competitive </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/25/spanberger-and-earle-sears-tied-in-first-2025-gubernatorial-poll/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">gubernatorial race</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democrats currently have a 21-19 edge in the Senate and a  51-48 lead in the House with Republican Glenn Youngkin as governor.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">She added that Virginia can be a key indicator of “what the fight ahead looks like” to build Democratic power in states amid the Republican majorities in federal government. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Fortifying the Democratic firewall in the states has never been more important, and that work starts in Virginia,” she said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Through the DLCC “spotlight” program, Srinivasan and Singh will be assisted in fundraising and can tap into DLCC experts on staff for advice or help with organizing. The group has boosted legislative candidates around the country and focuses on seats that are crucial for protecting or making majorities, said Sam Paisley, an interim communications director with DLCC. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Democratic majority can jumpstart planned constitutional amendments</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While DLCC is watching key state elections around the country for how they can support Democrats’ ability to balance out federal GOP majorities, Virginia’s Democratic majorities will be a key part of advancing planned amendments to the state’s constitution.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="j6PDqB758w"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/13/va-house-panel-advances-amendments-on-abortion-rights-marriage-equality-and-voting-rights/">Va. House panel advances amendments on abortion rights, marriage equality and voting rights</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Va. House panel advances amendments on abortion rights, marriage equality and voting rights&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/13/va-house-panel-advances-amendments-on-abortion-rights-marriage-equality-and-voting-rights/embed/#?secret=SmIsD8zngc#?secret=j6PDqB758w" data-secret="j6PDqB758w" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The amendments would enshrine abortion access protections into the constitution, remove a prohibition on same-sex marriage from it, and create an automatic process for formerly incarcerated people with felony convictions to have their rights restored. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia is the least-restrictive Southern state when it comes to abortion access. The matter was paramount in the 2023 state legislative elections as Democrats vowed to protect current law (and eventually enshrine it into the constitution) and many Republicans coalesced around a 15-week cap on most abortions. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Under current Virginia law, any abortion occurring in the third trimester requires approval from three doctors. The new amendment would reduce that threshold to one doctor, should a later stage abortion be deemed necessary to protect the life or mental health of the pregnant person or should their fetus be deemed not viable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With no national definition of fetal viability — which refers to the likelihood of a fetus being able to survive outside of the womb — doctors typically make the determination on a case-by-case basis.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Virginia, people with felony convictions are all but permanently disenfranchised from various rights, even after they’ve completed prison sentences. Previous governors’ administrations had streamlined a restoration process. Then Youngkin’s administration made it petition-based with unclear criteria. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That meant that hundreds of applicants this year were rejected — and therefore </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/23/these-virginians-wont-be-able-to-vote-next-month/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">unable to vote </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">in presidential and congressional elections — without knowing why. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This amendment creates a process that is bound by transparent rules and criteria that will apply equally to everybody,” the bill’s sponsor Del. Elizabeth Bennett-Parker, D-Alexandria said last month. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Meanwhile, the third amendment would allow Virginia to continue recognizing same-sex marriages should federal protections be undone, as they were with abortion protections. Since a 2006 amendment, </span><a href="https://law.lis.virginia.gov/constitution/article1/section15-A/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia’s constitution</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> defines marriage between a man and a woman. Though it’s been rendered moot since a 2015 Supreme Court of the United States decision, some lawmakers and LGBTQ advocates have stressed the importance of removing the prohibition in case that precedent were to fall (as Supreme Court judge Clarence Thomas has </span><a href="https://richmond.com/news/state-regional/government-politics/dem-lawmakers-want-to-put-same-sex-marriage-in-virginia-s-constitution/article_46aa7008-ab32-11ee-af3d-e79f1e61bf21.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">expressed interest</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in revisiting). </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While a Democrat-led panel was able to </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/13/va-house-panel-advances-amendments-on-abortion-rights-marriage-equality-and-voting-rights/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">advance</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> all three amendments earlier this month, the marriage equality one saw bipartisan support.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Placing these policies into the constitution would make them less subject to partisan shifts in the legislature or governors’ mansion — but it’s also a longer process than just passing one law. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Constitutional amendments have to clear both chambers of the legislature two years in a row, with a House of Delegates election in between. From there, they can appear as ballot referendums for voters around the state to approve or reject. This means voters could weigh in by November 2026 — if the proposals pass in 2025 and earlier in 2026. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Senate District 10 special election still unclear</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While Srinivasan and Singh have the chance to lock down Democratic control in each chamber, the Republican-leaning state senate seat still hasn’t had its special election set.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="z3bFbsFIoK"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/25/mcguire-still-hasnt-resigned-his-state-senate-seat-weeks-after-congressional-win/">McGuire still hasn’t resigned his state Senate seat weeks after congressional win</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;McGuire still hasn’t resigned his state Senate seat weeks after congressional win&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/25/mcguire-still-hasnt-resigned-his-state-senate-seat-weeks-after-congressional-win/embed/#?secret=CWP1I5rNtR#?secret=z3bFbsFIoK" data-secret="z3bFbsFIoK" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sen. John McGuire, R-Goochland’s election to Congress last month will create a vacancy in Senate District 10 — but he has not yet formally </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/25/mcguire-still-hasnt-resigned-his-state-senate-seat-weeks-after-congressional-win/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">resigned </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">from his current position. </span></p>
<p><a href="https://law.lis.virginia.gov/vacode/title24.2/chapter2/section24.2-216/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">S</span></a><a href="https://law.lis.virginia.gov/vacode/title24.2/chapter2/section24.2-216/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">tate law</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> outlines that special elections must be set within 30 days of a vacancy or notification of it — whichever occurs first.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Last week, Senate Minority Leader Ryan McDougle, R-Hanover told The Mercury that he was confident there would also be an election to replace McGuire on Jan. 7, but did not elaborate further. As of this week, he relayed that there are no new updates. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">McGuire, who was reached by phone, said to send him an email. He did not respond by the time of this publication. </span></p>
<p><em>Editor&#8217;s note: This article has been updated to correct the spelling of Del. Kannan Srinavasan&#8217;s name. </em><br style="font-weight: 400;" />        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trump’s victory sets the stage for high-stakes Virginia elections in 2025</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/20/trumps-victory-sets-the-stage-for-high-stakes-virginia-elections-in-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 10:32:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aaron Rouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abigail Spanberger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Babur Lateef]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ghazala Hashmi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Miyares]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jay Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Curran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shannon Taylor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia gubernatorial election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia House of Delegates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Winsome Earle-Sears]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40894</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Former President Donald Trump’s return to the White House following the Nov. 5 election is already sending ripples through Virginia politics and setting the stage for an intense 2025 election cycle in the commonwealth. With control of the governorship and the House of Delegates on the line, both parties are strategizing to leverage the shifting [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="741" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2190-1024x741.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2190-1024x741.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2190-300x217.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2190-768x556.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2190-1536x1112.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2190-2048x1483.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Executive Mansion in Richmond's Capitol Square, the official residence of the governor of Virginia. (Markus Schmidt/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Former President Donald Trump’s return to the White House following the Nov. 5 election is already sending ripples through Virginia politics and setting the stage for an intense 2025 election cycle in the commonwealth. With control of the governorship and the House of Delegates on the line, both parties are strategizing to leverage the shifting political landscape to their advantage.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I think we’re in a crucial moment in Virginia’s history, this is a moment where every single vote, every election and every voice can make a lasting difference, especially after the election of Donald Trump,” Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, said on a video call with reporters on Friday.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The 2017 elections in Virginia offer a compelling precedent. That year — Trump’s first in office —  galvanized the Democratic base, leading to a stunning 15-seat gain in the House and leaving the Republicans with a razor-thin 50–49 advantage. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Suburban districts that had long been Republican strongholds, including in the Richmond area and in Northern Virginia, flipped blue as many moderate voters reacted against the president’s divisive rhetoric and policies. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Additionally, Democrat Ralph Northam’s decisive victory in the gubernatorial race — he defeated Republican Ed Gillespie by a 9-point margin (54-45%) — underscored the state’s shift toward progressive politics, fueled by high turnout among women, young voters, and minorities united by their dislike for an incumbent president whom Hillary Clinton, the Democratic nominee, had defeated in the commonwealth with 49.75-44.43%. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Two years later, in 2019, Democrats picked up six more seats in the House, marking the first time that the party held control of both legislative and executive branches in Virginia since 1993.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Following Trump’s recent win, Virginia Democrats are hoping for a similar wave in 2025, betting that the Republican’s polarizing presidency will once again energize their coalition. With abortion rights, climate policy, and education likely to be central issues, Democrats believe they can maintain their control of the legislature and win back the Executive Mansion by appealing to suburban and urban voters alarmed by Trump’s policies.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“One of the things about Virginia is that you can never really predict what will happen, because Virginia voters are so in tune and aware of what’s going on. They don’t go for a lot of BS, which is why Virginia rejected Donald Trump three times,” Scott said, referring also to the presidential elections in 2020 and 2024, which Trump lost in the commonwealth. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40738" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/06/virginia-leaders-react-to-trump-win-as-harris-keeps-the-commonwealth-blue/img_3713/" rel="attachment wp-att-40738"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-40738" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_3713-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Virginia House Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, speaks to members of the media on Nov. 6, 2024. (Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginians, Scott said, pay “very close attention to what happens in DC right now,” and they will take note if Trump keeps his promise to abolish the U.S. Department of Education or eliminate federal jobs in Northern Virginia — actions that could fire up the Democratic party’s base.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republicans, on the other hand, are hoping for a reverse dynamic. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Trump’s successful third White House bid has emboldened Virginia conservatives, particularly in rural areas where his support remains robust, and the GOP campaigns of next year are likely to focus on economic issues and a law-and-order message to woo suburban voters who have drifted toward Democrats in recent cycles.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The Republican Party of Virginia and Trump very handily carried a number of Virginia House of Delegates districts that either Republicans lost by a small amount last year or won by a small amount,” Rich Anderson, the chairman of the Virginia GOP, said in a recent phone interview. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“So it’s going to be vital for us next year to take those Republicans who showed up for President Trump and to get them out in the 2025 election cycle. We will work hard in doing that because next year is a crucial year for us in the House of Delegates elections, and the Democrats only have a one seat margin. If we work hard, then we can flip it back, and that, of course, helps our nominees for governor, lieutenant governor and attorney general.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">David Richards, a political science professor at the University of Lynchburg, said that the current Democratic majorities in the House of Delegates (51-49) and the state Senate (21-19) are too close for either party to relax. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“If Virginia acts like 2021, where it voted against the party in power in Washington, then the GOP will have an uphill climb,” Richards said. “The question is how far along Trump’s agenda will be by the fall of 2025. If things are going well, the GOP could draft on that success, but if things are chaotic, then that will be a problem.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Deputy House Minority Leader Israel O’Quinn, R-Washington, said that Republicans plan to seize on a lagging enthusiasm among Democratic voters this year in order to flip the House in 2025. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_30127" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2022-ga-2-6/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-30127" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/2022-GA-2-6-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/2022-GA-2-6-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/2022-GA-2-6-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/2022-GA-2-6-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/2022-GA-2-6.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Del. Israel O&#8217;Quinn, R-Washington, speaks on the floor of the House of Delegates. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“These races are going on a race-by-race and a candidate-by-candidate basis, that’s why you have to put the work into the recruitment of quality candidates and make sure that you’re competitive in these really tight 50-50 House districts,” O’Quinn said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In 2020, Democrat Joe Biden won 60 out of 100 House of Delegates seats, and in the following year Democrats were able to capitalize on 51 of those, O’Quinn added. “I think Kamala Harris won 59 this year, so they’re going to have to run the table on all 51 to be able to continue to hold on to the majority, and I think we’re going to be very competitive there.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And less than one year before Virginia’s 2025 gubernatorial election and more than six months before the party primaries, the contest is effectively set, with two high-profile candidates leading the major-party tickets. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On the Democratic side, U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William, was the first </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/spanberger-virginia-governor-candidacy-c19ade683ab0dfaef67051b36791d30a" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">to announce</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> her bid in November of last year, positioning herself as a centrist with a focus on pragmatic leadership. Outgoing Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney, followed suit one month later, but in April he opted to pursue the lieutenant governor’s seat instead, streamlining Spanberger’s path to the nomination.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_36863" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=36863" rel="attachment wp-att-36863"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-36863" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/DSCF6603-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/DSCF6603-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/DSCF6603-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/DSCF6603-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/DSCF6603-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/DSCF6603-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William, speaks to a crowd of Democratic volunteers in Henrico County. (Graham Moomaw/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For Republicans, Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears emerged as the party’s standard-bearer after Attorney General Jason Miyares </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/18/miyares-to-seek-second-term-as-virginia-attorney-general/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">declared on Monday</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> he would seek reelection rather than enter the governor’s race. Earle-Sears, who </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">launched her campaign</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in September, is set to carry the GOP banner unopposed, benefiting from Miyares’ decision to focus on being reelected into his current role.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But despite her re-embrace of Trump as the Republican presidential nominee, the lieutenant governor’s campaign may still be haunted by her remarks from November 2022, when she publicly urged Americans to move on from the former president.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“A true leader understands when they have become a liability. A true leader understands that it’s time to step off the stage. And the voters have given us that very clear message,” Earle-Sears </span><a href="https://www.nbcwashington.com/news/politics/virginia-lt-gov-earle-sears-time-to-move-on-from-trump/3205900/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">said in a TV interview</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> at the time.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Richards, the political science professor, said that he expects the damning remarks to be brought up by political action committees aligned with Spanberger during the gubernatorial election cycle as a way to undermine Earle-Sears with Republicans.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“She will need to make up quickly with Trump. Had Trump lost she would have been able to brush off her previous comments, but now she will need his support,” Richards said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I suspect she will try to make nice. Her bigger hurdle will be convincing independent voters in Virginia she is not too extreme. Virginia is a purple state, and when it votes for the GOP it likes moderate-facing candidates, which is why Youngkin was careful to present himself that way in 2021.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A spokesman for Earle-Sears’ campaign declined to provide comment for this story. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_30208" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2022/05/25/virginia-lg-scheduled-to-speak-at-nra-fundraising-event-in-texas-this-week/ga-2022-4-4/" rel="attachment wp-att-30208"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-30208" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-300x200.jpg" alt="Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears presides over the Senate in this 2022 picture. (Ned Oliver/Virginia" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Lt. Gov. Winsome Sears presides over the Senate. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is little doubt that the match-up between Spanberger and Earle-Sears promises to be a defining battle of contrasting visions for Virginia’s future. Spanberger’s track record as a moderate in Congress and Earle-Sears’ bold embrace of conservative policies ensure the race will draw national attention.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spanberger’s “2025 campaign will continue to be laser-focused on the priorities that all Virginians share — stronger schools, safer communities, and lower costs,” campaign spokesman Connor Joseph said “And following the election of former President Trump, she also knows that Virginia must have a governor who is committed to protecting the rights and fundamental freedoms of all Virginians.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ernest McGowen, an associate professor at the Department of Political Science at the University of Richmond, said that Earle-Sears will likely face an uphill battle in a state that has increasingly voted for Democrats in statewide elections. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Earle-Sears may be a little too far right. If you look at Tim Kane and the kind of people that he had to run against, I think it may be kind of a similar situation,” McGowen said, referring to the Democratic U.S. senator from Virginia who has won his two reelection bids by fending of challenges from Republican nominees whose far-right positions have helped their primary campaigns but hurt their chances of winning a general election. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Also, Spanberger is more of a known commodity,” McGowen said. “If the Democrats in their election postmortem decide that their current ideological median isn’t isn&#8217;t where they thought it should be, I could see them actually really get behind Spanberger as not the new face of the party, but as someone to show the diversity of thought in the party.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The 2025 race for Virginia’s attorney general is also starting to take form, with three candidates having officially declared their bids. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After securing Gov. Glenn Youngkin’s </span><a href="https://x.com/glennyoungkin/status/1858574435449446657?s=46&amp;t=uQxq3EX7p3bygcqVfUnstg" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">endorsement</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> just moments after his announcement Monday, Miyares is unlikely to face a challenger for his party’s nomination. If reelected, the incumbent has vowed to focus on public safety and his record combating fentanyl and violent crime during a second term.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For Democrats, the field features a competitive primary between former Del. Jay Jones, who previously ran in 2021, and Henrico County Commonwealth’s Attorney Shannon Taylor. Jones has criticized Miyares for what he calls a “partisan agenda,” while Taylor has emphasized her decades of experience as a prosecutor dedicated to justice and public safety.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The lieutenant governor’s contest, however, remains wide open almost one year out. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">James City County business consultant and U.S. Navy veteran John Curran — who </span><a href="https://www.dailypress.com/2023/09/23/majority-of-jcc-supervisor-seats-up-for-grabs/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">ran unsuccessfully for the Board of Supervisors</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in 2023 — is the only Republican </span><a href="https://www.pilotonline.com/2024/09/27/james-city-county-business-consultant-to-run-for-lieutenant-governor-as-republican/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">who has filed</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> his paperwork to date, but the Democratic field is more crowded. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Besides Stoney, three additional candidates are vying for their party’s nomination: state Sens. Ghazala Hashmi, D-Chesterfield, and Aaron Rouse, D-Virginia Beach; and Babur Lateef, the former chairman of the Prince William County School Board. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But officials from both parties agree on one thing — the 2025 elections will likely serve as a referendum on Trump’s second term and provide a key barometer for the 2026 midterms and beyond.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It goes without saying that the Democrats will definitely be energized, because they have an intense dislike for President Trump,” said Anderson, the RPV chair. “The challenge for Republicans next year is being smarter and better equipped in 2025 than maybe we were in 2017, when we lost all those seats in the House of Delegates.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And House Speaker Scott expressed confidence in his party’s ability to harness its base’s enthusiasm and channel it into meaningful action.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We will stand up and we will fight, and I think the majority of Virginians will stand with us and push back against this administration,” Scott said. “I think that next year’s election will be that type of referendum on Donald Trump’s administration.” </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Miyares seeks reelection as attorney general, paves way for Earle-Sears in governor’s race</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/18/miyares-to-seek-second-term-as-virginia-attorney-general/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>cwoods@virginiamercury.com (Charlotte Rene Woods)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 18:31:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Glenn youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Miyares]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jay Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shannon Taylor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia attorney general]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Winsome Earle-Sears]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=40875</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Virginia Attorney General Jason Miyares announced Monday that he will seek reelection in 2025, putting to rest speculation that he might enter the Republican primary for governor. His decision effectively clears the way for Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears to secure her party’s nomination for the state’s top job. “I serve as the people’s protector,” Miyares [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Trump24-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Trump24-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Trump24-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Trump24-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Trump24-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Trump24-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Virginia Attorney General Jason Miyares joins former president Donald Trump at a rally in Chesapeake on June 28, 2024. Charlotte Rene Woods/ Virginia Mercury</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia Attorney General Jason Miyares announced Monday that he will seek reelection in 2025, putting to rest speculation that he might enter the Republican primary for governor. His decision effectively clears the way for Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears to secure her party’s nomination for the state’s top job.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I serve as the people’s protector,” Miyares said of his role as the state’s top lawyer in an </span><a href="https://x.com/JasonMiyaresVA/status/1858570888251404777" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">X post</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> announcing his reelection campaign. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Highlighting his aspirations for another four years as attorney general, Miyares pointed to key public safety initiatives he has championed, including the “One Pill Can Kill” campaign to raise awareness about fentanyl overdoses and his office’s work with “Ceasefire Virginia,” a program that combines prosecution efforts with community engagement to combat crime.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Earlier this year, Miyares </span><a href="https://richmond.com/news/state-regional/article_2b71d3a4-e6d7-11ee-8831-93f7ac7b8121.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">celebrated crime reductions</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> associated with the initiative. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Miyares’ campaign launch comes roughly a week after Democratic candidate </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/12/former-virginia-delegate-jay-jones-launches-second-bid-for-attorney-general/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jay Jones announced</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> his latest bid for the position. Jones lost a Democratic primary to former Attorney General Mark Herring in 2021, who later went on to lose to Miyares later that year in the general election. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Though Miyares hadn’t officially announced yet, Jones took a jab at Miyares last week — accusing him of using his office to “attack Virginians’ freedoms, pander to the fringes of his own party and side with corporate price gougers and polluters” at the cost of Virginia families. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Moments after Miyares’ announcement, Gov. Glenn Youngkin also turned to X to endorse the attorney general and Earle-Sears for next year’s Republican ticket. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“As attorney general, Jason vigorously defends the laws of the commonwealth, stands with law enforcement every single day while leading our shared fight to end the free flow of opioids and fentanyl into our communities, and has been a constant advocate for victims of human trafficking and domestic violence,” Youngkin wrote. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“He has never backed down when it comes to standing up for Virginians. He is an exceptional attorney general.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin also hailed Earle-Sears — a U.S. Marine Corps veteran who </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">declared her bid</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for the state’s highest office in September and would likely face U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger — as “an outstanding” lieutenant governor. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“She will be a great governor. She has been an outspoken advocate for commonsense conservative principles and policies, a passionate voice for our military and veterans, and a relentless advocate for educational freedom and economic opportunity. She brings the fighting spirit of a Marine to the office every single day.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Earle-Sears said in a statement that she was “deeply honored” to receive Youngkin’s endorsement. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Together with our outstanding attorney general, Jason Miyares, we will continue championing common-sense safety and security policies that keep Virginia the ‘Number 1 Best State for Business,’” she said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While Miyares is so far the only Republican candidate vying for the seat, Jones will face Henrico Commonwealth Attorney Shannon Taylor in a primary. Miyares took aim at both on social media last week after Jones announced his bid. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Both of the announced (democratic) candidates for Attorney General are far-left, anti-police, criminal rights progressives who will make Virginia less safe. They will support the same criminal first, victim last policies that lead to a surge in violent crime,” Miyares wrote. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">He reiterated similar messaging in his re-election campaign launch video Monday, and said that in a second term he will continue to press for more tough-on-crime policies. Also during his time in office, Miyares has signed onto legal briefs with other Republican attorneys general </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/03/virginia-attorney-general-joins-efforts-to-fight-back-against-title-ix-changes/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">challenging</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> President Joe Biden administration’s </span><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/education/2024/08/01/biden-titleix-courts-gender-identity-discrimination/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Title IX rules</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> meant to protect LGBTQ+ students from discrimination.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In her pushback to Miyares, Taylor noted her over 25 years of experience as a prosecutor. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Every day of every one of those years has been spent working with law enforcement to keep people safe and seeking justice for victims of crime and their families,” </span><a href="https://x.com/ShannonTaylorVA/status/1856481762563465512" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">she wrote on X</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> with a repost of Miyares’ post. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And Democratic Party of Virginia Chair Susan Swecker in a statement called Miyares “a MAGA mouthpiece in pushing an extreme agenda,” referring to President-elect Donald Trump’s Make America Great Again campaign motto. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Virginians deserve an attorney general who will stand up for their rights and freedoms, not someone who is constantly trying to take them away,” Swecker said. “It is clear that, if re-elected, Miyares would use his office as a partisan tool to serve the interests of the Trump administration, rather than the needs of hard-working Virginians.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stephen Farnsworth, a political scientist at the University of Mary Washington, said it was “a smart move” by Miyares to put his gubernatorial ambitions on hold and run for reelection next year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“There was no guarantee that he would prevail in a contest with the lieutenant governor. He can run for reelection now and legitimately claim the right to be first in line in 2029 for the party&#8217;s gubernatorial nomination,” Farnsworth said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While Republican attorneys general end up running for governor consistently and sometimes have been able to prevail over Republican lieutenant governors because they are more explicitly conservative, that is not the case this time, Farnsworth said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The current lieutenant governor is not an ideological moderate the way some Republican lieutenant governors have been in the past,” he said of Earle-Sears. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democrats would likely have preferred a competition for the GOP’s gubernatorial nomination among the two Republican statewide office holders, Farnsworth added.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“If nothing else, a fight between Miyares and Winsome Earle-Sears would have put a lot of Republican money into the primary that otherwise would have been spent on a general election.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Connor Joseph, a spokesman for Spanberger’s campaign, said that no matter who her eventual opponent is, the Democrat’s vision for Virginia remains the same. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Her 2025 campaign will continue to be focused on the priorities that all Virginians share — stronger schools, safer communities, and lower costs,” Joseph said. “Additionally, Abigail knows that Virginia must have a governor who is committed to protecting the rights and fundamental freedoms of all Virginians.”</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Va. House panel advances amendments on abortion rights, marriage equality and voting rights</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/13/va-house-panel-advances-amendments-on-abortion-rights-marriage-equality-and-voting-rights/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2024 00:53:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Abortion Policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Criminal Justice + Policing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[abortion rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Constitutional amendments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[same-sex marriage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia constitution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia General Assembly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia House of Delegates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Voting rights]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40842</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A Democratic-led House of Delegates panel on Wednesday advanced three proposed constitutional amendments, including a revised measure seeking to enshrine abortion rights in the state’s highest law. The new proposal would also require third-trimester abortions to be approved by one doctor instead of three, as the law currently mandates.  The 22-member House Privileges and Elections [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="729" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2228-1-1024x729.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2228-1-1024x729.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2228-1-300x213.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2228-1-768x546.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2228-1-1536x1093.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2228-1-2048x1457.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Committee Chair Del. Marcia Price, D-Newsport News, flanked by House Majority Leader Charniele Herring, D-Alexandria (left) and Del. Elizabeth Bennett-Parker, D-Alexandria, at a news conference in Richmond on Nov. 13, 2024. (Markus Schmidt/Virginia Mercury) </p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A Democratic-led House of Delegates panel on Wednesday advanced three proposed constitutional amendments, including a revised measure seeking to enshrine abortion rights in the state’s highest law. The new proposal would also require third-trimester abortions to be approved by one doctor instead of three, as the law currently mandates. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The 22-member House Privileges and Elections Committee further backed amendments to extend constitutional protections to marriage equality and the automatic restoration of voting rights for felons who have served their time.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The right to love, the right to vote, the right to bodily autonomy and privacy, these are the very rights and freedoms that are crucial to the foundation of this commonwealth and this nation,” committee chair Del. Marcia Price, D-Newport News, said in a brief news conference Wednesday afternoon. “We showed up today to do our jobs and to do everything within our power to protect these rights and freedoms for all Virginians.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The revised abortion amendment language in </span><a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/bill-details/20251/HJ1" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">HJ1</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> shocked the committee’s Republican members, who only saw the changes after the meeting was already underway. Price called a  five-minute recess to allow lawmakers to review the new language before deliberations and voting proceeded.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;I think we’re still trying to figure out what happened today,” a visibly frustrated House Minority Leader Del. Todd Gilbert, R-Shenandoah, said after the three-hour hearing. “Something this important and impactful — literally life-and-death decisions — I don’t think I’ve ever seen anything pushed through this fast where we didn’t get a chance to see it.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Gilbert warned that Price’s decision to not allow the committee more time to review the revised legislation would set a precedent for the way the House conducts its business in the future. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We were literally given five minutes to huddle and look at it before we had to decide what we were grappling with, and I think we still don’t know, other than it’s pretty clear that this is a pretty extreme version of efforts to protect abortion that goes well beyond what has been done in other states,” Gilbert said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Price, however, defended her decision to move forward with taking a vote on the proposal.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We have an entire legislative process just like any other committee, and [the resolution] will go to the floor where (Republicans) will also have a chance to either put forward amendments or have their voice heard as well,” she said at the news conference.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Amending the state Constitution takes several years in Virginia. The proposed amendment must be approved by the legislature in two separate years, with a General Assembly election occurring in between. Only then can the amendment proceed to a statewide referendum for voters to decide. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Because the next election in Virginia is in November 2025, the earliest the three amendments that the committee advanced Wednesday could be put on the ballot is November 2026 — if the measures pass in the 2025 and 2026 legislative sessions. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">The abortion rights amendment</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Under current Virginia law, third-trimester abortions require approval from three doctors. The new amendment would reduce this requirement to just one doctor when a late-term abortion is deemed necessary to protect the life of the pregnant individual, or their physical or mental health, or when a physician determines the fetus is not viable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At Wednesday’s hearing, dozens of abortion opponents lined up to speak against the proposal.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Among them was Olivia Turner, president of the Virginia Society for Human Life, who told the panel that her group opposed both the original amendment and its substitute. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We don’t know what’s going on with this new version, and how it will impact our ability as the people of Virginia to pass rational and reasonable protective laws in the future,” Turner said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And Gilbert, the House Minority Leader, said that the amendment capsized Roe v. Wade, the 1973 Supreme Court case that established abortion as a constitutional right and that was repealed in 2022. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Roe v. Wade has within it a compelling state interest in protecting the life of the unborn at a certain point in the pregnancy. This amendment doesn’t contain that protection at all, it leans in the other direction,” Gilbert said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The legislation we just saw, which was dropped on us literally today without any ability to look at it, reflect on it, think about it, compare notes, talk to experts, only leans into the protection of the patient, which is the mother. And so there is no more protection for the unborn, which was envisioned and embodied in Roe (v.) Wade.”</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40846" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:2560px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/13/va-house-panel-advances-amendments-on-abortion-rights-marriage-equality-and-voting-rights/img_2227-3/" rel="attachment wp-att-40846"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-40846 size-full" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="2560" height="1920" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2227-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  House Minority Leader Todd Gilbert, R-Shenandoah, talks to reporters after the House Privileges and Elections Committee meeting on Nov. 13, 2024. (Markus Schmidt/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But House Majority Leader Charniele Herring, D-Alexandria, the sponsor of HJ1, said that in her amendment both the state interest in protecting the unborn and life of the mother are considered. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The parameters are set out so if there is a live fetus, there are protections. But if there is a miscarriage, then the physician and the mother will be able to make a decision to abort and to complete a miscarriage. So they do coexist,” Herring said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Abortion rights advocates urged the committee to vote in favor of the amendment. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This amendment will protect Virginians’ rights to make their own reproductive health care decisions, including access to abortion, contraception, fertility treatment and miscarriage care,” said Jamie Lockhart, executive director of Planned Parenthood Advocates of Virginia. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Right now, with no state or federal protections in place, Virginians face the constant risk that anti-abortion politicians could restrict or ban essential care. No one is more qualified than an individual and their health care provider to make these complex personal decisions.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After defeating a Republican motion to kill the proposed amendment, the committee moved to advance the measure by a 12-9 party-line vote.</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Restoration of rights amendment </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/bill-details/20251/HJ2" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">HJ2</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, sponsored by Del. Elizabeth Bennett-Parker, D-Alexandria, seeks to automate the process of restoring voting rights to people convicted of felony crimes who have served their sentences. The proposal comes in response to a </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/03/23/youngkin-administration-now-requires-felons-to-apply-to-get-their-voting-rights-back/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">2023 policy change</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> implemented by Gov. Glenn Youngkin that requires people with felony convictions to proactively apply to regain their voting rights upon release from prison and is not automatically restoring rights for any group of offenders — a shift from Virginia’s three previous governors.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bennett-Parker told reporters Wednesday that her amendment proposes automatic restoration of voting rights for individuals who have been released from incarceration, which she said would foster “a more just and bare” society.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The disenfranchisement of people with all convictions is a relic of Virginia’s Jim Crow past and was intentionally inserted into the 1902 Virginia Constitution to disenfranchise as many Black voters as possible,” Bennett-Parker said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">She added that the right to vote is fundamental and the amendment ensures that if a person has served their time they deserve to have their rights to participate in democracy restored.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Virginia is the only state to permanently disenfranchise all individuals with felony convictions unless they individually petition the governor for rights restoration. The current system has no transparency and changes every four years, so no one knows what steps to take to get their rights restored. This amendment creates a process that is bound by transparent rules and criteria that will apply equally to everybody.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The committee backed HJ2 with a 12-9 party-line vote.</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Marriage equality amendment</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although the U.S. Supreme Court granted same-sex couples the right to marry in the Obergefell v. Hodges ruling in 2014, the state Constitution still includes the 2006 Marshall-Newman Amendment, which defines marriage as solely between one man and one woman and bans recognition of any legal status that approximates “the design, qualities, significance, or effects of marriage.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Because it could become law again should the Supreme Court overturn its 2014 ruling one day, Del. Mark Sickles, D-Arlington, sponsored </span><a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/bill-details/20251/HJ9" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">HJ9</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in an effort to repeal the current constitutional provision and enshrine marriage as a “fundamental right inherent in the liberty of persons,” unrestricted by factors like sex, gender or race. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jeff Caruso, executive director of the Virginia Catholic Conference, told the committee that his group has opposed efforts to repeal the Marshall-Newman Amendment for more than 16 years. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We affirm the dignity of every person, we also affirm that marriage has an original design and purpose, which predates any nation, any religion and any law, and we urge you to uphold that principle today.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Narissa Rahaman, executive director of Equality Virginia, pushed back against that notion and reminded the panel that today there are more than 20,000 same-sex couples in Virginia who have more similarities than differences with couples in traditional marriages.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Here in Virginia we have seen how a state has evolved in its thinking about same-sex couples, and LGTBQ people overall. Now it’s time for our state to fully complete our evolution and finish the job in protecting marriage equality for all,” Rahaman said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The committee advanced the amendment on a bipartisan 16-5 vote, with four Republicans joining Democrats. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I think our straightforward amendment will be welcomed by Virginia citizens and I’m really appreciative of the vote today in the committee,” Sickles said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All three amendments are now set to be voted on by the General Assembly during its 2025 session, which begins in January. </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Former Virginia delegate Jay Jones launches second bid for attorney general</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/12/former-virginia-delegate-jay-jones-launches-second-bid-for-attorney-general/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 19:26:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attorney General Jason Miyares]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jay Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shannon Taylor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jay Jones, a Democratic former state delegate from Norfolk, on Tuesday announced his bid for Virginia attorney general at two separate events in Norfolk and Richmond.  For Jones, who represented the 89th District in the House of Delegates from 2019 to 2021, it marks his second run for his party’s nomination for attorney general. In [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2146-1024x768.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2146-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2146-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2146-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2146-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/IMG_2146-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Jay Jones, a former state delegate from Norfolk, announced his renewed bid for attorney general during a gathering at the Maggie L. Walker Memorial Plaza in Richmond Tuesday. (Markus Schmidt/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jay Jones, a Democratic former state delegate from Norfolk, on Tuesday announced his bid for Virginia attorney general at two separate events in Norfolk and Richmond. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For Jones, who represented the 89th District in the House of Delegates from 2019 to 2021, it marks his second run for his party’s nomination for attorney general. In 2021, he lost the Democratic primary to then-incumbent Mark Herring, despite an endorsement from former Gov. Ralph Northam.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Last week we awoke to an uncertain future and a president-elect who openly flouts the rule of law,” Jones said before a small crowd of supporters that had gathered at Maggie L. Walker Memorial Plaza in Richmond Tuesday afternoon.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“With an incoming administration, families now face the threat of higher healthcare costs as (Donald) Trump seeks to kick tens of thousands of working Virginians off Medicaid and end the protections of the Affordable Care Act,” Jones said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">He also accused Attorney General Jason Miyares, the Republican incumbent and his potential opponent, of using his office “to attack Virginians’ freedoms, pander to the fringes of his own party and side with corporate price gougers and polluters” at the cost of Virginia families. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“He’s used his office to advance his own radical, personal, partisan-political agenda,” Jones said of Miyares. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So far, Jones is one of two declared candidates in the 2025 attorney general’s race, alongside Henrico County Commonwealth’s Attorney Shannon Taylor. Miyares responded to Jones’ announcement Tuesday by calling out his potential opponents on social media. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Both of the announced Democrat candidates for attorney general are far-left, anti-police, criminal rights progressives who will make Virginia less safe,” Miyares wrote on X, formerly Twitter. “They will support the same criminal first, victim last policies that lead to a surge in violent crime.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Miyares has yet to declare whether he will run for reelection or seek his party’s nomination for governor.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">During his Richmond appearance, Jones declined to comment on the attorney general’s response to his announcement.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“You have to ask him why he said that,” he said. “We’re focused on this campaign, whatever he says and whatever he tweets out, that’s him, and his campaign’s business.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jones’s pre-legislature career includes a stint at Goldman Sachs in New York, where he specialized in risk management and credit advisory for natural resources and tech companies. After two years, he returned to Virginia, earning his law degree from the University of Virginia School of Law in 2015. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While in law school, Jones interned for Del. Algie Howell, who represented the 90th House District from 2004 until 2014. Jones was elected to the body himself in 2017 after winning a competitive Democratic primary and defeating Libertarian candidate Terry Hurst in the general election, succeeding then-Del. Daun Hester, D-Norfolk.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jones said on Tuesday that he is running because Virginians need an attorney general who is focused on keeping the commonwealth safe instead of following a partisan agenda. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“As your attorney general, I will protect Virginia’s families, our children, and our most vulnerable,” he said. “We will crack down on those who would do our kids harm by working with law enforcement to get illegal guns off our streets, shut down drug traffickers and hold to account the gun manufacturers whose weapons of war are used to commit mass shootings and crimes.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Jones vowed to “go after the criminals that prey on children and our families and put them where they belong — behind bars,” and he promised to take on social media companies “fueling a mental health crisis among our young people” and corporations that pollute air and water. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“And if the Trump administration again tries to raise the health care cost by taking apart the Affordable Care Act, I’ll be the first to take him to court to stop it,” Jones said, adding that he would always fight back against “any attempt to undermine abortion rights in Virginia” and use “the full weight of the office” to protect women and medical professionals.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The House Privileges and Elections Committee is set to meet Wednesday to consider several proposed constitutional amendments, including one to guarantee access to abortion in Virginia and another to remove outdated language defining marriage solely as a union between a man and a woman. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I will join the fight to enshrine these rights in our Constitution today,” Jones said. </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spanberger and Earle-Sears tied in first 2025 gubernatorial poll</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/25/spanberger-and-earle-sears-tied-in-first-2025-gubernatorial-poll/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 15:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abigail Spanberger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Miyares]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kamala Harris]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia governor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Winsome Earle-Sears]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A little over one year before the 2025 gubernatorial election, Republican Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears and U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William, the two leading declared candidates for governor, are tied at 39% support each, according to a new statewide poll by the University of Mary Washington’s Center for Leadership and Media Studies. The remaining [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="385" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-25-at-12.18.07 PM-1024x385.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-25-at-12.18.07 PM-1024x385.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-25-at-12.18.07 PM-300x113.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-25-at-12.18.07 PM-768x289.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-25-at-12.18.07 PM.png 1456w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Candidates in Virginia's 2025 gubernatorial contest U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William (left) and Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears, R (right). Spanberger photo by Charlotte Rene Woods/Virginia Mercury, Earle-Sears photo by Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury.</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A little over one year before the 2025 gubernatorial election, Republican Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears and U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William, the two leading declared candidates for governor, are tied at 39% support each, according to a </span><a href="https://www.umw.edu/news/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2024/09/UMW-Survey-Topline-Two-1.pdf" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">new statewide poll</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> by the University of Mary Washington’s Center for Leadership and Media Studies.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The remaining 22% of respondents in the survey of 1,000 adult Virginians said they were undecided, did not plan to vote,  would back another candidate or refused to answer. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The poll is in line with the results from </span><a href="https://www.umw.edu/news/wp-content/uploads/sites/7/2024/09/UMW-Survey-Topline-One-1-1.pdf" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">another UMW survey</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> that also found Vice President Kamala Harris and former President Donald Trump locked in a tight contest in Virginia, with the Democrat edging her Republican opponent by 48-46%. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spanberger, who has represented Virginia’s 7th Congressional District since 2019, was the first candidate </span><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/11/13/abigail-spanberger-virginia-governor-00126815" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">to announce</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> her gubernatorial bid in November 2023. Earle-Sears, the first Black woman in the commonwealth to hold statewide office, and the first woman to attain such a role since Mary Sue Terry’s tenure as attorney general in the 1990s, </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">launched her campaign</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> earlier this month. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Attorney General Jason Miyares, another potential Republican candidate for his party’s gubernatorial nomination, would be equally competitive in a general election, the poll found. In a possible match-up between Spanberger and Miyares, 40% of survey respondents backed Spanberger while 39% favored Miyares, well within the survey’s margin of error.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Miyares has not yet announced his intentions for 2025, but Virginia attorney generals often either run for re-election to the commonwealth’s top legal office or campaign to become governor. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Republican Glenn Youngkin, the current governor, cannot run for re-election next year because of Virginia’s one consecutive term limit for governors.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Virginia elections are often close, and the look ahead to next year suggests more of the same in the campaign for governor,” said Stephen J. Farnsworth, a political scientist at the University of Mary Washington and director of UMW’s Center for Leadership and Media Studies. “The big challenge for these potential candidates is becoming better known across the commonwealth.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginians were more negative about the direction of the nation than about the direction of the commonwealth, with 24% saying Virginia was headed in the right direction and 26% saying it was headed in the wrong direction. The rest offered mixed views. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For the nation overall, 51% of those surveyed said that things in the country were headed in the wrong direction, with only 16% saying the nation was on the right track.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Virginians in this new survey said they approved of Youngkin’s job performance by a 46 to 34% margin. As for President Joe Biden’s job performance, 37% of survey respondents approved while 53% disapproved.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Elections never stop in Virginia, and 2025 looks to be another very interesting electoral year in the commonwealth,” Farnsworth said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The UMW poll was conducted by Research America Inc. between Sept. 3 and 9, 2024. The survey included a total of 1,000 Virginia residents, consisting of 870 registered voters and 774 likely voters. The margin of error is +/- 4.1%. </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Virginia House Speaker Don Scott endorses Abigail Spanberger for governor</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/virginia-house-speaker-don-scott-endorses-abigail-spanberger-for-governor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlotte Rene Woods]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cwoods@virginiamercury.com (Charlotte Rene Woods)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2025 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abigail Spanberger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Don Scott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[governor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=39946</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Days after Republican Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears announced her bid for governor of Virginia — a contest that will take place next year but is already ramping up — House Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, is throwing his support behind the only other declared candidate in the governor’s race, congresswoman Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William. Scott’s endorsement [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_2188-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_2188-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_2188-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_2188-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_2188-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_2188-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-7th, speaks to a crowd in Richmond, Virginia on the second anniversary of the overturn of federal abortion protections. (Charlotte Rene Woods / Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Days after Republican </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears announced her bid for governor of Virginia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> — a contest that will take place next year but is already ramping up — House Speaker Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, is throwing his support behind the only other declared candidate in the governor’s race, congresswoman Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="shDKEvsvR5"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/">Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears announces run for Virginia governor</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears announces run for Virginia governor&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/embed/#?secret=MRhcWvVB44#?secret=shDKEvsvR5" data-secret="shDKEvsvR5" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Scott’s endorsement joins a growing list of over 100 current or former state, local or federal officials to back Spanberger. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Scott, a lawyer and former U.S Navy officer, made history as the first Black Speaker elected in the 400-year history of Virginia’s General Assembly. Spanberger is a former Central Intelligence Agency case officer who was first elected to represent Virginia’s 7th Congressional District in 2018, the first woman to do so. Now, Scott hopes to see her become Virginia’s first woman governor. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">He recalled “getting to know [Spanberger] over the last few years” and their mutual support for each others’ efforts to connect with constituents and other elected officials across party lines around the state. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I think her number one quality is that she listens,” Scott said in a phone call Monday afternoon. “She has made an effort to serve every corner of our community and our Commonwealth.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Likewise, Spanberger noted Scott’s efforts to engage with people around the state too. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Speaker Scott is dedicated to uplifting his fellow Virginians — and his ability to work with both parties shows his commitment to getting things done for the Commonwealth,” she said in a statement.”I am truly grateful for his endorsement.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Both will be up for election next year, and should Democrats retain their control of the House of Delegates, Scott could continue in his role as Speaker.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_37470" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=37470" rel="attachment wp-att-37470"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-37470 size-medium" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/IMG_4030-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/IMG_4030-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/IMG_4030-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/IMG_4030-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/IMG_4030-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/IMG_4030-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Del. Don Scott, D-Portsmouth, addresses his colleagues in the House of Delegates after being elected speaker of the House at the Virginia State Capitol on Jan. 10. (Nathaniel Cline/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spanberger’s bipartisan efforts to bring infrastructure and broadband funding to the state and her support of congress’ Inflation Reduction Act earned Scott’s backing, he said. He noted their shared goals of increasing investments in public education and Spanberger’s support for three constitutional amendments that Virginia Democrats plan to kick start next year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In 2025, Democrats plan to advance</span><a href="https://richmond.com/news/state-regional/government-politics/virginia-abortion-rights-restoration-same-sex-marriage/article_731f82a4-b4b0-11ee-9c14-7719906ce1fc.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> proposed amendments</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to Virginia’s constitution that will cement abortion protections, remove a same-sex marriage prohibition from the constitution, and enshrine the automatic restoration of voting rights for formerly incarcerated people who have served their prison time. The measures will need to pass two years in a row with a House of Delegates election in between before appearing on statewide ballots for voters to approve or reject, meaning they are not subject to gubernatorial approval.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But that doesn’t mean Spanberger’s support won’t be important for their potential success, should she ascend to the governor’s chair, Scott said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We’re going to win together [next November],” he said.”That’s because we&#8217;re going to continue to move Virginia forward and not take us backwards.” </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        <br style="font-weight: 400;" /><br style="font-weight: 400;" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears announces run for Virginia governor</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/06/lt-gov-winsome-earle-sears-announces-run-for-virginia-governor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Markus Schmidt]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>mschmidt@virginiamercury.com (Markus Schmidt)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 15:28:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2025 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia governor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39923</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears on Thursday evening officially announced her candidacy for governor of Virginia in the upcoming 2025 election, aiming to become the nation’s first Black female governor. Sears made history in 2022 by becoming the first Black woman in the commonwealth to hold statewide office, and the first woman to attain such a [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears presides over the Senate in this 2022 picture. (Ned Oliver/Virginia" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/GA-2022-4-4.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Lt. Gov. Winsome Sears presides over the Senate. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears on Thursday evening officially announced her candidacy for governor of Virginia in the upcoming 2025 election, aiming to become the nation’s first Black female governor. Sears made history in 2022 by becoming the first Black woman in the commonwealth to hold statewide office, and the first woman to attain such a role since Mary Sue Terry’s tenure as attorney general in the 1990s. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The future, a new chapter, is about to begin,” Earle-Sears said at a rally in Virginia Beach. “Together, we have the power to ensure that our brightest days are ahead of us still. But to make that future a reality, we must come together, it is really that simple. We must stand strong, we must support each other, we must share each other’s values and visions.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Earle-Sears’s candidacy marks a significant milestone in Virginia’s political landscape. Should she become the Republican nominee, she would likely face U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Prince William, who was the first candidate </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/spanberger-virginia-governor-candidacy-c19ade683ab0dfaef67051b36791d30a" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">to announce</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> her bid in November. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">​​Spanberger is the only Democrat currently seeking her party’s nomination, after Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney dropped his bid to instead run for lieutenant governor.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Earle-Sears announcing her run for governor of Virginia was expected, because the lieutenant  governor role is often seen as a stepping stone to the state’s highest office,” said David Richards, a political scientist at the University of Lynchburg. “Glenn Youngkin is a popular governor and so Earle-Sears should try to take advantage of that to go to the next level.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A trailblazer in Virginia politics, Earle-Sears first made history in 2021 when she was elected as the state’s first Black woman to hold statewide office. Her rise in the GOP has been marked by her strong conservative values, her advocacy for education reform, and her emphasis on public safety — themes that are expected to play a central role in her gubernatorial campaign.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A native of Kingston, Jamaica, Earle-Sears, 60, immigrated to the United States at the age of 6. She grew up in the Bronx, New York City, and served as an electrician in the U.S. Marine Corps from 1983 until 1986. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">She also directed a Salvation Army homeless shelter before launching her career in public service in 2001, when she was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates, representing the 90th District, becoming the first Jamaican-American, female Republican,</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">first female veteran, and first naturalized citizen to serve in the General Assembly.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">On her path to seize the Republican nomination for governor Earle-Sears will likely face Attorney General Jason Miyares, who is also speculated to announce his candidacy in the coming weeks. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another obstacle for Earle-Sears may be her decision in November 2022 to </span><a href="https://www.nbcwashington.com/news/politics/virginia-lt-gov-earle-sears-time-to-move-on-from-trump/3205900/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">publicly withdraw</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> her support for former President Donald Trump, who at the time was teasing an announcement for a third White House run — a move that might haunt her as the Republican nominee for president has shown little tolerance for disloyalty.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“A true leader understands when they have become a liability. A true leader understands that it’s time to step off the stage. And the voters have given us that very clear message,” Earle-Sears said in a TV interview with Fox News at the time. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But on Thursday, Earle-Sears left no doubt about her return into the Make America Great Again fold. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This is such a great country, God bless America. And folks, first and foremost, in 2024, that means standing with President Trump, it means standing with [Republican nominee] Hung Cao for our Senate, and it means that we must stand very steadfast with our incumbents so they can continue to defend Virginia’s best interests in Congress,” she told her audience. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some Trump loyalists already pushed back against an Earle-Sears candidacy over her previous remarks about the former president. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“She’s an insufferable, never-Trumper that’s totally myopic and self serving,” conservative talk show host John Fredericks wrote on the social media platform X on Thursday, suggesting that the lieutenant governor’s bid “might as well be paid for and authorized” by Vice President Kamala Harris’ presidential campaign.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Once again, it’s all about Winsome Sears, and it’s all about screwing Trump — because that’s all she does,” Fredericks said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But Richards, the political scientist, said that it is possible for Earle-Sears to overcome her rocky relationship with Trump and secure her party’s nomination. “She is popular with state Republicans, polling ahead of Miyares in a survey earlier this year. Whether she can replicate Youngkin’s 2021 surprise win statewide remains to be seen.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Either way, an Earle-Sears v. Spanberger matchup would be historic, Richards said. “Two women running for governor of Virginia, and Earle-Sears would be the first Black woman and, if elected, the first person since the 1700s to be governor not born in the U.S.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At her rally in Virginia Beach on Thursday, Earle-Sears vowed that she would mount a good fight. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Winning Virginia is not just possible, it is necessary because the Democrats have had a headstart and they are fighting tooth and nail to win in November. And they want to win in November 2025 as well, but we are not going to let them. So, let’s roll up our sleeves and let’s get to work,” she said. </span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stoney drops out of Virginia governor race, will run for LG instead</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/stoney-drops-out-of-virginia-governor-race-will-run-for-lg-instead/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Graham Moomaw]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>gmoomaw@virginiamercury.com (Graham Moomaw)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 16:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2025 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aaron Rouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abigail Spanberger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Levar Stoney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayor Levar Stoney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richmond]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia governor's race 2025]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=briefs&#038;p=38454</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney announced Tuesday that he’s no longer seeking the Democratic nomination for governor in 2025 and will instead run for lieutenant governor next year. Stoney’s downshift appears to put Democratic congresswoman Abigail Spanberger on a clear path to become her party’s next pick for governor, making her the lone Democrat officially running [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/2019-session-pohotos-13.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney outside a meeting of the Richmond Branch of the NAACP. (2019 Photo by Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney announced Tuesday that he’s no longer seeking the Democratic nomination for governor in 2025 and will instead run for lieutenant governor next year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stoney’s downshift appears to put Democratic congresswoman Abigail Spanberger on a clear path to become her party’s next pick for governor, making her the lone Democrat officially running for the seat.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After serving as Richmond’s mayor since 2017, Stoney seemed to acknowledge Spanberger’s solid frontrunner status in a statement announcing his decision, saying he only had a “narrow path” to victory.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I believe this is a time when Democrats must stand united and avoid an ugly primary for governor,” Stoney said, adding that he and his wife also welcomed the birth of a daughter in March.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stoney said that running for lieutenant governor — a largely ceremonial position that’s nevertheless seen as a launchpad for aspiring governors — is “the right move for me and my family, the right move for the Democratic Party, the right move for the future of the Commonwealth of Virginia.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A former executive director of the Democratic Party of Virginia who served as Virginia’s secretary of the commonwealth under former Gov. Terry McAuliffe, Stoney was long expected to make a move for higher office. His second term as mayor of Virginia’s capital city expires at the end of the year. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite running for a less prestigious position, Stoney will still face primary competition for the lieutenant governor job.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Shortly after Stoney’s announcement Tuesday morning, Sen. Aaron Rouse, D-Virginia Beach, formally announced he too is running for lieutenant governor. A former professional football player, Rouse flipped a Hampton Roads-area seat in the Virginia Senate in early 2023, a Democratic win that ensured Gov. Glenn Youngkin and his Republican allies wouldn’t be able to pass a bill rolling back abortion access that year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I’ve built my career on winning in tough spots when it matters – whether it be under the glare of NFL lights or flipping the State Senate seat needed to ensure we blocked Republicans’ assaults on reproductive freedom and voting rights,” Rouse said in a statement. “Virginia is ready for a new generation of leaders to step up.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Babur Lateef, an ophthalmologist who serves as chairman of the Prince William County School Board, announced last month that he’s running a Democratic campaign for lieutenant governor.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Several other Virginia Democrats are thought to be considering runs for lieutenant governor, and the field could continue to grow as 2025 approaches.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If no other Democrat files to run for governor against Spanberger, she is expected to face either Republican Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears or Republican Attorney General Jason Miyares in the 2025 general election. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">No Republicans have officially announced bids for the seat yet, but Earle-Sears and Miyares are considered top contenders to try to succeed current Gov. Glenn Youngkin.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Any primaries for Virginia’s Executive Branch offices would take place in June of 2025.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spanberger has big lead over Stoney in early poll of 2025 gubernatorial primary</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/spanberger-has-big-lead-over-stoney-in-early-poll-of-2025-gubernatorial-primary/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Graham Moomaw]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>gmoomaw@virginiamercury.com (Graham Moomaw)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 19:49:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2025]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Abigail Spanberger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christopher Newport University]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Levar Stoney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[poll]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?post_type=blog_va&#038;p=37616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Congresswoman Abigail Spanberger is much better known among Virginia Democrats than Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney, according to early poll numbers gauging how familiar voters are with the two Democrats running for governor in 2025. The poll from the Wason Center for Civic Leadership at Christopher Newport University found 52% of Democrats back Spanberger, 8% support [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/mercury-5.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger, D-Henrico. (Ned Oliver/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Congresswoman Abigail Spanberger is much better known among Virginia Democrats than Richmond Mayor Levar Stoney, according to early poll numbers gauging how familiar voters are with the two Democrats running for governor in 2025.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The poll from the Wason Center for Civic Leadership at Christopher Newport University found 52% of Democrats back Spanberger, 8% support Stoney and 40% are unsure.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“This early in the campaign season these numbers are likely to heavily reflect name recognition of the candidates and signal that Mayor Stoney has a long way to go in getting his name and message out to voters,” CNU researchers said in their </span><a href="https://cnu.edu/wasoncenter/surveys/archive/2024-01-24.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">summary of the poll’s findings</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spanberger, a former CIA officer, has served in Congress since 2019 after winning several tough elections in her original district in the Richmond suburbs and — after redistricting — a newly drawn district in Northern Virginia. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stoney, who has been mayor of the capital city since 2017, is a former executive director of the Democratic Party of Virginia who also served as secretary of the commonwealth under former Gov. Terry McAuliffe.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Both are seeking the chance to succeed current Gov. Glenn Youngkin when the Republican’s four-year term concludes at the end of 2025. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Youngkin can’t run again next year under Virginia’s term limits, but Attorney General Jason Miyares and Lt. Gov. Winsome Earle-Sears are considered possible GOP nominees for governor in 2025.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Aligning with other recent poll results, the CNU survey of 1,000 registered Virginia voters found 50% approved of Youngkin, compared with 36% approval for President Joe Biden.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
