<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Josh Kurtz, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/josh-kurtz/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/josh-kurtz/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 17:23:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Josh Kurtz, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/josh-kurtz/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>With Trump presidency looming, state, federal leaders renew commitment to Bay cleanup</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/10/with-trump-presidency-looming-state-federal-leaders-renew-commitment-to-bay-cleanup/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 23:03:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay cleanup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay Executive Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maryland]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41399</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Top officials from all the Chesapeake Bay states and the federal government gathered in Annapolis Tuesday to reiterate their commitment to cleaning up the historically and economically critical estuary and strengthening the decade-long partnership that has helped improved the Bay’s health — even if that progress hasn’t been as swift and consistent as they might [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/dec_10_24_1800-01-9E3A8069-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/dec_10_24_1800-01-9E3A8069-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/dec_10_24_1800-01-9E3A8069-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/dec_10_24_1800-01-9E3A8069-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/dec_10_24_1800-01-9E3A8069-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/dec_10_24_1800-01-9E3A8069.jpg 1800w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Gov. Wes Moore leads Virginia Gov. Glenn Youngkin and officials of Chesapeake Bay watershed jurisdictions, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency and Chesapeake Bay Commission from the Maryland State House to the annual public meeting of the Chesapeake Executive Council on Dec. 10, 2024. (Will Parson/Chesapeake Bay Program)</p><p>Top officials from all the Chesapeake Bay states and the federal government gathered in Annapolis Tuesday to reiterate their commitment to cleaning up the historically and economically critical estuary and strengthening the decade-long partnership that has helped improved the Bay’s health — even if that progress hasn’t been as swift and consistent as they might have hoped.</p>
<p>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore (D), seated next to Virginia Gov. Glenn Youngkin (R), with Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro (D) participating by video, convened the annual meeting of the Chesapeake Bay Executive Council, which consists of leaders of the six states in the Bay watershed, along with the District of Columbia, to retool their 10-year-old cooperative agreement at a critical juncture in the Bay cleanup.</p>
<p>The meeting comes just weeks before the inauguration of President-elect Donald Trump, who unsuccessfully tried to eliminate funding for Bay programs during his first term, adding an element of uncertainty for the Chesapeake’s state-based environmental stewards. But officials from red and blue states described their allegiance to the Bay cleanup as durable and unshakable Tuesday.</p>
<p>Moore called the Bay “the greatest heirloom clearly we have,” saying, “We did not create it. We inherited it. So it’s up to us to protect it.”</p>
<p>He also outlined legislation that he plans to introduce during the 2025 General Assembly session to strengthen Bay health, which he is tentatively calling the Bay Legacy Act.</p>
<p>The original multistate partnership, fashioned by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency in 2014 during the Obama administration, laid out 31 goals for the Bay states and D.C. to meet by 2025. While some states have fallen short of hitting some of the marks, federal and state officials describe the program — and particularly the sense of partnership it has engendered — as an overwhelming success.</p>
<div class="halfwidth ">
<div class="donateContainer">
<div class="donateTextContainer"></div>
<div class="donateButtonContainer">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="JqnaAepBtF"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/09/virginia-regional-governors-to-discuss-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-goals/">Virginia, regional governors to discuss Chesapeake Bay cleanup goals</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia, regional governors to discuss Chesapeake Bay cleanup goals&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/09/virginia-regional-governors-to-discuss-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-goals/embed/#?secret=5MVgY76bNz#?secret=JqnaAepBtF" data-secret="JqnaAepBtF" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>“The goals don’t need to be changed,” Youngkin said. “We just need more time to achieve them.”</p>
<p>The state and federal leaders did vote Tuesday to <a href="https://d18lev1ok5leia.cloudfront.net/chesapeakebay/documents/FINAL-Beyond-2025-Steering-Committee-Report.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">revise the watershed agreement</a>, taking several recommendations from a steering committee of numerous stakeholders that has been meeting for more than two years. Some of the proposed changes seek to streamline the way data is collected and analyzed, and also try to heighten accountability in Bay cleanup efforts.</p>
<p>One proposal would place more emphasis on habitat rehabilitation throughout the Bay watershed, while another would spotlight climate impacts in the government’s ongoing scientific inquiry.</p>
<p>The Chesapeake Bay Program is also going to create an Agricultural Advisory Committee, to elevate the priorities of a sector that’s critical to Bay health — and a huge economic driver in the region — before the executive council.</p>
<p>“This allows farmers to make improvements while preserving the viability of their businesses,” Youngkin said.</p>
<p>The agriculture committee will complement the work of the <a href="https://www.chesapeakebay.net/who/group/lgac" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Local Government Advisory Committee</a>, <a href="https://www.chesapeakebay.net/who/group/stac" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Scientific and Technical Advisory Committee</a> and <a href="https://www.chesapeakebay.net/who/group/citizens-advisory-committee" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Stakeholders Advisory Committee</a>.</p>
<p>Every speaker during the public meeting Tuesday — including environmental agency officials from D.C., Delaware, West Virginia and New York, and two high-ranking EPA officials — emphasized the importance of the ongoing partnership between the states and the federal government.</p>
<p>“The Chesapeake Bay has always been our region’s greatest unifier, and we just saw that bipartisan support for the Bay is alive and well,” said Hilary Harp Falk, president and CEO of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation. “It’s a really big deal when three governors and leaders from around the region meet to stack hands and reaffirm commitments to clean water. This kind of local and state leadership is more critical than ever.”</p>
<p>Such cooperation hasn’t always been the case. In 2020, Maryland, Virginia and D.C. <a href="https://marylandmatters.org/2020/09/10/maryland-virginia-d-c-sue-epa-over-failure-to-enforce-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-plans/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">filed a federal lawsuit</a>against the Trump administration’s EPA, accusing the agency of violating the Clean Water Act by failing to enforce Chesapeake Bay pollution reduction limits for Pennsylvania and New York.</p>
<p>During his speech Tuesday — he was supposed to attend the meeting in person, but was sidelined by the heavy fog that blanketed the Mid-Atlantic — Shapiro acknowledged that his state had been lagging on its commitment to Bay cleanup goals until recent years.</p>
<figure id="attachment_85317" class="wp-caption alignright"><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"> </figcaption></figure>
<p>“It is important for me to participate in this conversation, because for a long time, Pennsylvania was on the sidelines and now we’re in the game,” he said.</p>
<p>And in another sign of interstate collegiality, Youngkin nominated Moore to serve another year as chair of the executive council.</p>
<p>Asked after the meeting about the potential impact of the incoming Trump administration on Bay cleanup efforts, Moore reiterated the states’ commitment to working together.</p>
<p>“We all collectively understand the importance of this work,” he said, adding, “We look forward to working with the new administration to ensure that our goals are met.”</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Moore’s Bay Legacy Act</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Moore, from the dais of Tuesday’s meeting, offered broad details of the legislation he’s planning to introduce in the upcoming legislative session on Bay health. Those plans were fleshed out slightly by administration officials in interviews Tuesday. They said the bill, tentatively called the Bay Legacy Act, would:</p>
<ul>
<li>Seek to increase regenerative farming practices in the state, particularly on land owned by the Maryland Department of Natural Resources (DNR), in part by offering long-term leases to farmers to encourage them to regenerate the soil;</li>
<li>Improve aquaculture permitting in the state; and</li>
<li>Strengthen water-quality monitoring programs within DNR, largely by establishing new protocols that would make it easier for the agency to work with other entities and “citizen scientists” who conduct water quality tests of their own.</li>
</ul>
<p>Administration officials said more details on the proposed legislation could be released in a matter of days.</p>
<p>“We are going to continue to move forward and move fast in this state,” Moore said, “because that is what the people of Maryland demand and require.”</p>
    <div class="snrsInfobox">
		<div class="snrsInfoboxContainer">
			<div class="snrsInfoboxSubContainer" style="padding-top:24px;">
				<span style="font-weight: 400;">At the meeting, Virginia Gov. Glenn Youngkin reiterated his </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/09/virginia-regional-governors-to-discuss-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-goals/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">executive directive</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> that expressed a desire to “work with farmers, not against them,” by maintaining the voluntary adoption of pollution-reducing agricultural best management practices through a cost-share program, which added 574 new farmers last year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“We need to accomplish our water quality goals through these voluntary approaches that allow our farmers to make conservation improvements while maintaining the viability of their businesses,” Youngkin said on Tuesday, later adding that “partnership compounds effectiveness.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After the meeting, Virginia Secretary of Natural and Historic Resources Travis Voyles acknowledged in a statement to the Mercury that technical assistance, which is the engineering component needed to get pollution reducing agricultural best management practices installed properly and counted toward cleanup goals, is important.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Coupling technical assistance with fully funding the agricultural cost-share program is a critical component of providing farmers the tools needed to successfully implement best management practices,” Voyles said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The directive from Youngkin also called for re-evaluating how the state’s taxpayer dollars are used, “including stormwater,” Voyles noted. One form of funding for stormwater cleanup projects is the Stormwater Local Assistance Fund, or SLAF, which was created in 2013 and has awarded matching grants to local governments for 357 projects totalling $212 million after approvals made earlier this </span><a href="https://www.deq.virginia.gov/home/showpublisheddocument/22326/638415063756400000" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">year</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And, the directive called for the creation of a Statewide Wetlands Technical Team, led by the Department of Wildlife Resource.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wetlands can soak up pollution before it enters waterways, but have been diminished  due to development and sea level rise from climate change. Given that the watershed hasn’t been able to keep up with preserving wetlands, Virginia director of the Chesapeake Bay Commission Adrienne Kotulasaid the wetlands team will “certainly help the experts creating on-the-ground projects better align efforts, and result in increased efficiencies in their work.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Calling the loss of wetlands her top concern for reaching cleanup goals, Kotula pointed to the $8 million in funding the Department of Wildlife Resources recently received from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration through the Bipartisan Infrastructure Law to enhance the Ragged Island Wildlife Management Area along the </span><a href="https://dwr.virginia.gov/media/press-release/dwr-receives-grant-to-enhance-and-restore-critical-marsh-habitat-at-ragged-island-wildlife-management-area/?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTAAAR0fQafdwSn9XzPd4wsL6aUH2kbehWdu1IeLwauR5EzPDlNpIH1jYqHNETs_aem_5IbrEuAHr-hNymAhhK-nCQ" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">James River</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as an example the wetlands team can focus on That project can be coordinated “together,” Kotula said, with the about </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/01/federal-government-awards-150-million-to-reduce-emissions-in-virginia/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">$50 million</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the agency received as part of a larger appropriation from the Environmental Protection Agency to conserve wetlands. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The question of how Virginia will address wetlands loss at the policy level remains unanswered and is critical for the Commonwealth to address,” Kotula said, roughly four weeks before the General Assembly session starts Jan. 8. — Charlie Paullin, Virginia Mercury reporter</span>			</div>
		</div>
    </div>

	
<p><em>This story was republished with permission from <a href="https://marylandmatters.org/2024/12/10/with-trump-presidency-looming-state-federal-leaders-renew-commitment-to-bay-cleanup/" target="_blank">Maryland Matters</a>, a nonprofit newsroom which, like The Virginia Mercury, is a part of States Newsroom. </em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Latest Bay report card: Middling health but signs of progress</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/06/07/latest-bay-report-card-middling-health-but-signs-of-progress/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 04:01:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bay health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[environmental justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nitrogen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[phosphorus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UMCES report card]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=35457</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALEXANDRIA — Amid the complicated network of land and waterways spread over six states and the District of Columbia that constitutes the Chesapeake Bay watershed, Virginia and Maryland officials gathered with environmental scientists along the banks of the Potomac River Tuesday to discuss the health of the Chesapeake Bay. “Welcome to Virginia. But a heavy [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_presser.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_presser.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_presser-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_presser-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Sen. Chris Van Hollen (D-Md.) addresses state officials and environmental leaders Tuesday as the 2022 report card on Chesapeake Bay health is unveiled along the Potomac River in Alexandria, Va. (Josh Kurtz./ Maryland Matters) </p><p>ALEXANDRIA — Amid the complicated network of land and waterways spread over six states and the District of Columbia that constitutes the Chesapeake Bay watershed, Virginia and Maryland officials gathered with environmental scientists along the banks of the Potomac River Tuesday to discuss the health of the Chesapeake Bay.</p>
<p>“Welcome to Virginia. But a heavy Maryland presence,” observed Virginia Secretary of Natural and Historic Resources Travis Voyles.</p>
<p>U.S. Sen. Chris Van Hollen, D-Maryland, acknowledged the anomaly.</p>
<p>“It takes a lot to get this Marylander to this side of the Potomac River,” he said. “But this occasion is one of those moments.”</p>
<p>The occasion was the annual release of the <a href="https://ecoreportcard.org/report-cards/chesapeake-bay/bay-health/" target="_blank">report card on Bay health</a> from the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences (UMCES).</p>
<p>The topline narrative for 2022 is that overall Bay health remains at a C, which is where it has been for the last several years. But on a variety of fronts, UMCES scientists said, Bay health is improving, and the report card helps reveal where the success stories and the challenges are.</p>
<p>Of the seven indicators the environmental center uses, there were improvements in water clarity, nitrogen, phosphorus and aquatic grasses. Although conditions in the Bay overall are improving, many tributaries still have poor scores, and scores are particularly bad in many Eastern Shore watersheds.</p>
<p>Watershed health was scored in three categories: ecological, societal and economic health. In 2022, ecological earned a B-minus, societal scored a C, and economic scored a C. Overall, the conditions across all three were worse on the Eastern Shore of Maryland and Virginia than in other regions.</p>
<p>Increasingly, UMCES researchers aren’t looking just at scientific data, water quality and aquatic life to assess Bay health. They’re also trying to measure how every category they study impacts the millions of people living in the Bay watershed.</p>
<p>“We need healthy communities to achieve a healthy Bay,” said Bill Dennison, UMCES vice president for science application.</p>
<p>Assigning letter grades to the health of the Bay’s waterways, land use policies and economic conditions may seem like a gimmick. But it’s also a way to get a measure of accountability from federal, state and local leaders and the various industries that impact Bay health.</p>
<p>“Report cards are critical for holding people accountable, but they’re also important for communicating with people,” said Josh Kurtz, secretary of Maryland’s Department of Natural Resources.</p>
<p>It’s also aspirational for environmental leaders, said Serena McIlwain, Maryland’s secretary of the environment.</p>
<p>“We’re A students,” she said. “We won’t be happy until we get all A’s.”</p>
<figure id="attachment_35460" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:639px;"><a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_scores.jpg" target="_blank"><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-35460 size-full" src="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_scores.jpg" alt="" width="639" height="1024" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_scores.jpg 639w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/UMCES_scores-187x300.jpg 187w" sizes="(max-width: 639px) 100vw, 639px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Scores from the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences report card on Chesapeake Bay health.</p></figure>
<p>(The UMCES report card is one periodic assessment of Bay health. The Chesapeake Bay Foundation’s State of the Bay report card <a href="https://www.cbf.org/about-the-bay/state-of-the-bay-report/index.html" target="_blank">offered a D+ grade</a> earlier this year.)</p>
<p>The big reveal from UMCES this year took place at the Washington Sailing Marina at Daingerfield Island in Alexandria, on property owned by the National Park Service. Planes flying in and out of Reagan National Airport threatened to drown out the speakers from time to time — and so did a few honking Canada geese.</p>
<p>The annual Bay report card comes as states in the watershed, along with Washington, D.C., scramble to meet federally mandated pollution reduction goals by 2025 — and most jurisdictions are expected to fall short to one degree or another. But even so, UMCES leaders said, it’s still important for states to try to reach them, and to look beyond 2025 and to next steps for improving Bay health.</p>
<p>“The nutrient diet is working,” Dennison said. “We just need to tighten our belts and keep improving.”</p>
<p>Statewide politics play a role in the health of the Bay. While a new Democratic administration in Annapolis isn’t quite five months old, in Virginia, Republicans have been running state government for the past year and a half after eight years of Democratic rule. Voyles, Virginia’s secretary of natural and historic resources, said Republican Gov. Glenn Youngkin remains committed to Bay health and conservation, and accused the administration’s predecessors of not being transparent about what it would take for Virginia to achieve its Bay cleanup goals.</p>
<p>“On day one, Gov. Youngkin told me, he is a conservative, and conservation is a big part of being a conservative,” Voyles said.</p>
<p>He also noted the absence of agricultural representatives at the event Tuesday, calling them “a key partner” in the push for better Bay health.</p>
<p>Voyles said the Youngkin administration is pushing to allocate 20% of the state’s discretionary spending on natural resources and restoration. “He’s really showing that this is a bipartisan issue,” he said.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">On the environmental justice front</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>For the first time, the 2022 report card also sought to track the environmental justice challenges in the Bay watershed, which has some of the nation’s poorest areas, in cities like Baltimore, in Appalachia, and along the Delmarva Peninsula.</p>
<p>The index characterizes the cumulative impacts and patterns of environmental injustice across the watershed, considering such social factors such as poverty, race, ethnicity and pre-existing health conditions, which can increase these impacts. Tracked by census tract, the results were mixed.</p>
<p>But it will be a few years before UMCES is ready to assign letter grades on the environmental justice front or use the index to help calculate the overall health of the Bay.</p>
<p>“We’re not there yet,” Dennison said. “It’s new. We’re still digging into it, trying to figure out the complexity of what we’re finding.”</p>
<p>Van Hollen said the federal government can help pull together the cleanup goals and efforts of states and other shareholders.</p>
<p>“When you have a watershed that encompasses six states and the District of Columbia and knows no boundaries, it’s important that you have a federal presence,” he said.</p>
<p>The federal government’s Chesapeake Bay Program provides $92 million annually, and a new program within the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service has a program that provides $8 million a year to sustain lands that surround the Bay. Additionally, the big federal infrastructure spending bill has earmarked $238 million for bay cleanup over five years.</p>
<p>But Van Hollen and other speakers Tuesday said climate change is jeopardizing the progress the state and federal governments are making in combating Bay pollution. He likened it to trying to run up an escalator.</p>
<p>“We’re running faster to stay in place with climate change,” said Martha Shimkin, deputy director of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s Chesapeake Bay office, picking up on the metaphor.</p>
<p><em>This story was <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2023/06/06/latest-bay-report-card-middling-health-but-signs-of-progress/" target="_blank">first published</a> by Maryland Matters, a sister site of the Mercury within the States Newsroom network. Maryland Natural Resources Secretary Josh Kurtz is no relation to Josh Kurtz of Maryland Matters.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>EPA settles lawsuit with states, enviros over Chesapeake Bay pollution from Pa.</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/04/20/epa-settles-lawsuit-with-states-enviros-over-chesapeake-bay-pollution-from-pa/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 21:41:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bay cleanup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maryland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nutrient pollution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pennsylvania]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Environmental Protection Agency]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=35050</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has reached a tentative settlement with Virginia, other states and environmental groups that sued the agency in 2020, charging that federal officials weren’t doing enough to stop Chesapeake Bay pollution originating in Pennsylvania. The proposed settlement will be published Friday in The Federal Register, triggering a 30-day public comment period. When the comment [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="665" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-1024x665.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-1024x665.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-300x195.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-768x499.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-1536x998.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-2048x1331.jpg 2048w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-696x452.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-1068x694.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-646x420.jpg 646w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Deltaville-Bay-view-3-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Deltaville sits near the tip of Virginia's Middle Peninsula on the Chesapeake Bay. (Sarah Vogelsong/Virginia Mercury)</p><p>The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has reached a tentative settlement with Virginia, other states and environmental groups that sued the agency in 2020, charging that federal officials weren’t doing enough to stop Chesapeake Bay pollution originating in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.cbf.org/document-library/litigation/chesapeake-bay-final-settlement-agreement-042023.pdf" target="_blank">proposed settlement</a> will be published Friday in <a href="https://public-inspection.federalregister.gov/2023-08510.pdf" target="_blank">The Federal Register</a>, triggering a 30-day public comment period. When the comment period closes, EPA will work out final details with the plaintiffs.</p>
<p>“We think this is another important moment in the effort to clean up the Bay, where we see collective accountability to meeting the [pollution reduction] goals,” Hillary Harp Falk, president of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, a lead plaintiff in the litigation, said Thursday on a call with reporters.</p>
<p>The settlement would end <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2020/09/10/virginia-maryland-d-c-sue-epa-over-failure-to-enforce-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-plans/" target="_blank">two separate lawsuits</a> filed against EPA during the Trump administration — one from the Chesapeake Bay Foundation and several other groups, including Anne Arundel County, the other from the attorneys general of Maryland, Virginia, Delaware and the District of Columbia. The suits accused EPA of failing to enforce provisions of the Clean Water Act by not requiring Pennsylvania to develop a plan to fully meet pollution reduction goals for the Bay set several years earlier in a multi-state compact with the federal government.</p>
<p>The suits also noted that EPA did not use its mechanisms for penalizing states like Pennsylvania that did not meet their pollution reduction goals or for requiring the states to earmark sufficient funding for Bay cleanup.</p>
<p>The settlement requires EPA to, among other things, look for ways to reduce pollution from agriculture in Pennsylvania — the state’s biggest source of water pollution — and stormwater runoff from urban and suburban land. As part of the settlement, EPA commits to increasing compliance and enforcement efforts, as long as it has the funding to do so.</p>
<p>EPA has also promised to prioritize its efforts in Pennsylvania in the jurisdictions that contribute the most pollution to, or have the largest impact on, local rivers and streams: Lancaster, York, Bedford, Cumberland, Centre, Franklin and Lebanon counties.</p>
<p>The EPA will also take a close look at farms not currently required to have federal permits that have proximity to rivers and streams to see if there is significant damage to water quality from manure generation, manure management practices and/or available storage capacity, as well as those farms&#8217; compliance history. If EPA determines that a farm is a significant contributor of pollution, the regulators will confer with Pennsylvania officials about designating the farm as a pollution source subject to environmental permitting.</p>
<p>“This settlement agreement really puts things in writing and makes sure that we have clear deadlines,” Falk said. “So we think this is a significant moment today.”</p>
<p>During the Obama administration, EPA reached an agreement with all the states in the Chesapeake Bay watershed — Maryland, Virginia, Pennsylvania, Delaware, New York, West Virginia and the District of Columbia — to reduce the “total maximum daily load” of pollution in the Bay. Each state was given specific targets to meet by 2025.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="ePEZwY3kdo"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/02/16/deal-reached-over-extension-for-va-farmers-to-adopt-pollution-reduction-practices/">Deal reached over extension for Va. farmers to adopt pollution reduction practices</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Deal reached over extension for Va. farmers to adopt pollution reduction practices&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/02/16/deal-reached-over-extension-for-va-farmers-to-adopt-pollution-reduction-practices/embed/#?secret=jd6SNEGuOw#?secret=ePEZwY3kdo" data-secret="ePEZwY3kdo" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Last fall, EPA leaders <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2022/10/12/chesapeake-bay-leaders-resolute-even-as-cleanup-targets-become-more-elusive/" target="_blank">tacitly conceded that most states would fall short of their goals</a>, and regional leaders now say that 2025 is “a deadline but not the finish line.” In, Virginia lawmakers and the Chesapeake Bay Foundation <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2023/02/16/deal-reached-over-extension-for-va-farmers-to-adopt-pollution-reduction-practices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.virginiamercury.com/2023/02/16/deal-reached-over-extension-for-va-farmers-to-adopt-pollution-reduction-practices/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1682101125906000&amp;usg=AOvVaw088iaD8rz0w2RMkN7q2V-T">reached a deal during the past legislative session</a> to extend the deadline from 2026 to 2028 for farmers to voluntarily implement best management practices to reduce nutrient runoff before the practices become mandatory, and require the state to fully-fund its cost-share program.</p>
<p>But Pennsylvania, by the account of the federal government and neighboring states, has consistently lagged behind.</p>
<p>On the press call Thursday, officials, environmental activists and industry leaders asserted that the agreement will bring a measure of accountability to Bay cleanup efforts.</p>
<p>“This settlement is all about the EPA taking action to ensure that Pennsylvania, a signatory to the agreement, is doing its part to prevent pollution from going into the Bay,” said Maryland’s Democratic Attorney General Anthony G. Brown.</p>
<p>Anne Arundel County Executive Steuart Pittman (D), whose jurisdiction has 500 miles of waterfront along the Bay and its tributaries, said his county has invested about $500 million over the past decade to bolster the shoreline and limit farm runoff — a possible model for Pennsylvania leaders to follow.</p>
<p>“We can tell Pennsylvania that yes, you can do this,” he said. “It’s hard work, but it needs to be done.”</p>
<p>Bobby Whitescarver, a Virginia farmer and former Natural Resource Conservation Service representative, said monitoring and encouraging best management practices among farmers &#8220;assures water quality improvement for the Bay.&#8221;</p>
<div>&#8220;We welcome EPA’s input to help Pennsylvania farmers do their part to save the Bay, its tributaries, and the water where they live,” said Whitescarver.</div>
<p>Last summer, <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2022/07/21/pennsylvania-bay-cleanup-money-could-be-turning-point-in-regional-efforts/" target="_blank">Pennsylvania officials committed $220 million</a> to a new fund dedicated to reducing pollution flowing into state waterways, which regional leaders hailed as important to Bay cleanup efforts.</p>
<p>Falk on Thursday called the Clean Streams Fund “an important down payment on Pennsylvania’s commitment to clean streams, a clean Susquehanna [River] and a clean Bay. But we need more.”</p>
<p>Jon A. Mueller, vice president for litigation at the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, said the draft settlement with the federal government does not foreclose future litigation if stakeholders believe any of the parties aren’t living up to their end of the bargain.</p>
<p>“If at any place along the way we feel that EPA has not lived up to the agreement, we have the ability to go back to court,” he said.</p>
<p>Robert T. Brown, president of the Maryland Watermen’s Association, another plaintiff in the 2020 lawsuit, said the industry is counting on federal officials to comply with the agreement.</p>
<p>“We have to trust the EPA to enforce these laws,” he said. “We had a little problem with them doing it before this lawsuit. Now we have to trust them. We have to trust and verify.”</p>
<p><em>This story was <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2023/04/20/epa-settles-lawsuit-with-states-enviros-over-chesapeake-bay-pollution-from-pa/" target="_blank">first published</a> in Maryland Matters, a sister site to the Mercury within the States Newsroom network. Mercury reporter Charlie Paullin contributed to this story. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chesapeake Bay leaders resolute even as cleanup targets become more elusive</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2022/10/12/chesapeake-bay-leaders-resolute-even-as-cleanup-targets-become-more-elusive/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 15:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[agricultural pollution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay cleanup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay Executive Council]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gov. Glenn Youngkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nitrogen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[phosphorus]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=33292</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a 2025 federal deadline for states to meet ambitious goals for cleaning up the Chesapeake Bay draws closer, it is starting to dawn on state and U.S. officials and other stakeholders that some states will fall short. Virginia Gov. Glenn Youngkin (R) admitted as much on Tuesday. “That was a difficult recognition,” he said. [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="800" height="532" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds.jpg 800w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-768x511.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-696x463.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-632x420.jpg 632w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Snowy egrets and mallard on eroding marsh near Poplar Island in Talbot County, Md., on May 20, 2010. (Photo by Alicia Pimental/Chesapeake Bay Program)</p><p>As a 2025 federal deadline for states to meet ambitious goals for cleaning up the Chesapeake Bay draws closer, it is starting to dawn on state and U.S. officials and other stakeholders that some states will fall short. Virginia Gov. Glenn Youngkin (R) admitted as much on Tuesday.</p>
<p>“That was a difficult recognition,” he said. “I think we have a clear commitment to meeting those goals. Unfortunately, it won’t be by 2025.”</p>
<p>Youngkin made his remarks at the annual meeting of the Chesapeake Bay Executive Council, which brings the leaders of states in the Bay watershed together with federal officials and other leaders to assess the state of the Bay’s health. Tuesday’s meeting was held at the headquarters of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, which has just issued its own <a href="https://d18lev1ok5leia.cloudfront.net/chesapeakebay/documents/2021-2022-Bay-Barometer_2022-10-10-202922_hdrd.pdf" target="_blank">mixed though generally sunny assessment</a>.</p>
<p>These meetings are usually a chance for governors and cabinet secretaries and other officials to boast about the progress being made cleaning up the Chesapeake Bay — progress that they say is tangible and real.</p>
<p>“It is clear that so many positive developments have been made despite the emerging threats of climate change and with the growing population,” said Kandis Boyd, the new director of EPA’s 39-year-old Chesapeake Bay Program.</p>
<p>But the enthusiasm was dampened by knowledge that some states won’t meet their targeted goals by 2025. Still, U.S. EPA  Administrator Michael Regan, who was chairing the meeting, said that officials from all six Bay states and the District of Columbia are committed to attaining the pollution reduction goals. It’s up to environmental agency officials in each state, he said, to figure out which goals are realistic, how to expedite certain plans of action, and to reconsider how to ensure that the lagging targets are met as quickly as possible.</p>
<p>“I think we’ve all acknowledged that 2025 is fleeting in terms of achieving all of our substantial goals,” Regan said. “We intend to set reasonable achievable goals in a timeline that can help us [eventually] meet our broader, more ambitious goals.”</p>
<p>He added that the bipartisan federal infrastructure bill that became law last year will provide an additional $90 million a year over the next five years earmarked for Chesapeake Bay cleanup. That will go to state and local governments, agricultural groups, watermen and nonprofits, among others.</p>
<p>In Virginia, the <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2022/06/29/record-funding-to-reduce-agricultural-pollution-expected-to-aid-bay-cleanup/" target="_blank">General Assembly dedicated record funding this year</a> to state programs that help farmers pay for pollution reduction practices like streamside fencing. <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2021/06/08/as-2025-deadline-for-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-looms-virginia-zeroes-in-on-agriculture/" target="_blank">About three-quarters of the pollution reductions Virginia still has to achieve are expected to come from the agricultural sector</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="AzfLjgnBBc"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2021/06/08/as-2025-deadline-for-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-looms-virginia-zeroes-in-on-agriculture/">As 2025 deadline for Chesapeake Bay cleanup looms, Virginia zeroes in on agriculture</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;As 2025 deadline for Chesapeake Bay cleanup looms, Virginia zeroes in on agriculture&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2021/06/08/as-2025-deadline-for-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-looms-virginia-zeroes-in-on-agriculture/embed/#?secret=5REHBM9eXa#?secret=AzfLjgnBBc" data-secret="AzfLjgnBBc" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<div id="attachment_72683" class="wp-caption alignright">
<p id="caption-attachment-72683" class="wp-caption-text">.</p>
</div>
<p>In an interview, Hillary Harp Falk, president of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, which issued its own report last week on the health of the Bay, complete with <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2022/10/05/states-not-on-track-to-meet-2025-chesapeake-bay-goals-says-report/" target="_blank">warnings about how certain states are falling short</a>, said she was pleased that state and federal leaders publicly recommitted to meeting the cleanup goals.</p>
<p>But she added, “We need strong state leadership and federal accountability to get close to 2025. The devil’s in the details.”</p>
<p>The Choose Clean Water Coalition, which consists of more than 270 nonprofit groups in the Chesapeake watershed, expressed similar sentiments.</p>
<p>“We are focused on the actions that will follow the words shared this afternoon from the members of the Executive Council,” said the coalition’s executive director, Kristin Reilly. “If we are to provide clean water to all 18 million people whose local waterways feed the Bay, we need accountability and sufficient investments to ensure we meet our commitments.”</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Youngkin says Northam administration &#8216;wasn&#8217;t completely transparent&#8217; about Bay plans</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>Without naming him, Youngkin sought to pin some of the blame for Virginia’s shortfall on his predecessor, former Gov. Ralph Northam (D), an Eastern Shore native, saying “the previous administration wasn’t completely transparent about how they went about setting their agenda.” He suggested that the Northam administration did not provide adequate funding for Bay cleanup and also set “artificial expiration dates” for certain programs.</p>
<p>Asked about the transparency concerns and programs that expired early, Youngkin spokesperson Macaulay Porter pointed to other comments made by Youngkin at the meeting.</p>
<p>The governor criticized the state&#8217;s &#8220;unrealistic&#8221; goal of planting 30,000 acres of urban tree canopy by 2025, compared to other Bay states that planned on planting 6,000 acres. &#8220;The reality of course is that our forestry staff has informed me that this goal isn&#8217;t feasible,&#8221; he said. &#8220;In fact, there had been no previous focus on achieving it.&#8221;</p>
<p>Youngkin also said the previous administration &#8220;in fact had 2030 as the ultimate timeline. Funding streams as a result were insufficient in order to meet the 2025 goals.&#8221;</p>
<p>“I’m a homegrown Virginia boy,” Youngkin asserted. “Not just in Virginia, but in Virginia Beach, and the Chesapeake means a whole lot to me personally. I grew up on it. I love the Bay and I want other folks to have the chance to love it just as much as I do.”</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="W3lYlo91A9"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2020/10/22/with-new-roadmap-to-combat-rising-seas-virginia-officially-acknowledges-the-threat-of-climate-change/">With new roadmap to combat rising seas, Virginia officially acknowledges the threat of climate change</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;With new roadmap to combat rising seas, Virginia officially acknowledges the threat of climate change&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2020/10/22/with-new-roadmap-to-combat-rising-seas-virginia-officially-acknowledges-the-threat-of-climate-change/embed/#?secret=Itx9SsDRkZ#?secret=W3lYlo91A9" data-secret="W3lYlo91A9" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Youngkin brought with him Andrew Wheeler, a former coal company lobbyist who served as EPA administrator during the Trump administration. Wheeler, whose nomination as Virginia&#8217;s top environmental official was <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2022/02/08/senate-democrats-block-wheeler-appointment/" target="_blank">blocked by Senate Democrats</a>, is now advising the Virginia governor on environmental matters and <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2022/07/01/youngkin-appoints-wheeler-to-head-new-office-of-regulatory-management/" target="_blank">leading a new Office of Regulatory Management</a> that aims to reduce the state&#8217;s regulatory requirements by 25%. Environmentalists have harshly criticized Youngkin’s association with Wheeler.</p>
<p>Maryland Sen. Sarah Elfreth, D-Anne Arundel, noted that Virginia had adopted a revolving loan fund for climate resilience programs, created a <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2021/12/08/we-can-adapt-virginia-releases-coastal-master-plan/" target="_blank">flood protection master plan</a>, hired a chief resiliency officer — a program Maryland is emulating — and has begun teaching environmental literacy.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, “in Maryland, we had one of our best sessions yet,” Elfreth said, referencing passage of the Climate Solutions Now Act, a bill to ban the chemical PFAS, and to support oyster restoration programs.</p>
<p>“But there is so much more work ahead,” she said.</p>
<p>Ann Swanson, executive director of the Chesapeake Bay Commission, who is retiring later this fall after more than 30 years on the job, reminded the governors of the unique role they play in ensuring the Bay’s health — not just because of their impact on policy but because of their ability to shape the public conversation.</p>
<p>“You have voices that are incredibly unique,” she said. “When you speak, people jump.”</p>
<p><em>This story originally appeared in Maryland Matters, a sister publication of The Virginia Mercury within the States Newsroom network. It has been updated with comments from Gov. Glenn Youngkin&#8217;s office. The story was corrected to note that Wheeler was a coal company lobbyist, not a company executive. </em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New director for Chesapeake Bay program selected</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2022/06/06/new-director-for-chesapeake-bay-program-selected/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 04:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chesapeake Bay Program]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kandis Boyd]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=32017</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A veteran government scientist and meteorologist is poised to become director of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s Chesapeake Bay Program, which oversees federal and regional Bay environmental monitoring and cleanup efforts. The EPA announced Thursday that Kandis Boyd will take over as director of the program on Monday. She’ll be the first person of color [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="800" height="532" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds.jpg 800w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-768x511.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-696x463.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/baywithbirds-632x420.jpg 632w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Snowy egrets and mallard on eroding marsh near Poplar Island in Talbot County, Md., on May 20, 2010. (Photo by Alicia Pimental/Chesapeake Bay Program)</p><p>A veteran government scientist and meteorologist is poised to become director of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s Chesapeake Bay Program, which oversees federal and regional Bay environmental monitoring and cleanup efforts.</p>
<p>The EPA announced Thursday that Kandis Boyd will take over as director of the program on Monday. She’ll be the first person of color to hold a leadership position on government Chesapeake Bay policy — and the first permanent head of that EPA office in over a year.</p>
<p>“I’m thrilled to have Kandis join our leadership team as we are stepping up restoration efforts for the Bay in the face of emerging challenges,” said EPA Mid-Atlantic Regional Administrator Adam Ortiz — a former state and local environmental official in Maryland. “Her experience as a strategic leader in the sciences and success engaging diverse communities and youth will help take the Bay effort to a new level as we focus on climate change and vulnerable communities.”</p>
<p>According to the EPA, Boyd has nearly 30 years of experience leading, teaching, advising and mentoring students and early career enthusiasts in environmental and atmospheric science. The first African-American woman to receive an undergraduate degree in Meteorology from Iowa State University, Boyd served most recently as strategic advisor for the Office of Equity and Civil Rights at the National Science Foundation. That position included serving as the first deputy division director of the NSF Division of Grants and Agreements, where she provided oversight and direction for 35 staffers, a $5 billion budget, and more than 12,000 new grants a year. She has a has a Ph.D. in public administration and master’s degrees in meteorology, water resources engineering and project management</p>
<div id="attachment_69466" class="wp-caption alignleft">
<figure id="attachment_69466" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:180px;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="img-fluid wp-image-69466 size-full" src="https://www.marylandmatters.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/F8B620B5-FBF1-E4D6-C9156DB9F813746F_medium.jpg" alt="" width="180" height="180" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69466" /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Kandis Boyd, the new director of EPA’s Chesapeake Bay Program.</p></figure>
<p id="caption-attachment-69466" class="wp-caption-text">
</div>
<p>Boyd spent most of her career at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. During Hurricane Katrina, she delivered around-the-clock on-site meteorological forecasts during the 2005 landfall of that hurricane. She served as the designated federal officer for the third National Climate Assessment Development Advisory Committee, co-chaired the first NOAA Environmental Modeling Strategic Plan, served as an adviser for NOAA’s $2 billion satellite portfolio, and was both acting director and deputy director of the NOAA Weather Program Office.</p>
<p>EPA’s Chesapeake Bay Program coordinates activities and implements strategies for meeting the restoration goals of the Chesapeake Bay watershed, which covers 64,000 square miles across New York, West Virginia, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia and the District of Columbia.</p>
<p>“I’m extremely humbled and excited to work with a forward-focused team of specialists and experts to advance the ongoing work of EPA and the Chesapeake Bay partners,” Boyd said. “I’m ready to dive in and get to work on the most pressing matters before us.”</p>
<p>The last permanent head of the Chesapeake Bay program was Dana Aunkst, who served from December 2018 to March 2021. Aunkst was a longtime official with the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection before taking the EPA job. He served at a time when the Trump administration was regularly trying to cut Bay cleanup programs and was sued by states like Maryland for not doing enough to hold other states accountable for their pollution reduction commitments.</p>
<p>Hillary Falk, president of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, which has been a plaintiff in some of those lawsuits, praised Boyd’s selection.</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">“Many challenges remain, time is running short, and climate change threatens to reverse the progress we’ve made,” she said. “The good news is we also have unprecedented new funding for the Chesapeake Bay Program and federal farm conservation programs that can help us make up ground quickly. Dr. Boyd has the leadership skills to help coordinate the efforts of the multiple federal agencies that play a significant role in Bay restoration, the knowledge to ensure we are guided by the best science, and the personal commitment to ensure that vulnerable communities are not left behind.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chesapeake Bay Foundation names new president</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/chesapeake-bay-foundation-names-new-president/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 16:40:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cheseapeake Bay]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?post_type=blog_va&#038;p=29293</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Chesapeake Bay Foundation, the advocacy group dedicated to Bay health, announced Monday that its Board of Trustees has selected Hilary Harp Falk to be CBF’s next president and CEO. She will succeed William C. Baker, who began working for CBF as an intern in 1976 and has led the organization since 1981. Falk comes [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="560" height="420" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/HilaryHarpFalk_Photo-Credit_Dave-Harp41629-1-560x420-1.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/HilaryHarpFalk_Photo-Credit_Dave-Harp41629-1-560x420-1.jpg 560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/HilaryHarpFalk_Photo-Credit_Dave-Harp41629-1-560x420-1-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Hilary Harp Falk, incoming president of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation. (Photo by Dave Falk/ Courtesy of Chesapeake Bay Foundation.)
</p><p class="x_MsoNormal">The Chesapeake Bay Foundation, the advocacy group dedicated to Bay health, announced Monday that its Board of Trustees has selected Hilary Harp Falk to be CBF’s next president and CEO. She will succeed William C. Baker, who began working for CBF as an intern in 1976 and has led the organization since 1981.</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">Falk comes to CBF from the National Wildlife Federation, where she was chief program officer, leading and integrating national and regional programs while serving as strategic adviser to the CEO. Previously, Falk was the federation’s vice president for regional conservation, responsible for leading the organization’s seven regional offices.</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">Falk said she was “humbled and honored” to be succeeding Baker at a time when the federal government and Bay states, along with other stakeholders, are working to attain aggressive pollution abatement goals by 2025.Falk also had stints as NWF’s regional executive director for the Mid-Atlantic and director of the Choose Clean Water Coalition, which comprised more than 200 advocacy organizations working together to protect and restore the Chesapeake Bay. And she was an intern at the Chesapeake Bay Foundation in 1997.</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">“We stand at a crossroads for Bay restoration,” she said. “Finishing the work of Chesapeake Clean Water Blueprint by 2025 and leaving a restored Bay to our children and grandchildren is possible. But it is not certain.”</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">Currently, the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, is suing the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency in federal court for not holding some states, particularly Pennsylvania, accountable for their clean water commitments. The CBF has offices in Annapolis, Harrisburg, Pa., Richmond, Va., and Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>Baker praised Falk, saying she has “Bay water in her veins.”</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">She is also being hailed as a champion for women’s leadership and advancing equity in the conservation movement. She was a 2016-2017 fellow with the International Women’s Forum and co-chaired the National Wildlife Federation’s Women in Conservation Leadership Advisory Council.</p>
<p class="x_MsoNormal">“Strong leadership skills, a commitment to equity in the environmental movement, and a devotion to following the science to restore the health of the Chesapeake Bay made Hilary Harp Falk the clear choice for leading CBF during this critical time,” said Elizabeth Oliver-Farrow, chair of the organization’s board of trustees.</p>
<p>Falk is scheduled to start her new job on Jan. 3.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bay states seek new federal funding initiative for farm cleanup</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/bay-states-seek-new-federal-funding-initiative-for-farm-cleanup/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>svogelsong@virginiamercury.com (Sarah Vogelsong)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 04:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?post_type=blog_va&#038;p=28673</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Virginia Agriculture and Forestry Secretary Bettina Ring and her counterparts from the five other Chesapeake Bay states are seeking a sit-down with U.S. Agriculture Secretary Tom Vilsack to discuss a proposal to pump extra federal funding into a concerted effort to clean up the Bay. Ring and the other state  agriculture officials are embracing a [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="521" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/Susquehanna-River-Valley-Hyner-View.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/Susquehanna-River-Valley-Hyner-View.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/Susquehanna-River-Valley-Hyner-View-300x153.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/Susquehanna-River-Valley-Hyner-View-768x391.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The West Branch of the Susquehanna River in central Pennsylvania. (Getty Images) </p><p style="font-weight: 400;">Virginia Agriculture and Forestry Secretary Bettina Ring and her counterparts from the five other Chesapeake Bay states are seeking a sit-down with U.S. Agriculture Secretary Tom Vilsack to discuss a proposal to pump extra federal funding into a concerted effort to clean up the Bay.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Ring and the other state  agriculture officials are embracing a proposal from the Chesapeake Bay Commission to create a <a href="https://www.agriculture.pa.gov/FoodForThought/Documents/CRFI%20Proposal%20to%20USDA.pdf" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.agriculture.pa.gov/FoodForThought/Documents/CRFI%2520Proposal%2520to%2520USDA.pdf&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1631134111844000&amp;usg=AFQjCNGzPfGTg81081bubym2w3V0a2eHpQ" target="_blank">Chesapeake Resilient Farms Initiative</a>, which would tap $737 million in federal funding over the next decade to help clean up nutrient and sediment pollution from farms in the Chesapeake Bay watershed.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">In their <a href="https://www.agriculture.pa.gov/FoodForThought/Documents/CRFI%20Letter%20of%20Support.pdf" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.agriculture.pa.gov/FoodForThought/Documents/CRFI%2520Letter%2520of%2520Support.pdf&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1631134111844000&amp;usg=AFQjCNFzMOasRWVcIOuJG9EhVvL2i4gKxw" target="_blank">letter to Vilsack</a>, dated Aug. 25, the state leaders noted that federal cleanup mandates for the Bay, which provide goals for each state in the watershed, must be met by 2025, and that 80 percent of the remaining pollution reductions the federal government is seeking are being imposed on the agricultural sector. The officials said states would find it easier to meet their cleanup goals with dedicated federal funding that aids farmers.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;We know we have a receptive audience for voluntary cost-share programs designed to achieve these restoration goals,&#8221; Ring and her counterparts from West Virginia, Maryland, Delaware, New York and Pennsylvania wrote. &#8220;What we lack is the necessary capacity, both human and financial.&#8221;</p>
<figure id="attachment_809" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:245px;"><a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/watershed_map_from_tmdl_website.gif" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-809" src="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/watershed_map_from_tmdl_website.gif" alt="" width="245" height="350" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  The Chesapeake Bay watershed. Image from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.</p></figure>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">The officials said new sources of funding would be needed to meet Chesapeake Bay cleanup goals, and suggested that the U.S. Agriculture Department was uniquely equipped to help them find it.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, representatives from the Chesapeake Bay Commission including current commission Chair David Bulova, a Democratic state delegate from Fairfax, wrote Vilsack that &#8220;without additional resources from our federal partners to assist farmers in the bay watershed, we will not meet our goals.&#8221;</p>
<p>Modeled after the Mississippi River Basin Healthy Watersheds Initiative, which Vilsack created in 2009, the Chesapeake Resilient Farms Initiative would pool various federal agricultural funding programs and target them for Bay cleanup.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;This funding would primarily target those sub-watersheds — particularly the Susquehanna River — known to have the greatest influence on the Chesapeake Bay and offer the most cost-effective solutions,&#8221; the agriculture leaders wrote to Vilsack in their Aug. 25 letter. &#8220;This is particularly true in Pennsylvania, where agriculture is heavily concentrated and the rural nature of the Susquehanna River watershed means agriculture is the dominant source of excess nutrients in the commonwealth&#8217;s waters.&#8221;</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Pennsylvania Gov. Tom Wolf (D) endorsed the idea on Tuesday. He said a regional initiative would help farmers and regulators create more sustainable agriculture practices that reduce nitrogen output, improve water quality, and would mitigate the impacts of climate change on agriculture.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Last week, we all saw the devastating and deadly impacts of climate change as Hurricane Ida swept across our nation,&#8221; Wolf said.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Farmers are waiting to jump into action,&#8221; he added. &#8220;We just need support, as was provided to the Mississippi River Basin, to get moving.&#8221;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Will Baker, longtime head of Chesapeake Bay Foundation, to step down by year&#8217;s end</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2021/01/28/will-baker-longtime-head-of-chesapeake-bay-foundation-to-step-down-years-end/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 18:13:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://s37751.p1438.sites.pressdns.com/?p=25062</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[William C. Baker, longtime president of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, announced Thursday that he plans to retire later this year after 40 years on the job. Baker, 67, joined the CBF as an intern in 1976 and became its leader in 1981, transforming the organization from a local environmental group into a regional powerhouse that [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size-300x225.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size-768x576.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size-80x60.png 80w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size-265x198.png 265w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size-696x522.png 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Will-Baker-correct-size-560x420.png 560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Chesapeake Bay Foundation President William C. Baker has announced that he will be retiring by the end of 2021. (Chesapeake Bay Foundation photo.)
</p><p>William C. Baker, longtime president of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, announced Thursday that he plans to retire later this year after 40 years on the job.</p>
<p>Baker, 67, joined the CBF as an intern in 1976 and became its leader in 1981, transforming the organization from a local environmental group into a regional powerhouse that mixes advocacy with conservation work, education programs and community outreach. From a handful of employees when Baker came on board, CBF now has a staff of 200, with offices in Annapolis, Richmond, Va., Harrisburg, Pa., and Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>Baker’s retirement was <a href="https://www.bayjournal.com/news/people/chesapeake-bay-foundation-leader-will-baker-retiring-after-40-years/article_75aaab34-60e9-11eb-a3ec-5f5c5f2d4366.html" target="_blank">first reported</a> in <em>The Bay Journal</em>.</p>
<p>“I’m proud of the many things we have accomplished over the years. But there is a lot left to do in 2021 and beyond,” Baker said.</p>
<p>He connects the organization’s growth and impact in its half century to the progress that governments and stakeholders have made in cleaning up the Chesapeake Bay.</p>
<p>While the CBF’s own studies <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/2021/01/05/chesapeake-bay-receives-d-for-second-year-in-a-row/" target="_blank">have shown mixed progress</a> when it comes to improving the Bay’s health, the seven states in the Bay watershed and the federal government are moving toward meeting pollution abatement goals by 2025 ― though it has not been a seamless process. In September, Maryland, Virginia and Washington, D.C., <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2020/09/10/virginia-maryland-d-c-sue-epa-over-failure-to-enforce-chesapeake-bay-cleanup-plans/" target="_blank">filed a federal lawsuit </a>against the U.S. Environmental Protection Administration accusing the agency of violating the Clean Water Act by failing to enforce pollution reduction limits for two upstream states, Pennsylvania and New York.</p>
<p>“We stand on the precipice of saving this national treasure,” Baker said. “We, all who are involved across the Bay’s vast watershed, are making history. Saving the Chesapeake Bay can be the greatest environmental success this country has ever seen.”</p>
<p>Tributes to Baker rolled in from Maryland leaders Thursday.</p>
<p>“It has been a privilege to work with Will over the last 30 years, from my time in the General Assembly to now,” U.S. Sen. Chris Van Hollen (D-Md.) said in a statement. “I am grateful to have counted on Will as a partner in our many efforts ― from fighting to prevent slant drilling in sensitive areas around the Bay, to pushing for increased federal funding for the Chesapeake Bay Program, to providing support for farmers to prevent agricultural runoff, and most recently, securing the enactment of the Chesapeake WILD Act.”</p>
<p>U.S. House Majority Leader Steny H. Hoyer (D-Md.) said Baker “leaves behind an unmatched legacy as a dedicated advocate for the Chesapeake Bay.”</p>
<p>Elizabeth Oliver-Farrow, the chair of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation board, said she and her colleagues are “committed to a broad and thorough search for a new president. I am confident we will find a replacement who shares our passion and commitment and will guide our work in restoring this national treasure.”</p>
<p><strong><em>This article was first published by Maryland Matters.</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cross-Potomac unity: Virginia and Maryland Democrats team up on PAC</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2019/09/26/cross-potomac-unity-virginia-and-maryland-democrats-team-up-on-pac/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 11:02:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2019]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://s37751.p1438.sites.pressdns.com/?p=11671</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Democratic and union operatives in Virginia and Maryland have teamed up to create a political action committee to help political candidates on both sides of the Potomac River.  But for now, their focus is on Virginia, where all 140 seats in the General Assembly will go up for reelection in just over a month and [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="650" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-1024x650.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-1024x650.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-300x190.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-768x487.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-696x442.png 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-1068x678.png 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river-662x420.png 662w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/potomac-river.png 1302w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Great Falls of the Potomac. (Aquatint engraved by J. Cartwright and drawn by George Beck, 1802)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Democratic and union operatives in Virginia and Maryland have teamed up to create a political action committee to help political candidates on both sides of the Potomac River. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But for now, their focus is on Virginia, where all 140 seats in the General Assembly will go up for reelection in just over a month and organizers plan to send busloads of volunteers into the state &#8212; likely low voter-turnout districts in the Richmond area &#8212; to help Democratic candidates. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other volunteers will be tasked with phone-banking and postcard-writing, to aid voter turnout efforts. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The PAC, known as Potomac Rising, held its first fundraiser last week in Gaithersburg. The event was billed as an ERA house party, pegged to the push to get the now-dormant Equal Rights Amendment ratified in Virginia. Eileen Davis, a longtime ERA advocate who is the mother of U.S. Rep. Abigail Spanberger (D-Va.), and Virginia state Sen. Scott Surovell (D) were the featured speakers.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While liberal activists from Maryland sporadically travel to Virginia to door-knock for Democratic candidates in tight congressional races or in state elections here, the organizers of the PAC are aiming to make the relationship more durable and more reciprocal. Maryland Democrats usually don’t get out of state help – even when they need it – because the state is considered so blue.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“What we thought was, if we created a permanent structure with a long-term vision, we could start building coalitions to help each other on campaigns and in policy battles,” said Brian Kildee, one of the two co-founders of Potomac Rising, who serves as the PAC’s treasurer. “A lot of the efforts you see are one-offs, and they drop off after the election.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Kildee, a former official with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, is a Silver Spring resident who has been active in Montgomery County politics for a quarter century. He currently runs a consulting business that mostly works with labor unions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The PAC’s other co-founder and chairwoman is Laura McClintock, a Richmond-based political consultant who held high-ranking posts at the U.S. Department of Labor during the Obama administration and has run several campaigns and ballot initiatives on the West Coast.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">McClintock and Kildee have been meeting with politicians, staffers, operatives and activists on both sides of the Potomac.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“I’m really excited about the potential,” Surovell, who represents parts of Fairfax, Prince William and Stafford counties, said in an interview. “Our states are tied together in a lot of ways that I don’t think people realize. Our states should be working a lot more closely together on policy and politics. We share a lot of the same quality-of-life issues.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Given the realities of the political calendar, Virginia will be the focus of the PAC’s activities for the foreseeable future – though two more fundraisers are planned for this fall in Maryland.</span></p>
<p>And e<span style="font-weight: 400;">ven after November, Virginia will likely continue to receive most of the PAC’s attention for the next couple of years. There don’t appear to be any competitive congressional races in Maryland in 2020, while the nonpartisan </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cook Political Report</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> places four Virginia House districts in the competitive category. Cook rates two of those races – including Spanberger’s bid for a second term – as tossups.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_11673" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12.jpg" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-11673" src="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-80x60.jpg 80w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-265x198.jpg 265w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-696x522.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-1068x801.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12-560x420.jpg 560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/FullSizeRender-12.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Va. Sen. Scott Surovell, D-Fairfax, spoke at the inaugural fundraiser for Potomac Rising in Maryland last week. (Josh Kurtz/Maryland Matters)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In 2021, Virginia will have elections for its three statewide offices – governor, lieutenant governor and attorney general – as well as races for all the House of Delegates seats.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Maryland political season cranks up in 2022, and PAC leaders hope to send the message that Democrats can’t take anything for granted, despite the Free State’s reputation. Even though Democrats hold a 7-1 edge in the congressional delegation and super majorities in the Maryland General Assembly, Republicans have won three of the last five gubernatorial elections, and the race to replace retiring Gov. Lawrence J. Hogan Jr. (R) could be highly competitive in 2022, depending on the political climate. Congressional boundaries in Maryland could also be significantly different.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Historically, I don’t think [Virginia] Democrats think about Maryland because we have our own problems,” Surovell conceded.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Potomac Rising has been established as a federal PAC and is considered a hybrid account – one of the accounts can accept unlimited contributions.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“That’s what gave us the flexibility to work between both jurisdictions,” McClintock said – noting that Virginia and Maryland have significantly different campaign finance rules.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Potomac Rising isn’t the only joint political effort between Democrats in the two states this fall. Last week, Jeffrey Z. Slavin, a vice chairman of the Maryland Democratic Party and mayor of Somerset, hosted a fundraiser for Virginia legislative candidates focusing on LGBTQ issues. Virginia Del. Danica Roem (D), the first transgender person to serve in a state legislature, was a featured speaker.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In mid-October, the Washington, D.C.-based lobbying firm Cornerstone Government Affairs, which has outposts in seven state capitals, including Annapolis, is hosting a fundraiser at its D.C. office for Virginia State Senate Minority Leader Dick Saslaw (D). Former Virginia Gov. Terry McAuliffe (D), U.S. House Majority Leader Steny H. Hoyer (D-Md.) and Maryland Senate President Thomas V. Mike Miller Jr. (D-Calvert) are scheduled to speak. Ticket prices start at $1,000.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Potomac Rising PAC doesn’t have that kind of financial firepower yet, but organizers are undaunted.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Our fundraising focus is to do as much as we can between now and the election and to never stop,” Kildee said.</span></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">jkurtz@marylandmatters.org  </span></i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pa.&#8217;s lack of progress a &#8216;600-pound gorilla that was ignored&#8217; at bay cleanup meeting, conservation group leader says</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2019/09/06/pa-s-lack-of-progress-was-a-600-pound-gorilla-that-was-ignored-at-bay-cleanup-meeting-conservation-group-leader-says/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Josh Kurtz]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>josh@joshkurtz.com (Josh Kurtz)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2019 04:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://s37751.p1438.sites.pressdns.com/?p=11268</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[OXON HILL, Md. — The Chesapeake Bay Foundation&#8217;s president blasted the silence surrounding Pennsylvania&#8217;s failure to live up to its commitments to cut pollution flowing into the Chesapeake Bay Thursday at a meeting of the Chesapeake Bay Executive Council. “There was a 600-pound gorilla in the room that was ignored until it was brought up [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="791" height="1024" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed-791x1024.png" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed-791x1024.png 791w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed-232x300.png 232w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed-768x994.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed-696x901.png 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed-325x420.png 325w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/chesapeake-watershed.png 871w" sizes="(max-width: 791px) 100vw, 791px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Chesapeake Bay watershed. (U.S. Department of Agriculture) </p><p>OXON HILL, Md. — The Chesapeake Bay Foundation&#8217;s president blasted the silence surrounding Pennsylvania&#8217;s failure to live up to its commitments to cut pollution flowing into the Chesapeake Bay Thursday at a meeting of the Chesapeake Bay Executive Council.</p>
<p>“There was a 600-pound gorilla in the room that was ignored until it was brought up by the media,” said William C. Baker, the foundation&#8217;s president. “I don’t call that leadership.”</p>
<p>The foundation says Maryland, Virginia and Pennsylvania account for 90 percent of the pollution in the bay and that Pennsylvania&#8217;s &#8220;lackluster efforts are threatening years of progress under the collaborative cleanup agreement established in 2010.&#8221;</p>
<p>Virginia Gov. Ralph S. Northam (D) was the only other state chief executive besides Maryland Gov. Larry Hogan, a Republican, to attend Thursday’s annual meeting in Oxon Hill of the council, which Hogan leads and consists of leaders from the six Chesapeake Bay watershed states and the District of Columbia.</p>
<p>Northam, who spoke, as he often does, about growing up on the Eastern Shore and considering the bay “literally my backyard,” touted an “environmental literacy” summit that his wife led earlier this year and said the state was seeing real progress with a higher grade of crab, more oysters and more subaquatic grasses.</p>
<p>Northam said he still worried about the state’s <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/2019/08/27/state-commission-passes-new-emergency-regulations-to-protect-striped-bass-numbers/" target="_blank">striped bass population</a> and that his administration had enacted <a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/blog-va/virginia-releases-final-roadmap-for-cleaning-up-chesapeake-bay-by-2025/" target="_blank">enhanced protections</a>.</p>
<p>“I’m proud that we have developed a bold and comprehensive roadmap for success,” he said.</p>
<p>Northam took gentle jabs at other bay states. Thanking Hogan for the crab cake lunch the officials ate before the formal meeting, he noted, “These crabs originate in the water of the Chesapeake Bay down in Virginia. [Hogan] says that when they get older and wiser, they move up to Maryland. I say they don’t think as clearly.”</p>
<p>Northam also pointed out that 22,000 Pennsylvanians purchased saltwater fishing licenses in Virginia last year, and that one in 12 tourists on the Virginia coast come from New York.</p>
<p>Northam expressed confidence that the EPA would closely scrutinize the states’ bay cleanup proposals and would “take action” if necessary. But Baker, of the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, expressed fears that the EPA was unprepared to force states –<a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/blog-va/for-chesapeake-bay-pennsylvania-remains-a-problem/" target="_blank"> especially Pennsylvania</a> – to meet their commitments.</p>
<p>“If we don’t get any action from EPA we’re going to have to evaluate our options,” he said.</p>
<p>Hogan sought to downplay any animus between his state and Pennsylvania over Chesapeake Bay cleanup efforts – a week after blistering the Keystone State <a href="https://www.marylandmatters.org/blog/hogan-rips-pa-on-chesapeake-bay-cleanup/" target="_blank">in a letter</a> to federal and commonwealth officials.</p>
<p>“I wouldn’t really describe it as a tiff,” Hogan said in response to a reporter’s question. “I think we’ve had very productive discussions today. I do think they’re doing everything they can. …They’re good neighbors.”</p>
<p>In his letter last week to Pennsylvania Gov. Tom Wolf (D) and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency Administrator Andrew Wheeler, Hogan complained bitterly that Pennsylvania was falling short of its requirements to reduce nitrogen in state waterways and had a $320 million funding gap to meet federally mandated cleanup goals.</p>
<p>The six states in the Chesapeake Bay watershed, along with the District of Columbia, submitted final bay cleanup plans to EPA in late August, outlining their commitments through 2025. Representatives from each of the jurisdictions summarized their proposals at Thursday’s meeting.</p>
<p>Asked by a reporter about Pennsylvania’s so-called Watershed Implementation Plan, Wheeler said EPA officials would need a couple of months to evaluate each jurisdiction’s goals and were prepared to follow up if they found deficiencies.</p>
<p>“I’m not going to prejudge those proposals,” he said.</p>
<p>But Baker expressed skepticism that the industry-friendly Trump administration EPA, which has scaled back numerous environmental regulations, was equipped to provide sufficient oversight of the states’ plans.</p>
<p>“How can they say that they’re going to get the job done when they don’t even express concern about an acknowledged $320 million shortfall?” he said.</p>
<p>Representatives boasted about the efforts each of their states are making to help clean up the Chesapeake Bay, and many lauded the sense of collaboration among the states. But each state has its own unique relationship with the bay – and residents of upstream states are sometimes unaware that they even have an impact on the bay’s health, blunting those states’ sense of urgency.</p>
<p>“If the water in the Chesapeake Bay were as good as the water quality when it leaves New York, the Chesapeake Bay would not be impaired,” said James Tierney, a deputy commissioner at the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
<p>Patrick McDonnell, secretary of the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection, said the commonwealth under Wolf was spending record amounts of money to clean up its waterways.</p>
<p>“The state of Pennsylvania is committed to implementing our plan and getting there by 2025,” he told his colleagues. “Pennsylvanians value the water resources that we have.”</p>
<p>But McDonnell suggested that waterway cleanup is designed to benefit Pennsylvania first and foremost. He said that effort would benefit from the first-ever Pennsylvania farm bill that passed recently, which includes agricultural conservation funding.</p>
<p>“We have a sense of ownership of the challenge of improving water conservation … but there’s an understanding that more needs to be done,” McDonnell said.</p>
<p>In a brief interview, McDonnell acknowledged that “other states have concerns” about Pennsylvania’s ability to fund its bay cleanup mandates. But, he added, “I know some of the other states have concerns about their own funding.”</p>
<p>But Hogan, who was re-elected to serve another year as head of the Chesapeake Bay Executive Council, expressed satisfaction with all the states’ progress.</p>
<p>“The goal of clean water is truly within our sights after three or four decades of collaboration,” he said.</p>
<p><em>jkurtz@marylandmatters.org</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
