<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>McKenna Horsley, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/mckenna-horsley/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/mckenna-horsley/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 09:20:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>McKenna Horsley, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/mckenna-horsley/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>U.S. appeals court agrees to block central part of new Title IX gender rules for schools</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/07/19/u-s-appeals-court-agrees-to-block-central-part-of-new-title-ix-gender-rules-for-schools/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[McKenna Horsley]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>MHorsley@kentuckylantern.com (McKenna Horsley)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 09:18:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Courts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[former President Donald Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[K-12 schools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President Joe Biden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[title ix]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39343</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A federal appellate court has upheld blocking central parts of new Title IX rules from the Biden administration and granted an expedited hearing in October. A three-judge panel of the 6th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals agreed Wednesday to block the rules from taking effect Aug. 1, shortly before most schools begin their academic year. The rules, [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="693" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/trans-rights.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/trans-rights.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/trans-rights-300x203.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/trans-rights-768x520.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Rebekah Bruesehoff, a transgender student athlete, speaks at a press conference on LGBTQI+ rights, at the U.S. Capitol on March 8, 2023 in Washington, D.C. Bruesehoff spoke out against a proposed national trans sports ban being considered by Republicans on the House Education and the Workforce Committee. (Photo by Kevin Dietsch/Getty Images)</p><p>A federal appellate court has upheld blocking central parts of new Title IX rules from the Biden administration and granted an expedited hearing in October.</p>
<p>A three-judge panel of the 6th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals <a href="https://www.ag.ky.gov/Press%20Release%20Attachments/DN%2041%20Order%20Denying%20Partial%20Stay.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">agreed Wednesday </a>to block the rules from taking effect Aug. 1, shortly before most schools begin their academic year. The rules, created by the U.S. Department of Education, were aimed at protecting students from discrimination based on gender identity and sexual orientation.</p>
<p>Chief Judge Jeffrey Sutton wrote in the majority opinion that all judges on the panel agreed the central parts of the rules should not take effect on Aug. 1.</p>
<p>“It is hard to see how all of the schools covered by Title IX could comply with this wide swath of new obligations if the Rule’s definition of sex discrimination remains enjoined,” Sutton said. “Harder still, we question how the schools could properly train their teachers on compliance in this unusual setting with so little time before the start of the new school year.”</p>
<p>Judge Andre Mathis wrote in a dissenting opinion that he would grant a partial stay, as requested by the Department of Education. “I am cognizant of Plaintiffs’ argument that the benefits of enacting the Rule’s unchallenged provisions are outweighed by the expense or confusion of phased implementation,” Mathis wrote. “But most of the expense is attributable to provisions that Plaintiffs neither directly challenge nor cite as a source of harm.”</p>
<p>The lawsuit was filed by Republican attorneys general in six states — Kentucky, Virginia, Indiana, Ohio, Tennessee and West Virginia.</p>
<p>Kentucky Attorney General Russell Coleman said in a statement that Title IX, which was established more than 50 years ago, “created equal opportunities for women and young girls in the classroom and on the field.” The Sixth Circuit ruling, he added, made it the first appellate court “to stop President Biden’s blatant assault on these fundamental protections.”</p>
<p>“This ruling is a victory for common sense itself, and it’s a major relief for Kentucky families,” Coleman said. “As Attorney General and as a Dad, we’ll keep up the fight for my girls and for women across Kentucky so they can continue to fulfill their potential for the next 50 years and beyond.”</p>
<p>In June, <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/2024/06/17/us-judge-in-kentucky-blocks-biden-title-ix-rules-says-sex-gender-identity-not-the-same-thing/" target="_blank">Chief Judge Danny Reeves</a> of the U.S. District Court in Eastern Kentucky sided with Coleman and the other five GOP attorneys general. The judge said the Department of Education “seeks to derail deeply rooted law” with its proposed Title IX rules.</p>
<p>“At bottom, the Department would turn Title IX on its head by redefining ‘sex’ to include ‘gender identity.’ But ‘sex’ and ‘gender identity’ do not mean the same thing,” Reeves wrote. “The Department’s interpretation conflicts with the plain language of Title IX and therefore exceeds its authority to promulgate regulations under that statute.”</p>
<p>Established in 1972, <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/tix_dis.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Title IX</a> was created to prevent “discrimination based on sex in education programs or activities that receive federal financial assistance,” according to the Department of Education.</p>
<p>The Biden administration introduced the rules to “build on the legacy of Title IX by clarifying that all our nation’s students can access schools that are safe, welcoming, and respect their rights,” U.S. Secretary of Education Miguel Cardona previously said in a statement. The rules also <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/2024/04/19/biden-administration-to-roll-back-the-betsy-devos-title-ix-rules/" target="_blank">would have rolled back Trump administration changes</a> that narrowly defined sexual harassment and directed schools to conduct live hearings, allowing those who were accused of sexual harassment or assault to cross-examine their accusers.</p>
<p>The Lantern has sought comment from the U.S. Department of Education on the latest ruling.</p>
<p><em>Editor&#8217;s note:</em> This story originally appeared in <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/2024/07/18/u-s-appeals-court-agrees-to-block-central-part-of-new-title-ix-gender-rules/" target="_blank">The Kentucky Lantern</a>, which, like The Virginia Mercury, is part of States Newsroom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>US judge in Kentucky blocks Biden Title IX rules, says &#8216;sex,&#8217; &#8216;gender identity&#8217; not the same thing</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/18/us-judge-in-kentucky-blocks-biden-title-ix-rules-says-sex-gender-identity-not-the-same-thing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[McKenna Horsley]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>MHorsley@kentuckylantern.com (McKenna Horsley)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 09:35:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attorney General Jason Miyares]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[title ix]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Department of Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Secretary of Education Miguel Cardona]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=38965</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A federal judge has blocked new Title IX rules, including those aimed at protecting LGBTQ+ students from discrimination in K-12 schools, and sided with Republican attorneys general in several states — including Virginia. Chief Judge Danny Reeves of the U.S. District Court in Eastern Kentucky on Monday issued a ruling siding with Virginia Attorney General [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/student-2048x1366-1-1024x683.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/student-2048x1366-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/student-2048x1366-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/student-2048x1366-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/student-2048x1366-1-1536x1025.jpeg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/student-2048x1366-1.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Biden administration introduced the rules to “build on the legacy of Title IX by clarifying that all our nation’s students can access schools that are safe, welcoming, and respect their rights,” said U.S. Education Secretary Miguel Cardona. (Getty Images)</p><p>A federal judge has blocked new Title IX rules, including those aimed at protecting LGBTQ+ students from discrimination in K-12 schools, and sided with Republican attorneys general in several states — including Virginia.</p>
<p>Chief Judge Danny Reeves of the U.S. District Court in Eastern Kentucky on Monday issued a ruling siding with Virginia Attorney General Jason Miyares and his counterparts in five other states. The ruling prevents the U.S. Department of Education from “implementing, enacting, enforcing, or taking any action to enforce the Final Rule, Nondiscrimination on the Basis of Sex in Education Programs or Activities Receiving Federal Financial Assistance,” which was set to begin Aug. 1.</p>
<p>Miyares and the GOP attorneys general <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/briefs/kentucky-attorney-general-leading-gop-effort-against-new-title-ix-rules-over-gender/" target="_blank">filed the lawsuit</a> in April. At the time, they argued the Department of Education “used rulemaking power to convert a law designed to equalize opportunities for both sexes into a far broader regime of its own making” with the new Title IX regulations.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="mZiEvUHrra"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/03/virginia-attorney-general-joins-efforts-to-fight-back-against-title-ix-changes/">Virginia attorney general joins efforts to fight back against Title IX changes</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia attorney general joins efforts to fight back against Title IX changes&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/03/virginia-attorney-general-joins-efforts-to-fight-back-against-title-ix-changes/embed/#?secret=8113gYWk5C#?secret=mZiEvUHrra" data-secret="mZiEvUHrra" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Reeves limited the injunction to the plaintiff-states of Tennessee, Kentucky, Ohio, Indiana, Virginia and West Virginia.</p>
<p>Miyares <a href="https://x.com/JasonMiyaresVA/status/1802708125746659838" target="_blank">posted on X</a> soon after the ruling that he was &#8220;pleased to announce that a court has stopped the Biden Administration&#8217;s unlawful Title IX regulations from going into effect in Virginia,&#8221; calling the regulation a &#8220;power grab&#8221; by the president that would &#8220;jeopardize half a century of landmark protections for women, violate the First Amendment, and ignore the clear text of the Title IX law passed by Congress. The rule should have never been issued in the first place.&#8221;</p>
<p>The Biden administration introduced the rules to “build on the legacy of Title IX by clarifying that all our nation’s students can access schools that are safe, welcoming, and respect their rights,” U.S. Secretary of Education Miguel Cardona said in a statement. The rules also would have rolled back Trump administration changes that <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/2024/04/19/biden-administration-to-roll-back-the-betsy-devos-title-ix-rules/" target="_blank">narrowly defined sexual harassment </a>and directed schools to conduct live hearings, allowing those who were accused of sexual harassment or assault to cross-examine their accusers.</p>
<figure id="attachment_18881" class="wp-caption alignright"><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-18881" src="https://kentuckylantern.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Cardona-300x200.jpeg" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" srcset="https://kentuckylantern.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Cardona-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://kentuckylantern.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Cardona.jpeg 594w" alt="" width="400" height="267" /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i> U.S. Secretary of Education Miguel Cardona (Photo by Joshua Roberts/Getty Images) </figcaption></figure>
<p>In their complaint, the state attorneys general said that under the Biden rule, “Men who identify as women will, among other things, have the right to compete within programs and activities that Congress made available to women so they can fairly and fully pursue academic and athletic excellence — turning Title IX’s protections on their head. … And anyone who expresses disagreement with this new status quo risks Title IX discipline for prohibited harassment.”</p>
<p>Established in 1972, <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/tix_dis.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Title IX </a>was created to prevent “discrimination based on sex in education programs or activities that receive federal financial assistance,” according to the Department of Education.</p>
<p>Reeves wrote in his opinion that “the Department of Education seeks to derail deeply rooted law” created by the implementation of Title IX.</p>
<p>“At bottom, the Department would turn Title IX on its head by redefining ‘sex’ to include ‘gender identity.’ But ‘sex’ and ‘gender identity’ do not mean the same thing,” he wrote. “The Department’s interpretation conflicts with the plain language of Title IX and therefore exceeds its authority to promulgate regulations under that statute.”</p>
<p><em>This story originally appeared in the <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/2024/06/17/us-judge-in-kentucky-blocks-biden-title-ix-rules-says-sex-gender-identity-not-the-same-thing/" target="_blank">Kentucky Lantern</a> and has been adapted for Virginia. The Lantern, like the Virginia Mercury, is a part of States Newsroom. </em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
