<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>natural gas Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/place/natural-gas/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/place/natural-gas/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 10:33:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>natural gas Archives &#8226; Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/place/natural-gas/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Natural gas projects accelerate as Virginia’s energy needs soar</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/23/natural-gas-projects-accelerate-as-virginias-energy-needs-soar/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Paullin]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 10:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41585</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Virginia’s booming data center industry is driving unprecedented energy demands, straining the state’s natural gas infrastructure and prompting calls for new pipelines. A Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC) report warns that expanding pipeline capacity may be necessary to meet the surge, bringing with it additional logistical and environmental challenges. Some efforts to expand [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/230727-MVP-BentMntn-6205-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/230727-MVP-BentMntn-6205-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/230727-MVP-BentMntn-6205-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/230727-MVP-BentMntn-6205-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/230727-MVP-BentMntn-6205-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/230727-MVP-BentMntn-6205-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Mountain Valley Pipeline's right of way, seen from Boones Mill on July 25, 2023. (Scott Yates for the Virginia Mercury)</p><p>Virginia’s booming data center industry is driving unprecedented energy demands, straining the state’s natural gas infrastructure and prompting calls for new pipelines. A Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC) report warns that expanding pipeline capacity may be necessary to meet the surge, bringing with it additional logistical and environmental challenges.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some efforts to expand pipeline capacity are already underway. In October, Williams Companies filed an </span><a href="https://elibrary.ferc.gov/eLibrary/filelist?accession_number=20241029-5076&amp;optimized=false" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">application </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">with the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission for its Southeast Supply Enhancement Project (SSEP), which would add about 55 miles of pipeline — mostly in Southwest Virginia — to the existing 10,000-mile Transco Pipeline stretching from Texas to New York.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This follows the company’s </span><a href="https://elibrary.ferc.gov/eLibrary/filelist?accession_number=20231116-3071" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">approval </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">last year for its Commonwealth Energy Connector Project in Southside, designed to link in Greensville County with the Columbia Gas Virginia Reliability Project. That initiative, now under </span><a href="https://www.whro.org/environment/2024-07-19/construction-begins-on-pipeline-expansion-in-hampton-roads#" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">construction</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, will deliver natural gas to the Hampton Roads region, addressing growing energy needs in that part of the state. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Southgate extension project, an effort to extend the Mountain Valley Pipeline from Pittsylvania County into North Carolina, began consultations with the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality this year for permit reviews.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In October, Balico, the Herndon-based developer previously associated with the canceled Atlantic Coast Pipeline, proposed a massive data center campus with 84 buildings and an on-site natural gas plant for power. However, strong community </span><a href="https://cardinalnews.org/2024/11/04/data-center-proposal-in-pittsylvania-withdrawn-for-now/" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">opposition</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> forced the company to scale back its plans.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mike Atchie, director of community and project outreach for Williams Companies, emphasized the importance of the  SSEP, which seeks to expand natural gas infrastructure across Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia, and Alabama.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“It ensures that infrastructure exists to support the rapid economic and population growth in the southeast,” Atchie said, adding that it also meets the region&#8217;s growing demand for stable and reliable energy to heat homes and power essential services.”.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The recent pipeline developments have drawn sharp criticism from environmental groups, who warn about the potential impact on waterways the projects may need to cross and the continued reliance on carbon-emitting fossil fuels. Scientists link these emissions to worsening climate change, including more frequent and intense storms. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Basically, we&#8217;re looking at two co-located projects,” said Jessica Sims, a field coordinator for Appalachian Voices. “You have two projects, co-located in Pennsylvania County, approximately [that] could be built at the same time.”</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">The Southeast Supply Enhancement Project</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Williams Company plans to add about 55 miles of pipeline in Virginia and North Carolina through a series of loops —  parallel pipes designed to increase carrying capacity along existing lines.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Virginia, the Eden Loop would include about 30.8 miles of 42 inch-diameter pipeline running from Pittsylvania County into Rockingham County, NC. The loop also includes two 33,000-horsepower electric-powered compressor stations, in addition to others in North Carolina.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=41587" rel="attachment wp-att-41587"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-41587" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/SSEP-project.jpg" alt="" width="1055" height="818" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/SSEP-project.jpg 1055w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/SSEP-project-300x233.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/SSEP-project-1024x794.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/SSEP-project-768x595.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1055px) 100vw, 1055px" /></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Williams has requested approval for the project by February 2026, with an in-service date set for Nov. 1, 2027. Among the gas recipients are the City of Danville and Southwest Virginia Gas, which would take 1,500 and 5,000 dekatherms, respectively.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Without new capacity, there is a risk of repeating past shortages and power outages,” Atchie said. “The expansion taps into established pipeline corridors to minimize environmental and landowner impacts and will be built and maintained using Williams’ industry-leading safety standards, including 24/7 monitoring and rigorous maintenance.”</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Southgate extension</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The SSEP pipeline is planned to follow a similar route  to the 31-mile Southgate Extension project, which Mountain Valley Pipeline announced last </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/01/02/mountain-valley-proposes-shrinking-southgate-extension/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">year</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> it would be reviving.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since then, the company has engaged with federal and state regulatory agencies, including the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ), to discuss the permits required for the project’s revised scope, spokesperson Shawn Day said.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But Sims of Appalachian Voices raised concerns during a State Water Control Board meeting last month about Virginia code provisions that allow the DEQ to waive the requirement for a Section 401 permit under the federal Clean Water Act if the pipeline is below 36 inches. </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_37341" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2560px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/12/26/the-feds-extended-the-deadline-for-the-southgate-pipeline-extension-heres-a-refresher/mountain-valley-pipeline-6/" rel="attachment wp-att-37341"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-37341" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="2560" height="1707" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/MVP_pipes_SPY-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  The Mountain Valley Pipeline right of way and some piping is visible beside Rt. 460 Sunday, July 16, 2023, in Elliston. (Scott P. Yates for the Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The revised plans reduced the Southgate pipeline from 75 to 31 miles, eliminating the need for a  controversial compressor station, but increased the pipeline diameter from 24 and 16 inches to 30 inches, still under the threshold allowing the DEQ to waive the need for a water permit.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The cumulative impacts from two major construction projects is one reason to give South gain more scrutiny than last time,” Sims told the board, pointing to its proximity to the SSEP project.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When asked by the Mercury if the DEQ would waive any permits for the Southgate Extension project, DEQ spokesman John Giese said the agency has not received formal plans. “Southgate/Equitrans has informed [the] DEQ of their intent to move forward on a project and has discussed their general layout and timing of design,” Giese said. “However, no formal plans or permit application(s) have been submitted to [the] DEQ for review.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The project is aiming to be operational by 2028, “to provide PSNC Energy and Duke Energy with an affordable, reliable and resilient natural gas supply to meet residential and business demand and generate electricity,” MVP Southgate spokesman Day said, adding the project &#8220;will secure all necessary permits and authorizations.”</span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Balico’s data center</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The JLARC report highlighted natural gas as the most viable option for onsite power generation, a necessity for many large-scale projects in Southwest Virginia.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Of the current technologies available, only natural gas appears viable for on-site generation, and it can be deployed only close to pipeline infrastructure that has sufficient capacity to serve generation needs,” the report stated.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_41586" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:1313px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=41586" rel="attachment wp-att-41586"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-41586" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Balico-data-center.jpg" alt="" width="1313" height="854" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Balico-data-center.jpg 1313w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Balico-data-center-300x195.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Balico-data-center-1024x666.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Balico-data-center-768x500.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1313px) 100vw, 1313px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  A engineering plan for the data center campus and onsite power generation source. (Courtesy of Pittsylvania County)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Pittsylvania County, Balico initially proposed a 2,300-acre data center campus with a 3,500-megawatt natural gas plant, but withdrew the plan after significant community pushback. In November, the company submitted a scaled down </span><a href="https://www.pittsylvaniacountyva.gov/home/showpublisheddocument/5911/638678889658570000" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">application</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for a project requiring “more than 760 acres” and </span><a href="https://www.pittsylvaniacountyva.gov/government/departments/upcoming-zoning-special-use-permit-applications/-folder-407" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">rezoning</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> land for “private electric power generation,” with a letter of intent from Mountain Valley Pipeline owner, EQT, “for the supply of a sufficient volume of natural gas to fuel the power plant proposed for the campus.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The proposal is expected to be reviewed next year. Nearby, the town of Hurt passed a </span><a href="https://www.chathamstartribune.com/news/local/article_df6b1e6c-b26d-11ef-9744-4f2fedf60454.html" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">resolution</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> supporting the project, agreeing to provide 2 million gallons of water per day through the construction of  a new water plant. Community opposition to the original proposal had largely centered on the water demands of the project.</span></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chesterfield community convenes &#8216;People’s Hearing&#8217; absent a county-held one</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/30/chesterfield-community-convenes-peoples-hearing-absent-a-county-held-one/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Paullin]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 18:30:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40604</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[CHESTERFIELD &#8211; About 150 Chesterfield County residents showed up Tuesday to again oppose Dominion Energy Virginia&#8217;s proposed gas plant that the utility says is needed to meet rising energy demand in the state. The Friends of the Chesterfield, a group formed to push back against the plant, held their own &#8220;People&#8217;s Hearing&#8221;  in lieu of [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_191301-1024x768.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_191301-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_191301-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_191301-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_191301-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_191301-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Maria Alvarado, a representative of the Central American Solidarity Association, or CASA, speaks at the Friends of Chesterfield People's Hearing Tuesday. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury)</p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">CHESTERFIELD &#8211; About 150 Chesterfield County residents showed up Tuesday to again oppose Dominion Energy Virginia&#8217;s proposed gas plant that the utility says is needed to meet rising energy demand in the state.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Friends of the Chesterfield, a group formed to push back against the plant, held their own &#8220;People&#8217;s Hearing&#8221;  in lieu of a public hearing they’ve requested but that the County Board of Supervisors hasn&#8217;t held.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Maria Alvarado, a representative of the Central American Solidarity Association, or CASA, a group advocating on behalf of Black, Latino, Afro-descendent, indigenous, and immigrant communities, called the planned plant “a ticking time bomb” threatening residents’ health. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Every breath we take is at risk. It is not just about today, it is about long term health and survival of our community,” Alvarado said in Spanish, a translator rendering her words in English to the crowd. </span></p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Sustained opposition  </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tuesday’s hearing was the latest pushback against the 1,000 megawatt natural gas plant that Dominion proposed in 2023. The utility has said the plant will provide power when solar and wind can&#8217;t amid increasing electricity demands from data center development, electrification of vehicles and Virginians’ everyday use.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Earlier this month, environmental and community groups, including the local Sunrise Movement, protested outside Dominion&#8217;s Thomas F. Farrell II building in downtown Richmond before dropping off a letter for Dominion Chair, President and CEO Bob Blue asking for alternative energy sources.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40605" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2560px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/30/chesterfield-community-convenes-peoples-hearing-absent-a-county-held-one/img_4530/" rel="attachment wp-att-40605"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-40605" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="2560" height="1707" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/IMG_4530-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Rallyers protest outside Dominion&#8217;s Thomas F. Farrell II building in downtown Richmond. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since the inception of initial plans to build the plant at the James River Industrial Park on Battery Brooke Parkway, community and environmental groups have lambasted the project, saying  it runs counter to the Virginia Clean Economy Act, a 2020 law that requires the state&#8217;s largest utilities to transition to zero-carbon emitting energy sources by mid-century, unless there is a concern over the ability to meet electricity needs. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After 15 state legislators issued a statement in </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/03/15/democratic-legislators-oppose-dominions-proposed-chesterfield-natural-gas-plant/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">opposition</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to the plant in May, four delegates attended the People’s Hearing Tuesday night, including Del. Rodney Willet, R-Henrico, Del. Rae Cousins, D-Richmond, Del. Mike Jones, D-Richmond, Del. Debra D. Gardner, D-Chesterfield. A staff member of Del. Dolores McQuinn, D-Richmond, was also present.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;We&#8217;ve heard tonight people would be directly affected by it and that&#8217;s just unacceptable,&#8221; said Willet alongside Cousins in an interview. &#8220;We passed the Clean Economy Act for a reason, to pursue those clean energy alternatives, and this is flying in the face of that.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The project is proposed to be built in  a community consisting largely of minority and low-income residents, according to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s environmental justice screening and mapping </span><a href="https://www.epa.gov/ejscreen" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">tool.</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;I am a resident of the city of Richmond, but I&#8217;m here, and I will be here to help that fight. At some point they will not get those permits,&#8221; said Richard Walker Tuesday, while referencing past court decisions that have overturned air permits for other controversial energy projects, including one for an Atlantic Coast Pipeline </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2020/01/07/federal-court-overturns-union-hill-compressor-station-permit/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">compressor station</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> in Buckingham County. &#8220;We went to the 4th Circuit Court of Appeals and that three judge panel told them, &#8216;You do not have sufficient evidence for us to agree to grant you this permit.’ That needs to happen here.&#8221;</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40607" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2560px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/20241029_192319/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-40607" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="2560" height="1920" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192319-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Attendees at the Friends of Chesterfield People&#8217;s Hearing Tuesday night. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The critics have asked the Chesterfield County Board of Supervisors to hold a public hearing to solicit community input for local approvals, a requirement for Dominion in order to receive its air permit from the Department of Environmental Quality and final certificate of public convenience and necessity from the State Corporation Commission. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But because a former coal plant site on Coxendale Road that is now the proposed location is already zoned for an electricity generation plant, Chesterfield officials have indicated to DEQ local requirements have been satisfied and no further public action is needed. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Attempts to reach Chesterfield County officials were unsuccessful, but Tuesday night, county Supervisor Jessica Schneider sent a statement to the Friends of Chesterfield, saying she was &#8220;sorry I am in the minority and could not convince my fellow supervisors to do the right thing and hold a public hearing.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;I continue to stand with you in opposition to the gas plant, because not only does it go against the Virginia Clean Economy Act, but more importantly, it poses severe health risks to the Black and Brown and economically disadvantaged communities that are nearby and have been subjected to over 60 years of coal pollution and air pollution from the coal plant,” Schneider’s statement read. “It is a clear case of environmental injustice.&#8221; </span></p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Dominion’s response</h4>

	
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In August, in response to community concern, the utility switched the location of the proposal to its former coal-fired Chesterfield Power Station where the existing infrastructure may be used to reduce construction costs. The utility signaled Tuesday that the planned plant will remain part of its future energy mix, which </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/16/dominion-pushes-for-renewables-more-natural-gas-in-latest-long-term-plan/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">includes</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> more solar, wind, battery storage and nuclear sources than its previous plan, though the percentage of zero-carbon sources has decreased from 95% to 80% of the plan.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;We are all-in on renewables, building the largest offshore wind project in the U.S. and operating the nation&#8217;s second-largest solar fleet,&#8221; said Jeremy Slayton, a Dominion spokesperson. &#8220;Renewables alone cannot reliably keep our customers&#8217; power on around the clock. The Chesterfield Energy Reliability Center will allow us to continue to transition to renewables without ever sacrificing reliability.&#8221; </span></p>
<figure id="attachment_40608" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:2560px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/20241029_192616/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-40608" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-scaled.jpg" alt="" width="2560" height="1920" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/20241029_192616-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  A map showing the impact of pollution from Dominion&#8217;s proposed natural gas plant. (Charlie Paullin/Virginia Mercury)</p></figure>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But a </span><a href="https://www.southernenvironment.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Report_DominionsProposedCERCFacilityAEC23Jul2024-2.pdf" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">report </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">from the Southern Environmental Law Center, created in partnership with </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Applied Economics Clinic and touted at Tuesday’s event</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">, suggests that clean energy could do the trick, instead.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;Not only would the 1,000 megawatt need be met with resources that do not add harmful air pollutants, these alternatives would cost less,” SELC staff attorney Rachel James told the crowd.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dominion previously said it expects DEQ to unveil a draft air permit by the end of the year. Critics of the plant say they&#8217;re preparing for Dominion to submit its application for a certificate of convenience and necessity to the State Corporation Commission early next year.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The project is still expected to come online in 2029, though an update to Dominion&#8217;s long term planning document, called the Integrated Resource Plan, or IRP, shows 944 megawatts of electricity from natural gas first being produced in 2030. That represents the first full year of service, Slayton said. </span></p>
<p><em>Editor&#8217;s note: This story was updated to correct a transcription error on the size of Dominion&#8217;s solar fleet, and to note that Del. Candi Mundon King did not attend the People&#8217;s Hearing as previously reported. </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dominion pushes for renewables, more natural gas in latest long-term plan</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/16/dominion-pushes-for-renewables-more-natural-gas-in-latest-long-term-plan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Paullin]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>cpaullin@virginiamercury.com (Charlie Paullin)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 18:04:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dominion Energy Virginia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[electric generation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electric grid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IRP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[renewable energy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40420</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Virginia’s largest utility, Dominion Energy, on Tuesday filed an update to its long-term electricity generation plan showing the majority of energy it expects to produce will come from renewable sources. Dominion’s revamped, non-binding Integrated Resource Plan (IRP) looks 15 years into the future to detail how power will be provided and calls for an “all-of-the-above” approach that [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/210609_dominion_energy-02.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Dominion Energy offices in Richmond, Va. (Parker Michels-Boyce/ For The Virginia Mercury)</p><p>Virginia’s largest utility, Dominion Energy, on Tuesday filed an <a class="c-link" href="https://www.dominionenergy.com/-/media/pdfs/global/company/IRP/2024-IRP-w_o-Appendices.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://www.dominionenergy.com/-/media/pdfs/global/company/IRP/2024-IRP-w_o-Appendices.pdf" data-sk="tooltip_parent">update</a> to its long-term electricity generation plan showing the majority of energy it expects to produce will come from renewable sources.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dominion’s revamped, non-binding Integrated Resource Plan (IRP) looks 15 years into the future to detail how power will be provided and calls for an “all-of-the-above” approach that includes more reliance on natural gas. The utility’s previous plan projection said about 95% of electricity generation would be pulled from </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/12/12/dominion-regulator-recommends-rejection-of-utilitys-long-term-plan/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">renewable</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> sources. Tuesday’s updated plan calls for  about 80% of generation to be spurred by renewables.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8220;We are experiencing the largest growth in power demand since the years following World War II,&#8221; said Ed Baine, president of Dominion Energy Virginia. &#8220;No single energy source, grid solution or energy efficiency program will reliably serve the growing needs of our customers.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although subject to change as technology and demands evolve, the IRP is a glimpse into Dominion’s generation project proposals, which are paid for by ratepayers. This year’s update is a fine-tune adjustment to the plan unveiled </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/05/03/dominion-projects-new-gas-plants-advanced-nuclear-will-be-needed-to-meet-soaring-demand/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">last </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">year, which is when the public learned that the utility was reviving plans for natural gas plants, one of which was </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/27/dominion-still-facing-opposition-to-natural-gas-plant-proposal-after-location-change/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">proposed </span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">in Chesterfield County to meet growing energy needs, heightened by Dominion’s concern over renewable energy’s ability to produce enough power.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="ueCn7uFQtW"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/27/dominion-still-facing-opposition-to-natural-gas-plant-proposal-after-location-change/">Dominion still facing opposition to natural gas plant proposal after location change</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Dominion still facing opposition to natural gas plant proposal after location change&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/27/dominion-still-facing-opposition-to-natural-gas-plant-proposal-after-location-change/embed/#?secret=wTwIxdp45n#?secret=ueCn7uFQtW" data-secret="ueCn7uFQtW" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Environmental and ratepayer groups decried last year’s plan and said it would contribute to the emission of greenhouse gasses that scientists say are exacerbating climate changes’ increasing storm intensity and frequencies. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Critics also said the utility’s IRP conflicted with the Virginia Clean Economy Act, which passed in 2020 with the goal of decarbonizing Dominion’s grid by 2045 by transitioning to renewable generation sources. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The law allows for a carbon-emitting, fossil fuel facility to remain online past 2045 if  grid reliability or the ability to provide enough power would be risked without it. Detractors countered by saying those risks are not a guaranteed reality and the plan would leave ratepayers on the hook for a polluting facility that will need to be shut down in years to come.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“Dominion’s latest energy plan blatantly disregards the financial well-being and health of Virginia families,” said Kate Asquith, deputy director of energy and operations at Clean Virginia, a group founded by millionaire Michael Bills to counter Dominion’s influence in the state legislature. “By continuing to invest in gas-burning facilities, Dominion is not just raising bills—it&#8217;s locking Virginians into a future of higher costs and greater pollution.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The IRP update this year considers four different plans based on different regulation requirements. The most realistic plan, which incorporates rules under the VCEA and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency could increase a current monthly bill of $142.77 to $214.24 by the end of 2039 for a typical residential customer using 1,000 kilowatts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Increased grid demand is the key driver of the updated forecast, with 5.5% annually now expected, compared to the 5.1% annual use projection Dominion relied on last year.  The new forecast also projects about 45 gigawatts of electricity that will be needed for use during the summer in 2039, an additional 6 gigawatts of power compared to what was expected last year. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The utility is also pushing to own more generation sources to avoid purchasing power during peak demand moments in the summer and winter when cooling and heating units are cranking and the electricity cost </span><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/07/costs-for-electricity-during-extreme-weather-rising-dominion-says-nothing-to-worry-about-yet/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">skyrockets</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Dominion’s plan also related an increased concern over the ability for solar, wind and battery storage sources to produce as much power as possible during cloudier, darker and colder months, known as an effective load carrying capability, or ELCC.</span></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="zQbPASQFXC"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/07/costs-for-electricity-during-extreme-weather-rising-dominion-says-nothing-to-worry-about-yet/">Costs for electricity during extreme weather rising; Dominion says nothing to worry about — yet</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Costs for electricity during extreme weather rising; Dominion says nothing to worry about — yet&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/07/costs-for-electricity-during-extreme-weather-rising-dominion-says-nothing-to-worry-about-yet/embed/#?secret=rlc78LwMyl#?secret=zQbPASQFXC" data-secret="zQbPASQFXC" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Data Center Coalition, a group advocating on behalf of the data center industry that is proliferating in Northern Virginia, has said they are committed to addressing the concern over renewables, even as fossil fuel generation sources that have been providing baseload power begin retiring under new state policies. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“The data center industry is leaning in as a collaborative partner with utilities, grid operators, policymakers, regulators, and other stakeholders at this transformative moment to advance and accelerate grid modernization and energy infrastructure to support Virginia&#8217;s — and the nation’s — economic growth and competitiveness,” said Josh Levi, president of the Data Center Coalition.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Almost 6 gigawatts, up from about 3 gigawatts, of new natural gas fired generation is included in the plan, the equivalent of five more of the 1 gigawatt plants Dominion has proposed in Chesterfield. Tuesday’s IRP didn’t suggest locations for new facilities beyond the use of brownfield sites, which are already-disturbed lands that require remediation.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The plan also explores adding combined cycle steam turbines to the generation mix, which could create electricity from the gas turbines to reduce emissions while also operating “more often to serve customers’ everyday loads.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nuclear is another part of the proposed generation plan, with the development of five small modular reactors slated to start in 2035. The update mentioned SMR development advancements as examples of the technology&#8217;s progression, including the design approval of NuScale Power, which was canceled amid ballooning costs, and the approval of </span><a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Wyoming-TerraPower-groundbreaking" target="_blank"><span style="font-weight: 400;">TerraPower’s</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> construction permit in May. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The renewable generation sources included in the plan include: about 3.4 gigawatts of offshore wind the utility is pursuing; about 12 gigawatts of solar; and 4.5 gigawatts of battery storage. Along with the IRP update, Dominion also filed an application for about 1 gigawatts worth of solar projects that the State Corporation Commission will review. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The updated IRP discussed  how energy efficiency can reduce Virginia’s energy needs by 314 megawatts in the summer in 2024 and 553 megawatts by 2029.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dominion is also considering blending hydrogen with natural gas to further reduce emissions, and is performing a company analysis of environmental justice communities in Virginia. So far, it found that 78% of the total geographical area and 89% of the population qualify as EJ communities under the Virginia Environmental Justice Act that passed in 2020.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">“With such a large proportion of the Commonwealth defined through the VEJA…as an EJ Community, avoidance is not possible,” the utility wrote.</span></p>
<p><i data-stringify-type="italic">Correction: </i>This story has been updated to clarify the amount of renewable energy sources in Dominion&#8217;s IRP filed Oct. 15, 2024.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
