<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Jane Norman, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/jane-norman/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/jane-norman/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 07:26:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Jane Norman, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/jane-norman/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>AP: Former President Donald Trump wins second term</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/06/dc/ap-former-president-donald-trump-wins-second-term/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jane Norman]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>jnorman@statesnewsroom.com (Jane Norman)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>afigueroa@statesnewsroom.com (Ariana Figueroa)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 14:37:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2024 presidential election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[former President Donald Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice President Kamala Harris]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia voters]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=dc_bureau&#038;p=40734</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — Former President Donald Trump on Wednesday morning was&#160;projected by The Associated Press to have captured enough votes in the Electoral College to win the presidency. The first-ever&#160;convicted felon elected to the Oval Office,&#160;Trump by 8 a.m. Eastern had won four of the vital seven swing states in which he and the Democratic nominee, [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/trumpnov5-1-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/trumpnov5-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/trumpnov5-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/trumpnov5-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/trumpnov5-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/trumpnov5-1-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The&nbsp;Republican presidential nominee, former U.S. President Donald Trump, reacts on stage with former first lady Melania Trump during an election night event at the Palm Beach Convention Center on Nov. 6, 2024 in West Palm Beach, Florida. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)</p><p dir="ltr">WASHINGTON — Former President Donald Trump on Wednesday morning was&nbsp;<a href="https://apnews.com/hub/election-2024" target="_blank">projected</a> by The Associated Press to have captured enough votes in the Electoral College to win the presidency.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The first-ever&nbsp;<a href="https://idahocapitalsun.com/2024/05/30/breaking-trump-found-guilty-on-34-felony-counts-in-ny-hush-money-trial/" target="_blank">convicted</a> felon elected to the Oval Office,&nbsp;Trump by 8 a.m. Eastern had won four of the vital seven swing states in which he and the Democratic nominee, Vice President Kamala Harris, spent most of their time campaigning through 2024.</p>
<p dir="ltr">North Carolina,<a href="https://georgiarecorder.com/2024/11/06/after-bitter-defeat-in-2020-trump-comes-back-to-win-georgia-in-2024/" target="_blank"> Georgia</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://penncapital-star.com/election-2024/donald-trump-projected-to-win-pennsylvanias-19-electoral-votes/" target="_blank">Pennsylvania</a> and Wisconsin all voted for Trump, giving him 277 Electoral College votes compared to 224 for Harris.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Still without a victor declared were Michigan, Nevada and Arizona. But even without them, Trump — who will be the nation’s 47th president as well as having been its 45th — had more than enough of the 270 votes required to win the Electoral College.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Trump still faces charges of election subversion related to his actions in connection with the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the U.S. Capitol.</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">GOP Senate</h4>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/struggle-control-congress-too-close-call-states-begin-adding-votes" target="_blank">Republicans also took control&nbsp;</a>of the U.S. Senate, guaranteeing Trump a relatively smooth path in confirming his appointments to the courts and the Cabinet in the coming months.</p>
<p dir="ltr">As of Wednesday morning, Republicans had nabbed 52 seats in the Senate and Democrats had 42, the AP said.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Montana Sen. Jon Tester, a longtime centrist Democrat viewed as his party’s most vulnerable senator in 2024,&nbsp;<a href="https://dailymontanan.com/2024/11/06/sheehy-leads-tester-in-early-montana-us-senate-results/" target="_blank">was ousted&nbsp;</a>by Republican Tim Sheehy in a high-profile race called by the AP on Wednesday morning.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Control of the U.S. House had not yet been called but Republicans were leading there on Wednesday morning, 198-180.</p>
<p dir="ltr">If they were to maintain control of the chamber, that would set up an extraordinary Republican trifecta in Washington that likely could expedite legislation including on taxes, the debt, reproductive rights and immigration.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Harris is expected to address the nation on Wednesday, her campaign co-chair, Cedric Richmond, told a crowd that had gathered Tuesday night for an election watch party at her alma mater, Howard University in Washington, D.C.</p>
<p dir="ltr">All results are unofficial until local election officials across the country&nbsp;<a href="https://www.eac.gov/election-officials/election-results-canvass-and-certification" target="_blank">verify and certify</a> the outcome in the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ncsl.org/elections-and-campaigns/election-certification-deadlines" target="_blank">coming days and weeks</a>.</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">Trump legal problems</h4>
<p dir="ltr">Trump’s long presidential campaign was punctuated by a busy legal schedule that included two federal cases, still&nbsp;<a href="https://missouriindependent.com/2024/10/03/special-counsel-jack-smith-reveals-new-evidence-against-trump-in-2020-election-case/" target="_blank">ongoing</a>, and cases in Georgia and New York. The former president was convicted in New York in May on 34 felony counts of falsifying business records related to hush money paid to a porn star ahead of the 2016 election. His sentencing is scheduled for Nov. 26.</p>
<p dir="ltr">His long appeal of the government’s 2020 election subversion charges against him eventually received a victory in the U.S. Supreme Court when the conservative majority ruled that former presidents enjoy criminal immunity for core constitutional duties, and presumed immunity for duties on the office’s outer perimeter, but none for personal actions.</p>
<p dir="ltr">After the election subversion case was returned to the lower court, U.S. special counsel Jack Smith presented new evidence to underscore that Trump schemed to overturn 2020 presidential results in a personal capacity, acting alongside his private lawyers. Trump has indicated numerous times that, if elected to another presidency, he would oust Smith.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Trump’s refusal to concede the 2020 presidential contest to President Joe Biden eventually culminated in his supporters’ violent attack on the U.S. Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Speaking to his supporters in West Palm Beach, Florida, earlier on Wednesday, alongside his running mate, Ohio Sen. J.D. Vance, Trump thanked “thousands of friends in this incredible movement like nobody’s ever seen before.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“Frankly, this was, I believe, the greatest political movement of all time. There’s never been anything like this in this country,” Trump said.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Trump promised to “heal” the country and that his second presidency “will truly be the golden age of America.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“We overcame obstacles that nobody thought possible,” Trump said.</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">A roller coaster race</h4>
<p dir="ltr">Trump had spent most of his reelection campaigning against President Joe Biden, who bowed out of the race in the summer after a disastrous debate performance.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That required the Trump team to pivot to a new campaign with a candidate Trump had never gone up against — Harris.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Harris, who touted herself as the underdog, tried to position herself as a new generation of leadership and through her policy plans on housing, health care and the economy, offering a new chapter for Americans.</p>
<p dir="ltr">She heavily ran on her support of reproductive rights and the threat to democracy that a second Trump presidency would bring, citing the immunity ruling from the Supreme Court.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In the end, Trump’s core campaign issues of immigration and criticisms of the economy appeared to have swayed voters, and she fell short of claiming any of the swing state votes that offered her a path toward victory.</p>
<p dir="ltr">As it became clear late Tuesday that she was falling behind in support in key states that carried Biden to the White House in 2020, thousands of her supporters who gathered at Howard University for a<a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/harris-watch-party-dc-hope-gives-way-anxiety" target="_blank"> watch party left in waves</a> as her chances for victory continued to narrow.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>Ashley Murray contributed to this report.</em></p>
<p dir="ltr"><em>This report will be updated.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Biden slams COVID-19 vaccine ‘lies,’ announces free at-home tests</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2021/12/21/biden-slams-covid-19-vaccine-lies-announces-free-at-home-tests/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jane Norman]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>jnorman@statesnewsroom.com (Jane Norman)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 01:35:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[COVID-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[booster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coronavirus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covid-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COVID-19 testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covid-19 vaccine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[omicron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trend – Vaccine Landscape]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=29893</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — President Joe Biden on Tuesday urged that COVID-19 vaccine doubters stop “peddling lies” on TV and online, as the nation grapples with a rising number of cases due to the highly transmissible omicron variant. Biden also announced new federal help for testing and treatment in the states, including 500 million at-home rapid test [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="799" height="533" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden_booster.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden_booster.jpg 799w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden_booster-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/biden_booster-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 799px) 100vw, 799px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">President Joe Biden receives a COVID-19 booster shot in the South Court Auditorium of the Eisenhower Executive office Building, Monday, September 27, 2021, at the White House. (Official White House Photo by Cameron Smith)</p><p>WASHINGTON — President Joe Biden on Tuesday urged that COVID-19 vaccine doubters stop “peddling lies” on TV and online, as the nation grapples with a rising number of cases due to the highly transmissible omicron variant.</p>
<p>Biden also announced new federal help for testing and treatment in the states, including 500 million at-home rapid test kits that will be distributed for free by the federal government beginning in January.</p>
<p>“Look, the unvaccinated are responsible for their own choices,” the president said in an afternoon address from the White House. “But those choices have been fueled by dangerous misinformation on cable TV and social media.</p>
<p>“You know, these companies and personalities are making money by peddling lies and allowing misinformation that can kill their own customers and their own supporters,” he said. “It’s wrong. It’s immoral. I call on the purveyors of these lies and misinformation to stop it. Stop it now.”</p>
<p>Biden stressed that Americans must get their vaccinations and booster shots as the best protection against contracting COVID-19. “Those who are not vaccinated are causing hospitals to be overrun again,” he said. “Omicron is serious, potentially deadly business for unvaccinated people.”</p>
<p>The new surge is causing many Americans to wonder if they can safely celebrate the holidays with family and friends, he acknowledged. “The answer’s yes, you can, if you and those who celebrate with you are vaccinated, particularly if you’ve gotten your booster shot,” he said.</p>
<p>He said more than 60 million Americans, including 62 percent of eligible seniors, have received boosters — including former President Donald Trump. “Maybe one of the few things he and I agree on,” said Biden.</p>
<p>The new surge “absolutely” will not resemble the initial wave of COVID-19 that hit the U.S. in March 2020, Biden insisted. More than 200 million Americans now are fully vaccinated, and the nation is more prepared, he said.</p>
<p>The White House announced <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2021/12/21/fact-sheet-president-biden-announces-new-actions-to-protect-americans-and-help-communities-and-hospitals-battle-omicron/" target="_blank">multiple steps that the U.S. will take </a>this winter as omicron emerges as the dominant variant, responsible for more than 73 percent of new COVID-19 cases, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
<p>It’s been difficult in many regions to obtain appointments or kits for COVID-19 tests, and administration officials said that Americans soon will be able to order free at-home kits from a website to be set up by the federal government.</p>
<p>The kits, which officials said will be delivered by mail, will be in addition to 50 million test kits already bought by the federal government for free distribution at community health and rural health centers, officials said.</p>
<p>White House press secretary Jen Psaki said details are still being worked out, such as the number of kits each individual can order and whether certain groups will be prioritized.</p>
<p>“Five hundred million tests in January is the largest order we’ve ever made to date, and we’re going to do it as quickly as we can,” she said.</p>
<p>Psaki earlier this year had <a href="https://theintercept.com/2021/12/07/jen-psaki-cant-explain-americans-dont-get-free-home-covid-tests/" target="_blank">rejected a suggestion</a> by a reporter that tests be sent to every home free of charge, questioning the cost. At retail, the kits generally cost at least $25 for a pack of two tests and often more.</p>
<p>She said with Tuesday’s move, “We are providing an opportunity, another opportunity or ability for people to…go on a website and request a test if their preference is to get their test to their home. Not everybody will want to do that.”</p>
<p>New federal free testing sites will be set up, the first in hard-hit New York City, in addition to thousands of sites that already are up and running, Psaki said. She said states are coordinating with the federal government as to where new sites should be located.</p>
<p>Biden said he will also direct the secretary of defense to mobilize an additional 1,000 troops such as medical doctors and nurses to work at hospitals through January and February as needed.</p>
<p>Six emergency response teams made up of federal clinical staff and paramedics will deploy to Michigan, Indiana, Wisconsin, Arizona, New Hampshire and Vermont, the White House said.</p>
<p>To assist hospitals with the expected surge in cases, Biden directed the Federal Emergency Management Agency to mobilize planning teams to work with every state to assess hospital needs and begin expanding bed capacity, “with the federal government paying for all of it,” according to a White House fact sheet. Millions of gowns, gloves, hospital gowns, masks and ventilators are stockpiled, too, Biden said.</p>
<p>FEMA also is ready to send out ambulances and emergency teams to transfer patients from overburdened medical facilities, the administration said. “Just this week, 30 paramedics are heading to New Hampshire, 30 to Vermont, and 20 to Arizona, and 30 ambulances are headed to New York and 8 to Maine,” according to the fact sheet.</p>
<p>On the vaccination front, the White House said that FEMA will establish new pop-up vaccination clinics across the country, including four new mobile units across New Mexico expected to open Thursday. More sites are expected in the coming weeks.</p>
<p>Biden in his remarks sought to calm anxiety provoked by the new round of business, school, college and entertainment closures.</p>
<p>“I know you’re tired…and I know you’re frustrated,” Biden said. “We all want this to be over. But we’re still in it. This is a critical moment. But we also have more tools than we’ve ever had before. We’re ready. We’ll get through this.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Vaccine mandate for health care workers halted nationwide by Louisiana judge</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2021/11/30/vaccine-mandate-for-health-care-workers-halted-nationwide-by-louisiana-judge/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jane Norman]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>jnorman@statesnewsroom.com (Jane Norman)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>laura@olson.com (Laura Olson)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 23:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[COVID-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biden adminstration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covid-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covid-19 vaccine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vaccine mandate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=29613</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON—A federal judge in Louisiana on Tuesday issued a ruling blocking nationwide the Biden administration mandate requiring millions of health care workers be vaccinated against COVID-19. A suit challenging the mandate was led on behalf of multiple states by Louisiana Attorney General Jeff Landry, a Republican, and U.S. Judge Terry Doughty granted the states’ request [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/210202_vm_covid_vaccine_0081.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Nurse Patti Kaloski gives Kathy Hennigan her first dose of the Moderna COVID-19 vaccine during Senior Weekend at Richmond Raceway in Richmond, Va., February 2, 2021. I didnt feel a thing, said Hennigan of the injection. (Parker Michels-Boyce/ For the Virginia Mercury)</p><p>WASHINGTON—A federal judge in Louisiana on Tuesday issued a ruling blocking nationwide the Biden administration mandate requiring millions of health care workers be vaccinated against COVID-19.</p>
<p>A suit challenging the mandate was led on behalf of multiple states by Louisiana Attorney General Jeff Landry, a Republican, and U.S. Judge Terry Doughty granted the states’ request for a preliminary injunction.</p>
<p>Doughty said in his opinion that he extended the injunction beyond those states and to the entire U.S. because “there are unvaccinated health care workers in other states who also need protection.”</p>
<p>States joining Louisiana in its suit, filed Nov. 15, included Montana, Arizona, Alabama, Georgia, Idaho, Indiana, Mississippi, Ohio, Oklahoma, South Carolina, Utah and West Virginia.</p>
<p>Doughty, an appointee of former President Donald Trump, said that “this court believes the balance of equities and the public interest favors the issuance of a preliminary injunction.&#8221;</p>
<p>“The public interest is served by maintaining the constitutional structure and maintaining the liberty of individuals who do not want to take the COVID-19 vaccine,” he wrote. “This interest outweighs Government Defendants’ interests. “</p>
<p>At issue is President Joe Biden’s <a href="https://lailluminator.com/2021/11/04/federal-vaccine-rule-for-private-businesses-to-kick-in-on-jan-4/" target="_blank">campaign to ensure that workers throughout the country are vaccinated against COVID-19</a>.</p>
<figure id="attachment_24640" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="max-width:100%;width:768px;"><a href="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-gets-jabbed-GettyImages-1295840599-768x512-1.jpg" target="_blank"><img decoding="async" class="size-full wp-image-24640" src="https://www.virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-gets-jabbed-GettyImages-1295840599-768x512-1.jpg" alt="" width="768" height="512" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-gets-jabbed-GettyImages-1295840599-768x512-1.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-gets-jabbed-GettyImages-1295840599-768x512-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-gets-jabbed-GettyImages-1295840599-768x512-1-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/biden-gets-jabbed-GettyImages-1295840599-768x512-1-630x420.jpg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  President-elect Joe Biden receives the second dose of the Pfizer/BioNTech COVID-19 vaccination on Jan. 11 in Newark, Del. (Photo by Alex Wong/Getty Images)</p></figure>
<p>Under Biden’s order, many private-sector employees were required to get vaccinated or undergo weekly tests, while some 17 million health care providers at facilities participating in the federal Medicare and Medicaid health insurance programs must be vaccinated — with no option to choose weekly testing instead.</p>
<p>Under the requirement, health care workers were to be fully vaccinated by Jan. 4, 2022.</p>
<p>Becker’s Hospital Review <a href="https://www.beckershospitalreview.com/workforce/30-of-healthcare-workers-remain-unvaccinated-cdc-study-finds.html" target="_blank">reported earlier this month</a> that a federal study found 30 percent of health care workers in 2,000 hospitals across the U.S. remained  unvaccinated as of Sept. 15.</p>
<p>“I applaud Judge Doughty for recognizing that Louisiana is likely to succeed on the merits and for delivering yet another victory for the medical freedom of Americans,&#8221; Landry said in a statement. “While Joe Biden villainizes our health care heroes with his ‘jab or job’ edicts, I will continue to stand up to the president&#8217;s bully tactics and fight for liberty.”</p>
<p>The Louisiana ruling followed <a href="https://iowacapitaldispatch.com/2021/11/29/federal-vaccine-mandate-for-health-care-workers-in-10-states-blocked-by-judge/" target="_blank">another on Monday</a> by a federal judge in Missouri that blocked enforcement of the Biden administration’s vaccine mandate for millions  in 10 states.</p>
<p>That ruling by U.S. District Judge Matthew Schelp, another Trump appointee, affected the states involved in that lawsuit: Missouri, Iowa, Kansas, New Hampshire, North Dakota, South Dakota, Nebraska, Arkansas, Wyoming and Alaska.</p>
<p>White House press secretary Jen Psaki told reporters Monday that the administration is “obviously going to abide by the law and fight any efforts in courts or otherwise” to prevent health care facilities from protecting their work forces.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Here’s what Biden plans to do on his first day as president</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2021/01/20/heres-what-biden-plans-to-do-on-his-first-day-as-president/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jane Norman]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>jnorman@statesnewsroom.com (Jane Norman)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 15:59:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://s37751.p1438.sites.pressdns.com/?p=24767</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — Joe Biden early Wednesday unveiled the list of executive orders, memos and directives he will make when he assumes the presidency later in the day, reversing a slew of Trump administration actions and laying out new policies of his own. “These actions are bold, begin the work of following through on President-elect Biden’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-2048x1366.jpg 2048w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-1068x712.jpg 1068w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/BIDEN_MASK_GETTY-1920x1280.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">President-elect Joe Biden arrives at General Mitchell International Airport with wife Jill September 03, 2020 in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. Biden was traveling to Wisconsin to visit the family of Jacob Blake, whose shooting by police sparked protests within the Kenosha community.   (Photo by Alex Wong/Getty Images)</p><header class="entry-header"></header>
<div class="entry-content">
<div id="modal-ready">
<p>WASHINGTON — Joe Biden early Wednesday unveiled the list of executive orders, memos and directives he will make when he assumes the presidency later in the day, reversing a slew of Trump administration actions and laying out new policies of his own.</p>
<p>“These actions are bold, begin the work of following through on President-elect Biden’s promises to the American people, and, importantly, fall within the constitutional role for the president,” the transition team said in a statement.</p>
<p>According to the transition team, Biden and Vice President-elect Kamala Harris will:</p>
<p>• Ask the American people to mask up for 100 days in a “100 days masking challenge” to prevent the spread of COVID-19. They will require masks and social distancing in all federal buildings and on all federal lands.</p>
<p>• Create the position of a COVID-19 response coordinator, reporting directly to the president.</p>
<p>• Cease the process of withdrawing from the World Health Organization, which has been coordinating the global response to COVID-19, and begin taking part in WHO meetings and other actions.</p>
<p>• Ask the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to extend the federal eviction moratorium until at least March 31 and call on Congress to provide more rental assistance. They will ask the Department of Veterans Affairs, Department of Agriculture, and the Department of Housing and Urban Development, to “consider extending foreclosure moratoriums for federally guaranteed mortgages and continuing applications for forbearance for federally guaranteed mortgages until at least March 31.”</p>
<p>• Ask the Department of Education to extend the pause on interest and principal payments for federal direct student loans until at least Sept. 30.</p>
<p>• Sign the document to rejoin the Paris Agreement on Climate Change and deposit it with the United Nations on Wednesday.</p>
<p>• Direct federal agencies to review actions taken during the Trump administration that were harmful to public health, damaging to the environment and not in the public interest.</p>
<p>• Direct agencies to consider revising vehicle fuel economy and emissions standards.</p>
<p>• Direct the Department of Interior to review the boundaries and conditions of the Grand Staircase-Escalante, Bears Ears, Northeast Canyons, and Seamounts Marine National Monuments and placing a temporary moratorium on all oil and natural gas leasing activities in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge.</p>
<p>• Revoke the presidential permit for the Keystone XL pipeline.</p>
<p>• Embed the concept of equity across the government by defining it as the “consistent and systematic fair, just and impartial treatment of all individuals, including individuals who belong to underserved communities, such as Black, Latino, Indigenous and Native American persons, Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders, and other persons of color; LGBTQ+ persons; people with disabilities; religious minorities, persons who live in rural areas; and persons otherwise affected by persistent poverty or inequality.”</p>
<p>• Direct federal agencies to review the state of equity in their departments and deliver action plans; launch a new data working group to make sure that federal data reflects American diversity; task the budget office with working for more equitable allocation of federal resources; and more.</p>
<p>• Reverse Trump administration orders that excluded undocumented immigrants from census counts.</p>
<p>• Sign a presidential memo supporting the Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals program and call on Congress to take action to pass laws for permanent status for Dreamers.</p>
<p>• End the restriction on entry into the United States of people from primarily Muslim and African nations.</p>
<p>• Stop construction of the border wall by terminating a national emergency declaration that was used by President Donald Trump to continue its funding.</p>
<p>• Sign an order aimed at prohibiting workplace discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity.</p>
<p>• Order every appointee in the executive branch to sign an ethics pledge.</p>
<p>• Issue an order that pauses any new Trump regulations from moving forward so they can be reviewed.</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Our home was attacked Wednesday. It may never be the same.</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2021/01/07/our-home-was-attacked-wednesday-it-may-never-be-the-same/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jane Norman]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>jnorman@statesnewsroom.com (Jane Norman)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 21:14:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Commentary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://s37751.p1438.sites.pressdns.com/?p=24344</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON—Many of us in our working lives have places away from the office that feel like a second home. It could be a back room at a business, a warehouse, a barn, even the front seat of a car. For me, that place for years was the U.S. Capitol. Thousands of people’s lives are tied [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="725" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265-300x212.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265-768x544.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265-100x70.jpg 100w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265-696x493.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-1294931265-593x420.jpg 593w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Capitol police officers point their guns at a door that was vandalized in the House Chamber during a joint session of Congress on January 06, 2021 in Washington, DC. when Trump supporters breached the building. Congress held a joint session today to ratify President-elect Joe Biden's 306-232 Electoral College win over President Donald Trump. A group of Republican senators said they would reject the Electoral College votes of several states unless Congress appointed a commission to audit the election results. (Photo by Drew Angerer/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON—Many of us in our working lives have places away from the office that feel like a second home. It could be a back room at a business, a warehouse, a barn, even the front seat of a car.</p>
<p>For me, that place for years was the U.S. Capitol. Thousands of people’s lives are tied to that creaky old building full of history — but also serving workers’ routine needs with coffee shops, a post office, vending machines, take-outs and cramped work spaces. I worked as a reporter for more than two decades covering Congress, first for The Des Moines Register and later for Congressional Quarterly, where I once spent nearly 24 hours straight there while covering the marathon passage of the health care law. The Capitol became not just a building but a community.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, that second home was attacked, vandalized and defiled by a rioting pro-Trump mob.</p>
<p>The Capitol Police in charge of guarding the Capitol complex were overwhelmed and, judging from videos, possibly even complicit to some extent in allowing the mayhem. Many people are already questioning if the same would have happened had it been Black Lives Matter protesters at the gates.</p>
<p>Some officers tried to do their job, against the odds. It hurt my heart to see a video of a single Black policeman trying to push back an oncoming swarm of White insurrectionists as they flooded up the Senate steps. Where was his backup? Why was he alone there?</p>
<p>Former colleagues and friends who have spent their lives at the Capitol shared horrified texts throughout the afternoon as the rioters engaged in an armed standoff at the door of the House chambers and frolicked on the floor of the Senate. One triumphantly put up his feet <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/06/us/politics/richard-barnett-pelosi.html" target="_blank">on House Speaker Nancy Pelosi’s desk</a>. Others destroyed furniture and broke windows. A woman was even <a href="https://iowacapitaldispatch.com/briefs/woman-shot-during-u-s-capitol-violence-dies/" target="_blank">shot during the melee</a> and died later at a local hospital. Three others died in what has been described as medical emergencies.</p>
<p>If you know the Capitol, these scenes were even more incredible. “Astonishing and shameful,” one reporter friend texted. Another was reminded of the warnings of relatives who survived the Holocaust.</p>
<p>Members of the press have a lot of freedom in the Capitol but it’s not unlimited. The police routinely badger reporters to display their  credentials and order us to move along if we linger too long in front of the Senate chamber. Bags are searched and examined at entrances, where often there are four or five officers. I once was scolded at length for sitting down my heavy backpack on the floor while I joined a scrum of other reporters in questioning a senator. The bag looked too suspicious.</p>
<p>Yet on Wednesday, hundreds of rioters broke into the Capitol, many of them wearing big backpacks with who knows what inside. “Murder the media” they scrawled on a door to one of the entrances. Perhaps that was part of their intent and if so, it was thwarted. Reporters huddling under chairs in the press galleries or fleeing through the tunnels emerged unharmed.</p>
<p>Our States Newsroom Washington bureau reporters were working remotely on Wednesday, for which I am grateful.  As an editor in Washington in the post 9/11 era, one of your greatest fears is the safety of your staff as they produce the news. The day of those terrorist attacks occupies a place in my memory that is almost too painful to revisit—and now rivals Wednesday’s attack by my own countrymen and women.</p>
<p>Today the hindsight and recriminations will begin, and they should. I don’t know if this was a massive fail by the Capitol Police or something avoidable. Budget cuts and COVID-19 staff shortages may have contributed. Perhaps the spectacle of a president encouraging his supporters to invade the Capitol simply was beyond the ken of people who plan security. It should not have been, since he gave ample warning.</p>
<p>The windows will be repaired, the debris collected, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2021/01/07/us/capitol-building-trump?smtyp=cur&amp;smid=tw-nytimes#at-least-56-police-officers-were-hurt-during-the-chaos-at-the-capitol-the-dc-police-chief-says" target="_blank">the blood wiped</a> off the statues. Congress defiantly came back late Wednesday night to continue certification of Joe Biden’s election as president, signaling that a constitutional process will not be stopped by marauders.</p>
<p>But I fear something has changed or shifted permanently, when some Americans will attack and try to destroy the very home of democracy they profess to love.</p>
<p>And you know what? I am a member of the press, and an American, and it’s my home, too.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trump in ‘good spirits’ after testing positive for COVID-19; Biden tests negative</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/briefs/trump-in-good-spirits-after-testing-positive-for-covid-19/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jane Norman]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>laura@olson.com (Laura Olson)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>afigueroa@statesnewsroom.com (Ariana Figueroa)</dc:contributor>
<dc:contributor>jnorman@statesnewsroom.com (Jane Norman)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 15:41:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[COVID-19]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://s37751.p1438.sites.pressdns.com/?post_type=blog-va&#038;p=22054</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON—President Donald Trump tweeted early Friday that he and first lady Melania Trump have tested positive for COVID-19, throwing the presidential campaign into a new uproar. “We will begin our quarantine and recovery process immediately. We will get through this TOGETHER!” Trump tweeted. White House chief of staff Mark Meadows told reporters Friday morning that the [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="799" height="533" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/trump_TRACTOR.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/trump_TRACTOR.jpg 799w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/trump_TRACTOR-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/trump_TRACTOR-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/trump_TRACTOR-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/trump_TRACTOR-630x420.jpg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 799px) 100vw, 799px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">President Donald J. Trump gestures to the crowd prior to delivering remarks in support of the Farmers to Families Food Box distribution program Monday, Aug. 24, 2020, at Flavor First Growers and Packers in Mills River, N.C. (Official White House Photo by Shealah Craighead)

</p><p>WASHINGTON—President Donald Trump tweeted early Friday that he and first lady Melania Trump have tested positive for COVID-19, throwing the presidential campaign into a new uproar.</p>
<p>“We will begin our quarantine and recovery process immediately. We will get through this TOGETHER!” Trump <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1311892190680014849" target="_blank">tweeted.</a></p>
<p>White House chief of staff Mark Meadows told reporters Friday morning that the president is experiencing mild symptoms, but is in “good spirits” and “very energetic.”</p>
<p>“We have a president who not only is on the job, will remain on the job,” said Meadows, who spoke without a mask, saying he tested negative. “I’m optimistic that he’ll have a very quick and speedy recovery.”</p>
<p>Late Thursday, Bloomberg News <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-10-02/trump-aide-hope-hicks-tests-positive-for-coronavirus-infection" target="_blank">had reported</a> that Hope Hicks, a close aide to Trump, had tested positive for the virus. Hicks had traveled to and from the presidential debate in Cleveland on Air Force One with Trump and also traveled to Minnesota with him, Bloomberg said.</p>
<p>Trump has repeatedly questioned the efficacy of wearing a face mask and other safety precautions, contradicting top health officials in his administration, and is rarely seen wearing one as he presides over large rallies packed with maskless attendees.</p>
<p>At Tuesday’s debate, Trump said he wears one when he “needs to,” and derided Biden for routinely wearing a face covering. He has insisted that his approach is fine because those close to him are tested every day.</p>
<p>Democratic presidential nominee Joe Biden, who shared the debate stage with Trump on Tuesday, posted on Twitter Friday that he and his wife, Jill, tested negative for the virus. “Thank you to everyone for your messages of concern,” he said. “I hope this serves as a reminder: wear a mask, keep social distance and wash your hands.”</p>
<p>In addition, Dr. Kevin O’Connor, the Bidens’ physician, issued a statement through the campaign. “Vice President Joe Biden and Dr. Jill Biden underwent PCR testing for COVID-19 today and COVID-19 was not detected,” he said.</p>
<p>Earlier Biden wished the president and first lady a swift recovery.</p>
<p>Vice President Mike Pence’s press secretary<a href="https://twitter.com/VPPressSec/status/1311997475226636291" target="_blank"> tweeted</a> that Pence and his wife, Karen, tested negative for the virus on Friday morning.</p>
<p>Sen. Mike Lee, a Utah Republican, <a href="https://twitter.com/SenMikeLee/status/1312055257992753152/photo/1" target="_blank">tweeted</a> Friday that he, too, has tested positive for COVID-19. Lee had met on Tuesday with Supreme Court nominee Amy Coney Barrett and posted a <a href="https://twitter.com/SenMikeLee/status/1311064032300929038" target="_blank">photo on Twitter</a> showing that meeting, in which neither of them were wearing masks.</p>
<p>Democratic presidential nominee Joe Biden, who shared a debate stage with Trump on Tuesday, posted on Twitter Friday morning, wishing the president a swift recovery.</p>
<p>“Jill and I send our thoughts to President Trump and First Lady Melania Trump for a swift recovery,” Biden tweeted. “We will continue to pray for the health and safety of the president and his family.”</p>
<p>House Speaker Nancy Pelosi, D-Calif., said Friday morning that she was praying for the president and his family, adding that she hoped the “tragic” situation would prompt “a transition to a saner approach” to minimizing the risk of infection.</p>
<p>“Maybe now that people who see the president of the United States with all the protection that he has, and the First Lady, still having this exposure, it might be … a learning experience,” Pelosi said during an interview on MSNBC. “But more than learning, it has to be something that’s acted upon.”</p>
<p>Pelosi said she was tested Friday out of “an abundance of caution,” but did not have the result yet. Her only contact with White House officials in recent days was negotiating over another coronavirus relief package with Treasury Secretary Steve Mnuchin, who announced he had a negative test Friday morning.</p>
<p>Sen. Tim Kaine, D-Va., wished the Trumps well in a statement. &#8220;Having had COVID-19, let me stress: all need to take this seriously,&#8221; he wrote. &#8220;Please follow CDC guidelines of mask wearing, hand washing, and social distancing.”</p>
<p>Gov. Ralph Northam, who tested positive last week, offered a similar message, tweeting, &#8220;This virus is very real and very serious. Let’s continue to take care of each other by doing the right things.&#8221;</p>
<p>A memo from Dr. Sean P. Conley, the president’s physician, said he received information on Thursday night that the president, who at 74 would be at high risk for complications from the virus, and Melania had tested positive for COVID-19.</p>
<p>“The President and First Lady are both well at this time, and they plan to remain at home within the White House during their convalescence,” Conley wrote.</p>
<p>“The White House medical team and I will maintain a vigilant watch, and I appreciate the support provided by some of our country’s greatest medical professionals and institutions,” he said. “Rest assured I expect the President to continue carrying out his duties without disruption while recovering, and I will keep you updated on any future developments.”</p>
<p>Trump’s updated schedule for Friday includes hosting a 12:15 p.m. phone call on COVID-19 support for vulnerable seniors.</p>
<p>On social media Friday morning, members of Congress from both parties reacted to Trump’s diagnosis, wishing him a quick recovery. Those who were in contact with Trump this week in D.C. and as he traveled to Ohio and Minnesota also weighed in with the precautions they planned to take.</p>
<p>U.S. Rep. Jim Jordan, R-Ohio, who flew on Air Force One with the president to Tuesday’s debate in Cleveland, said during a Fox News interview Friday morning that he was only around the president briefly but would be tested.</p>
<p>A spokeswoman for U.S. Sen. Rob Portman of Ohio, who was with Trump for an event outside the White House on Monday, said he is not experiencing any symptoms but canceled his in-person events Friday and plans to take a test.</p>
<p>Jason Lewis, a Republican U.S. Senate candidate from Minnesota, who interacted with Trump during the president’s visit to the state Wednesday, said he also was self-quarantining and would be getting a test “as soon as possible.”</p>
<p>The president’s positive test result comes days after he and Biden met for their first debate. The two men did not shake hands and stayed on opposite sides of the stage, which was in a large atrium on Case Western Reserve University’s campus.</p>
<p>Official safety precautions for that event, co-hosted by the Cleveland Clinic, largely focused on the audience, which was much smaller than usual for a presidential debate. The roughly 80 audience seats were spaced out from each other, and those seated had to test negative for coronavirus. Those in the audience could be seen wearing masks, with the exception of Trump’s family members and top aides.</p>
<p>A White House spokeswoman tweeted Friday morning that Trump’s daughter, Ivanka Trump, and her husband, Jared Kushner, who were both in the debate audience, tested negative Friday morning.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
