<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Shauneen Miranda, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/shauneen-miranda/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/shauneen-miranda/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 18:48:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Shauneen Miranda, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/shauneen-miranda/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Johnson wins Trump’s endorsement to continue as U.S. House speaker</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/30/dc/johnson-wins-trumps-endorsement-to-continue-as-u-s-house-speaker/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 18:32:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=dc_bureau&#038;p=41638</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — As U.S. House Speaker Mike Johnson vies to keep his gavel, President-elect Donald Trump on Monday gave the Louisiana Republican a major boost with his “Complete &#38; Total Endorsement.” Trump’s coveted backing — just days ahead of Friday’s House vote to elect a speaker — came as Johnson sat in the hot seat [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/gettyimages-2148449818-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="U.S. House Speaker Mike Johnson speaks as former President Donald Trump looks on at a press conference at Trump’s Mar-a-Lago club on April 12, 2024, in Palm Beach, Florida. Trump, who won November’s presidential election, endorsed Johnson to remain speaker Monday. (Photo by Joe Raedle/Getty Images)" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/gettyimages-2148449818-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/gettyimages-2148449818-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/gettyimages-2148449818-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/gettyimages-2148449818-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/gettyimages-2148449818-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. House Speaker Mike Johnson speaks as former President Donald Trump looks on at a press conference at Trump’s Mar-a-Lago club on April 12, 2024, in Palm Beach, Florida. Trump, who won November’s presidential election, endorsed Johnson to remain speaker Monday. (Photo by Joe Raedle/Getty Images)</p><p dir="ltr">WASHINGTON — As U.S. House Speaker Mike Johnson vies to keep his gavel, President-elect Donald Trump on Monday gave the Louisiana Republican a major boost with his “Complete &amp; Total Endorsement.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Trump’s coveted backing — just days ahead of Friday’s House vote to elect a speaker — came as Johnson sat in the hot seat over a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/congress-clears-bill-avert-government-shutdown-extend-farm-bill" target="_blank">government shutdown quarrel</a> earlier this month that exacerbated public dissatisfaction from several of his GOP colleagues over his leadership.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The spending fight also put a spotlight on his vulnerabilities in securing the votes to win the speakership again.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“The American people need IMMEDIATE relief from all of the destructive policies of the last Administration,” Trump said in a Monday post on&nbsp;<a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/113742374534233751" target="_blank">Truth Social</a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The soon-to-be president described Johnson as a “good, hard working, religious man,” noting that “he will do the right thing, and we will continue to WIN.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">In a post on&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/speakerjohnson/status/1873758339324362916?s=46" target="_blank">X</a> shortly after the endorsement, Johnson said he was “honored and humbled” by Trump’s support. “Together, we will quickly deliver on your America First agenda and usher in the new golden age of America,” he added.</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">Tensions flare</h4>
<p dir="ltr">But Johnson has failed to secure the backing of every House GOP colleague —&nbsp;which will be critical in a chamber Republicans will hold by a razor-thin margin. His opponents include Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky, who said he would not be voting for the incumbent.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In a post on&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/1873776475264213174" target="_blank">X</a>, Massie said: “I respect and support President Trump, but his endorsement of Mike Johnson is going to work out about as well as his endorsement of Speaker Paul Ryan.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“We’ve seen Johnson partner with the democrats to send money to Ukraine, authorize spying on Americans, and blow the budget,” he added.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In an earlier Monday post on&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/1873684971526955030" target="_blank">X</a>, Massie noted he was the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2017/01/paul-ryan-easily-wins-reelection-as-speaker-of-the-house-233139" target="_blank">only Republican</a> to not vote for former U.S. House Speaker Paul Ryan’s reelection to the speakership in 2017.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“Mike Johnson is the next Paul Ryan,” Massie said. He urged his colleagues to join him in voting against the Louisiana Republican “because history will not give America another ‘do-over.’”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Massie has not said whom he would prefer for the position.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In another post&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/1873704602513924355" target="_blank">on X</a>, Massie said he thinks no one will run for speaker until “Johnson concedes that he can’t be Speaker” and “Trump weighs in.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“To step up before then, or to nominate someone before then, is to doom that candidacy,” he said.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Indiana GOP Rep. Victoria Spartz has also been vocal in her dissatisfaction of Johnson’s leadership and so far has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.foxnews.com/video/6366548934112" target="_blank">refused to commit to voting</a> for his reelection.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">On Monday, Spartz laid out&nbsp;<a href="https://spartz.house.gov/media/press-releases/spartz-it-will-take-bold-and-decisive-leadership-reverse-titanic-its-0" target="_blank">several demands</a> for whoever becomes the next leader, saying: “Our next speaker must show courageous leadership to get our country back on track before this ‘Titanic’ strikes an iceberg at any moment.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“We must have a vision and a concrete PLAN to deliver on President Trump’s agenda for the American people, which I have not seen from our current speaker despite countless discussions and public promises,” she added, comparing federal spending to the iceberg that caused the infamous nautical disaster.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Spokespeople for House Democratic Leader Hakeem Jeffries of New York did not immediately respond Monday to a message seeking comment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>FAFSA form must launch by Oct. 1 every year under new law</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/16/dc/fafsa-form-must-launch-by-oct-1-every-year-under-new-law/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 10:25:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[colleges and universities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fafsa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal student aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial aid]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=dc_bureau&#038;p=41498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The form to apply for federal financial student aid must roll out by Oct. 1 annually after President Joe Biden signed a bill into law Wednesday that ensures an earlier processing cycle. Though the Free Application for Federal Student Aid, or FAFSA, typically launches in October each year, the U.S. Department of Education legally had [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="633" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/fafsaform-1024x633.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/fafsaform-1024x633.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/fafsaform-300x185.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/fafsaform-768x474.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/fafsaform-1536x949.jpeg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/fafsaform-2048x1265.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The form to apply for federal financial student aid now must roll out by Oct. 1 annually under a bill signed into law by President Joe Biden on Wednesday, Dec. 11, 2024. (Photo by Getty Images)</p><p dir="ltr">WASHINGTON — The form to apply for federal financial student aid must roll out by Oct. 1 annually after President Joe Biden <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-house-passes-bill-move-annual-fafsa-release-deadline" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signed a bill into law</a> Wednesday that ensures an earlier processing cycle.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Though the <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/feds-roll-out-2025-26-college-financial-aid-form-ahead-planned-date" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Free Application for Federal Student Aid</a>, or FAFSA, typically launches in October each year, the U.S. Department of Education legally had until Jan. 1 to make the form available.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The new law came as the department has taken heat over its <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/gaps-fafsa-rollout-are-closing-watchdog-tells-us-house-panel" target="_blank" rel="noopener">botched rollout</a> of the 2024-25 form, when users faced a series of glitches and errors. The form did not officially launch until January.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Adding fuel to the fire, the agency announced earlier this year that it would take a staggered approach to the 2025-26 form so it could address problems that might pop up before opening applications to everyone — again making the form available later than usual.</p>
<p dir="ltr">After <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-department-education-begins-testing-new-fafsa-form" target="_blank" rel="noopener">testing stages</a> that began Oct. 1, the department fully debuted the 2025-26 form in late November — 10 days ahead of its Dec. 1 official launch.</p>
<p dir="ltr">A spokesperson for the department said it is “committed to enforcing all laws duly passed by Congress” when asked about Biden signing the FAFSA bill into law.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Meanwhile, the department said Thursday it had received over 1.5 million 2025-26 FAFSA submissions and has delivered more than 7 million student records to states and schools.</p>
<p dir="ltr">U.S. Under Secretary of Education James Kvaal said that even with these developments, the department’s work “is not done.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">“We will continue to fix bugs and improve the user experience to make it easier for students and families to get the financial aid they need,” Kvaal said on a call with reporters Thursday regarding updates on the 2025-26 form.</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">FAFSA deadline bill breezed through Congress</h4>
<p dir="ltr">The bill was met with sweeping bipartisan support and swiftly passed both the House and Senate in November. Indiana GOP Rep. Erin Houchin, a member of the U.S. House Committee on Education and the Workforce, introduced the legislation in July.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Sen. Bill Cassidy, ranking member of the U.S. Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions, put forth the Senate version of the bill. The Louisiana Republican is in line to chair the panel next year.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Rep. Bobby Scott, ranking member of the House education panel, celebrated the bill becoming law on Wednesday.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“As college costs continue to rise, federal financial aid, including Pell Grants, is essential to making higher education more affordable and accessible,” the Virginia Democrat said in a statement.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Scott said that by standardizing the deadline, the measure “gives students and families more time to complete their applications and secure the financial support they need to attend college without unnecessary delays.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">The 2024-25 application got a makeover after Congress passed the FAFSA Simplification Act in late 2020 but was met with several issues that prompted processing delays and gaps in submissions.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The department’s staff worked to fix these errors and close the gap in submissions from the previous processing cycle, and officials said they reflected on how to make improvements for the 2025-26 form and beyond. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. Education Department pings states, schools to set policies on cellphone use</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/03/dc/u-s-education-department-pings-states-schools-to-set-policies-on-cellphone-use/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 20:26:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=dc_bureau&#038;p=41027</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The U.S. Education Department called on every state, school and district on Tuesday to adopt policies on cellphone use in schools. The department asks schools to have well-thought-out policies on the matter, but does not dictate exactly what those policies should be. An accompanying resource for schools notes the risk social media can [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/girls-with-phones-scaled-2-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/girls-with-phones-scaled-2-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/girls-with-phones-scaled-2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/girls-with-phones-scaled-2-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/girls-with-phones-scaled-2-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/girls-with-phones-scaled-2-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The U.S. Education Department urged schools and districts on Tuesday to set policies governing smartphone use in schools. (Photo by SDI Productions via Getty Images)</p><p dir="ltr">WASHINGTON — The U.S. Education Department called on every state, school and district on Tuesday to adopt policies on cellphone use in schools.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The department asks schools to have well-thought-out policies on the matter, but does not dictate exactly what those policies should be. An accompanying resource for schools notes the risk social media can pose to students’ mental health.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“In this digital age, every elementary, middle, and high school should have a clear, consistent, and research-informed policy to guide the use of phones and personal devices in school,” U.S Education Secretary Miguel Cardona said in a written statement.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“The evidence makes clear: there is no one-size-fits-all policy,” Cardona added, noting that “different school communities have different needs, and the nuances of this issue demand that local voices — parents, educators, and students — inform local decisions around the use of personal devices in school.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">The department acknowledged the role cellphones can play in keeping parents connected to their kids, especially in emergency situations, while also highlighting the increasing evidence on the harms social media can have on youth mental health, such as sleep deprivation and depression.</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">Increasing state policies</h4>
<p dir="ltr">An increasing number of states and school districts have enacted policies either prohibiting or restricting students from using their cellphones in the classrooms.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Across the country, schools and districts continue to grapple with how to deal with kids’ cellphone use, and <a href="https://www.axios.com/2024/09/29/cell-phone-schools-bans-states" target="_blank" rel="noopener">more than half of all states</a> have sought to ban or restrict cellphone use in classrooms.</p>
<p dir="ltr">As of early November, at least eight states have passed statewide policies that either limit or prohibit cellphone use in the classrooms, according to <a href="https://www.kff.org/mental-health/issue-brief/a-look-at-state-efforts-to-ban-cellphones-in-schools-and-implications-for-youth-mental-health/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KFF</a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That includes California, Florida, Indiana, Louisiana, Ohio, South Carolina and Virginia. A Minnesota law forces schools to <a href="https://www.mprnews.org/episode/2024/08/29/minnesota-now-new-school-cellphone-policy-landscape-across-minnesota-locked-pouches" target="_blank" rel="noopener">adopt a policy on cellphone use</a> by March 2025.</p>
<p dir="ltr">A handful of other states’ <a href="https://oregoncapitalchronicle.com/2024/11/01/oregon-department-of-education-offers-schools-guidance-on-limiting-student-cell-phone-use/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">education departments</a> have issued <a href="https://alaskabeacon.com/2024/10/24/alaska-joins-growing-number-of-states-considering-crackdown-on-cellphones-in-schools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">policy recommendations</a> or pilot programs, while lawmakers in several more have introduced statewide legislation regarding cellphone use.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The guidance from the U.S. Education Department coincides with the release of a <a href="https://tech.ed.gov/device-policy-playbook/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">resource</a> for education officials and local communities on adopting cellphone use policies.</p>
<p dir="ltr">In the playbook, Cardona points to U.S. Surgeon General Dr. Vivek Murthy’s <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/sg-youth-mental-health-social-media-advisory.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public warning</a> in 2023 on <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/prodded-fed-parents-some-congress-try-curb-kids-use-social-media" target="_blank" rel="noopener">social media’s effects</a> on youth mental health.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Murthy warns: “More research is needed to fully understand the impact of social media; however, the current body of evidence indicates that while social media may have benefits for some children and adolescents, there are ample indicators that social media can also have a profound risk of harm to the mental health and well-being of children and adolescents.” </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. House passes bill to move up annual FAFSA release deadline</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/11/18/dc/u-s-house-passes-bill-to-move-up-annual-fafsa-release-deadline/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 10:25:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Board of Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fafsa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal student aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Application for Federal Student Aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Rep. Bobby Scott]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?post_type=dc_bureau&#038;p=40864</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — A measure to ensure the federal student aid form opens up annually by Oct. 1 passed the U.S. House Friday with overwhelming bipartisan support. The&#160;effort — which passed 381-1 — came after the U.S. Department of Education faced major backlash over the botched rollout of the 2024-25&#160;Free Application for Federal Student Aid, or [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/fafsabus-scaled-2-1024x768.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/fafsabus-scaled-2-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/fafsabus-scaled-2-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/fafsabus-scaled-2-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/fafsabus-scaled-2-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/fafsabus-scaled-2-2048x1536.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A sign reminding people to complete the Free Application for Federal Student Aid — better known as FAFSA — appears on a bus near Union Station in Washington, D.C. (Shauneen Miranda/States Newsroom)</p><p dir="ltr">WASHINGTON — A measure to ensure the federal student aid form opens up annually by Oct. 1 passed the U.S. House Friday with overwhelming bipartisan support.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/BILLS-118hr8932rh/pdf/BILLS-118hr8932rh.pdf" target="_blank">effort</a> — which passed 381-1 — came after the U.S. Department of Education faced major backlash over the botched rollout of the 2024-25&nbsp;<a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/dont-give-fafsa-advocates-student-financial-aid-urge" target="_blank">Free Application for Federal Student Aid</a>, or FAFSA. California Democratic Rep. Zoe Lofgren was the only lawmaker to vote against the bill.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Though the form got a makeover after Congress passed the FAFSA Simplification Act in late 2020, users faced multiple glitches and technical errors throughout the form’s soft launch in December and past its full debut in January, prompting processing delays and gaps in submissions.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The department has worked to correct these glitches and close that gap while also fixing major issues that prevented parents without Social Security numbers from completing the form.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Adding another complication, the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-education-department-gradually-roll-out-new-fafsa-form-dec-1" target="_blank">department said in August</a> it would use a phased rollout of the 2025-26 form in an attempt to address any errors that might arise before it opens up to everyone — making the application fully available two months later than usual.</p>
<p>“Since Oct. 1, the Department has conducted three successful beta tests of the 2025–26 FAFSA form to ensure it is ready for all students and families on or before Dec. 1,” U.S. Under Secretary of Education James Kvaal said in a statement shared Monday with States Newsroom, while noting that the department already began its fourth testing stage this past week.</p>
<p>“We have a fully functioning site and a form working end-to-end that has been successfully submitted by more than 10,000 students, with dozens of schools all over the country receiving the data for student aid packages,” he said.</p>
<p>The department is on track to launch the 2026-27 FAFSA on Oct. 1, 2025, with “a fully functioning system,” according to Kvaal.&nbsp;</p>
<h4 dir="ltr">Codified deadline</h4>
<p dir="ltr">Though the department legally has until Jan. 1 to roll out the form, it typically launches Oct. 1.</p>
<p dir="ltr">U.S. Rep. Erin Houchin, an Indiana Republican and member of the U.S. House Committee on Education and the Workforce, in July&nbsp;<a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/house-bill/8932" target="_blank">introduced the bill</a> to standardize that deadline.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“I’m especially frustrated considering the Department of Education has had three years to simplify the FAFSA as Congress has dictated,” Houchin said during floor debate Friday.</p>
<p dir="ltr">She also&nbsp;<a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/gaps-fafsa-rollout-are-closing-watchdog-tells-us-house-panel" target="_blank">referenced recent findings</a> from the Government Accountability Office, including that nearly three-quarters of all calls to the call center went unanswered in the first five months of the 2024-25 rollout.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“We want this program to work — we want to make sure that children and families that want to send their kids to college have the availability to do that and that the FAFSA is available and workable,” she added.</p>
<p dir="ltr">U.S. Rep. Bobby Scott, ranking member of the House education panel, echoed his support during the floor debate, saying the measure will “help ensure that even more students have the information they need in a timelier manner to access Pell Grants and other vital student aid.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Scott initially opposed the effort when the committee took it up in July out of concerns that the implementation deadline could force the department to roll out an incomplete form on Oct. 1 of this year.</p>
<p dir="ltr">“However, because we’re now considering the bill after Oct. 1, the deadline will apply next year, 2025, and that gives the department ample time to make improvements and fix any lingering issues,” the Virginia Democrat said.</p>
<p dir="ltr">U.S. Sen. Bill Cassidy, a Louisiana Republican,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/senate-bill/4632" target="_blank">introduced a companion bill</a> in July.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The bill was referred to the U.S. Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions, where Cassidy serves as ranking member. After Republicans won a Senate majority in the Nov. 5 elections,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.help.senate.gov/ranking/newsroom/press/cassidy-to-chair-help-committee-in-119th-congress" target="_blank">Cassidy is in line</a> to chair the panel next year.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. Department of Education begins testing of new FAFSA form</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/10/02/u-s-department-of-education-begins-testing-of-new-fafsa-form/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 09:15:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fafsa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal student aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[higher education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Department of Education]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40241</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The U.S. Department of Education is launching the first testing period for its phased rollout of the 2025-26 form to apply for federal financial student aid on Tuesday, with more students set to partake in this beginning testing stage than initially expected. The department announced in August it would be using a staggered approach to [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/FAFSAbus-scaled-1-1024x768.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/FAFSAbus-scaled-1-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/FAFSAbus-scaled-1-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/FAFSAbus-scaled-1-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/FAFSAbus-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/FAFSAbus-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A sign reminding people to complete the Free Application for Federal Student Aid — better known as FAFSA — appears on a bus near Union Station in Washington, D.C. (Photo by Shauneen Miranda/States Newsroom)</p><p>WASHINGTON — The U.S. Department of Education is launching the first testing period for its phased rollout of the 2025-26 form to apply for federal financial student aid on Tuesday, with more students set to partake in this beginning testing stage than initially expected.</p>
<p>The department <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-education-department-gradually-roll-out-new-fafsa-form-dec-1" target="_blank">announced in August</a> it would be using a staggered approach to launch the 2025-26 <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/dont-give-fafsa-advocates-student-financial-aid-urge" target="_blank">Free Application for Federal Student Aid</a> — or FAFSA — in order to address any issues that might arise before the form opens up to everyone by Dec. 1. The number of students able to complete the form will gradually increase throughout four separate testing stages, with the first one beginning Oct. 1.</p>
<p>The phased rollout makes the form fully available two months later than usual and comes as the 2024-25 form — which got a makeover after Congress passed the FAFSA Simplification Act in late 2020 — faced a series of highly publicized hiccups that the department has worked to fix.</p>
<p>Earlier in September, the department <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-education-department-open-new-financial-aid-form-more-applicants" target="_blank">announced six community-based organizations</a> chosen to participate in the first testing period: Alabama Possible; Bridge 2 Life, in Florida; College AIM, in Georgia; Education is Freedom, in Texas; the Scholarship Foundation of Santa Barbara, in California; and the Scholarship Fund of Alexandria, in Virginia.</p>
<p>“Thanks to the wonderful organizations, we expect closer to 1,000 students in Beta 1 as opposed to the 100 we initially thought,” FAFSA executive adviser Jeremy Singer said on a call with reporters Monday regarding the 2025-26 form.</p>
<p>During this first testing stage, U.S. Under Secretary of Education James Kvaal said the department will process students’ FAFSAs, “give students an opportunity to make corrections, if needed, and send the records to colleges and state agencies.”</p>
<p>“Colleges will be able to use these same records when it’s time for them to make financial aid offers,” said Kvaal, who oversees higher education and financial aid, including the Office of Federal Student Aid.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Three more testing periods</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>The department on Monday also named 78 community-based organizations, governmental entities, high schools, school districts and institutions of higher education to participate in its three subsequent testing periods for the 2025-26 form.</p>
<p>Three of the community-based organizations chosen to take part in the first testing period — Florida’s Bridge 2 Life; Texas’ Education is Freedom; and Virginia’s  Scholarship Fund of Alexandria — will also participate in subsequent testing stages.</p>
<p>To help students and families prepare for the 2025-26 application cycle, the department said this week it’s releasing a revised <a href="https://studentaid.gov/aid-estimator/" target="_blank">Federal Student Aid Estimator</a>, updated resources for creating a <a href="http://studentaid.gov/" target="_blank">StudentAid.Gov account</a>, including a “parent wizard,” as well as an updated prototype of the 2025-26 FAFSA.</p>
<p>Last week, the department released <a href="https://www.ed.gov/sites/ed/files/2024-09/AFocusonImprovingtheFAFSAExperience.pdf" target="_blank">a report</a> outlining 10 steps it’s taking to <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/gaps-fafsa-rollout-are-closing-watchdog-tells-us-house-panel" target="_blank">improve the FAFSA application process</a>. Part of those efforts include the department strengthening its leadership team and working to address issues for families without Social Security numbers when completing the form, in addition to vendors adding more than 700 new call center agents.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gaps in FAFSA rollout are closing, watchdog tells U.S. House panel</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/25/gaps-in-fafsa-rollout-are-closing-watchdog-tells-u-s-house-panel/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 17:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[college admissions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fafsa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal student aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Application for Federal Student Aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government Accountability Office]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pell Grant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Education Secretary Miguel Cardona]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40168</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — Months after the rollout of the streamlined form to apply for federal financial student aid faced a series of highly publicized hiccups that prompted processing delays and frustrated students and families, a government watchdog offered some additional explanation Tuesday of what went wrong and recommendations for the U.S. Education Department going forward. Members [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="633" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/FAFSA-2048x1265-1-1024x633.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/FAFSA-2048x1265-1-1024x633.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/FAFSA-2048x1265-1-300x185.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/FAFSA-2048x1265-1-768x474.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/FAFSA-2048x1265-1-1536x949.jpeg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/FAFSA-2048x1265-1.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A federal watchdog found that about 432,000 fewer people submitted a FAFSA compared to last year — marking a 3% decrease as of late August. (Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — Months after the rollout of the streamlined <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/dont-give-fafsa-advocates-student-financial-aid-urge" target="_blank">form to apply for federal financial student aid</a> faced a series of highly publicized hiccups that prompted processing delays and frustrated students and families, a government watchdog offered some additional explanation Tuesday of what went wrong and recommendations for the U.S. Education Department going forward.</p>
<p>Members of the U.S. House Subcommittee on Higher Education and Workforce Development expressed frustration Tuesday over the botched rollout and its repercussions for students and families at a hearing that coincided with the release of a <a href="https://www.gao.gov/products/gao-24-107783" target="_blank">pair of findings</a> from the <a href="https://www.gao.gov/products/gao-24-107407" target="_blank">Government Accountability Office</a> on the major issues that plagued the rollout of the 2024-25 Free Application for Federal Student Aid, or FAFSA.</p>
<p>Though the application got a makeover after Congress passed the FAFSA Simplification Act, advocates have shared concerns over processing delays as a result of the form’s <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2024/01/24/politics/fafsa-inflation-fix-income/index.html" target="_blank">failure to adjust for inflation,</a> its <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/miscalculation-in-fafsa-formula-is-another-unforced-error" target="_blank">formula miscalculation</a> and its <a href="https://fsapartners.ed.gov/knowledge-center/library/electronic-announcements/2024-04-01/update-tax-data-received-fa-ddx-and-manually-entered-information" target="_blank">tax data errors</a>. Major issues also initially prevented parents without Social Security numbers from completing the form.</p>
<p>The department has worked to fix issues surrounding the 2024-25 form and reevaluated the implementation of the 2025-26 form, taking into account feedback from students, families and stakeholders.</p>
<p>On Monday, the <a href="https://www.ed.gov/sites/ed/files/2024-09/AFocusonImprovingtheFAFSAExperience.pdf" target="_blank">department released a report</a> reviewing implementation of the 2024-25 form as well as the progress it’s making to try to improve the user experience since the streamlined form launched.</p>
<p>Part of those efforts include the department <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-education-department-open-new-financial-aid-form-more-applicants" target="_blank">using a phased rollout of the 2025-26 form</a> in an effort to address any problems that might arise before opening to everyone by Dec. 1. The staggered approach will make the 2025-26 FAFSA fully available two months later than usual.</p>
<p>Members of both parties criticized the 2024-25 form’s rollout at Tuesday’s hearing.</p>
<p>Subcommittee Chairman Burgess Owens said the “FAFSA rollout was mired in delays, errors, frustration — and for some of our most vulnerable students — the loss of their dreams for a higher education.”</p>
<p>The Utah Republican said the “impact of the Biden administration’s failure on real lives has been devastating.”</p>
<p>Rep. Frederica Wilson, ranking member of the subcommittee, said implementation of the FAFSA Simplification Act “has been derailed by a series of mistakes made by the Department of Education, leading to delays and ongoing setbacks in the rollout of the new application.”</p>
<p>The Florida Democrat expressed frustration that “aside from the dozens of letters Congress has sent, this is not the first hearing we’ve had this year about this same issue, nor is this the first application cycle with these issues.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Lack of information</h4>

	
<p>In one of the two GAO reports released Tuesday, the watchdog found that about 432,000 fewer people submitted a FAFSA compared to last year — marking a 3% decrease as of late August.</p>
<p>The decline in submissions was “most pronounced among lower income students and families,” per GAO.</p>
<p>The investigators also found that the department did not consistently provide students with timely information on processing delays, changes in their student aid eligibility, or “solutions to technical barriers they encountered during the application process.”</p>
<p>Melissa Emrey-Arras, a director at GAO who oversees work on education, said at the Tuesday hearing that delays “significantly hindered (students’) ability to choose a college, thinking wisely about their finances and whether they could afford a school.”</p>
<p>“Can you imagine? It’s like buying a house but not knowing how much aid you’re gonna get and having to make a commitment right then and there,” Emrey-Arras said.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Understaffing leads to unanswered calls</h4>

	
<p>The government watchdog also found that, as a result of understaffing, nearly three-quarters of all calls to the call center went unanswered in the first five months of the 2024-25 rollout — totalling 4 million out of 5.4 million calls.</p>
<p>As for the communication with schools, GAO found that the department “consistently failed to meet promised deadlines and provide colleges with sufficient notice” of timeframe changes throughout the 2024-25 FAFSA rollout.</p>
<p>Marisol Cruz Cain, a GAO director who oversees work on information technology, said the Office of Federal Student Aid “did not fully test the system, leading to numerous performance problems.”</p>
<p>Cruz Cain said that after the initial deployment, “FSA identified 55 defects, which was almost twice as many as were identified when testing the system as a whole prior to launch.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Improvement plan</h4>

	
<p>In a Monday <a href="https://www.ed.gov/laws-and-policy/education-policy/secretarys-cover-letter-focus-improving-fafsa-experience" target="_blank">letter to college and university presidents</a> regarding progress on the 2025-26 form, U.S. Education Secretary Miguel Cardona said the department “has worked tirelessly to completely overhaul a system that had largely remained untouched for over four decades and itself included twenty different sub-systems that required significant changes — a wholesale transformation to enable the most sweeping changes to federal financial aid eligibility and processes in years.”</p>
<p>The department outlined in its <a href="https://www.ed.gov/sites/ed/files/2024-09/AFocusonImprovingtheFAFSAExperience.pdf" target="_blank">report</a> Monday 10 steps it has taken to improve the FAFSA application process, such as increasing the number of call center agents — with more than 700 new agents added. The department is also working to address issues families without Social Security numbers faced when completing the form.</p>
<p>The department’s efforts also include strengthening its leadership team and offering “additional outreach and support for students and families who need the most help completing the form.”</p>
<p>In a statement responding to Tuesday’s hearing, a spokesperson for the department said that “after the first major overhaul of the FAFSA system in more than four decades, there are more than 500,000 more students eligible for Pell Grants than there were at this time last year.”</p>
<p>“We have sought advice from students and families, colleges, and partners and provided more than 1,000 documents to the Government Accountability Office,” the spokesperson added. “Thanks to this input, along with community partnerships, we have now narrowed the FAFSA completion gap to about 2% compared to this time last year — down from 40% in March.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. House passes ‘anti-woke’ bill aimed at diversity, equity and inclusion in higher ed</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/20/u-s-house-passes-anti-woke-bill-aimed-at-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-in-higher-ed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 16:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[D.C. Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[higher education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[national education policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Title IV]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Rep. Bobby Scott]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40108</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON —  A GOP measure barring accrediting organizations from requiring colleges and universities to adopt diversity, equity and inclusion policies as a condition of accreditation passed the U.S. House Thursday, though its fate appears dim. The End Woke Higher Education Act — which succeeded 213-201 — marks one of several so-called anti-woke initiatives and messaging bills from Republican lawmakers to hit [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Getty_student_college-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Getty_student_college-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Getty_student_college-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Getty_student_college-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Getty_student_college-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Getty_student_college-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">(Getty Images / ferrantraite) </p><p>WASHINGTON —  A GOP measure barring accrediting organizations from requiring colleges and universities to adopt diversity, equity and inclusion policies as a condition of accreditation passed the U.S. House Thursday, though its fate appears dim.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://docs.house.gov/billsthisweek/20240916/RCP_3724_01_xml.pdf" target="_blank">End Woke Higher Education Act</a> — which succeeded <a href="https://clerk.house.gov/Votes/2024433" data-type="link" data-id="https://clerk.house.gov/Votes/2024433" target="_blank">213-201</a> — marks one of <a href="https://www.gop.gov/news/documentsingle.aspx?DocumentID=1850" target="_blank">several so-called anti-woke initiatives</a> and messaging bills from Republican lawmakers to hit the House floor this week.</p>
<p>The higher education measure, which drew fierce opposition from the Biden administration and major associations of colleges and universities, came amid a <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/government-shutdown-deadline-nearing-us-house-stumbles-stopgap-spending-bill%C2%A0" target="_blank">looming government shutdown deadline</a> and in the heat of the 2024 campaign.</p>
<p>Four House Democrats voted in favor of the GOP measure, including Reps. Don Davis of North Carolina, Jared Golden of Maine, Mary Peltola of Alaska and Marie Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington.</p>
<p>Baked into the legislation are two bills introduced by Republican members of the U.S. House Committee on Education and the Workforce — the Accreditation for College Excellence Act and the Respecting the First Amendment on Campus Act.</p>
<p>Utah Rep. Burgess Owens, chairman of the Subcommittee on Higher Education and Workforce Development, introduced the <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/house-bill/3724/text" target="_blank">Accreditation for College Excellence Act</a> in May 2023, while New York Rep. Brandon Williams brought forth the <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/house-bill/7683/text" target="_blank">Respecting the First Amendment on Campus Act</a> in March.</p>
<p>In a statement to States Newsroom, Owens said “House Republicans passed the End Woke Higher Education Act to stand up for academic freedom, defend students’ constitutional rights, and ensure that colleges and universities aren’t forced to bend the knee to activist accreditors pushing political agendas as a condition for federal funding.”</p>
<p>The Utah Republican said the “Biden-Harris administration has injected its far-left ideology — Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion and Critical Race Theory — into every part of American life, including our higher education system.”</p>
<p>Owens’ bill says accreditation standards must not require, encourage or coerce institutions to support or oppose “a specific partisan, political, or ideological viewpoint or belief” or “set of viewpoints or beliefs on social, cultural, or political issues” or support “the disparate treatment of any individual or group of individuals.”</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Williams’ Respecting the First Amendment on Campus Act forces schools to disclose policies regarding free speech to students and faculty as a condition of receiving any Title IV funds.</p>
<p>Title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 includes <a href="https://fsapartners.ed.gov/knowledge-center/library/program/All%20Title%20IV%20Federal%20Student%20Aid%20Programs" target="_blank">federal student financial aid programs</a>.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Strong opposition </h4>

	</strong></p>
<figure id="attachment_13889" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:300px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/21/u-s-house-dems-ask-osha-to-respond-to-reports-that-state-agencies-tipped-off-employers/nancy-pelosi-house-democrats-unveil-college-affordability-act/" rel="attachment wp-att-13889"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-13889" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/Va.-Bobby-Scott-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/Va.-Bobby-Scott-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/Va.-Bobby-Scott-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/Va.-Bobby-Scott-696x464.jpg 696w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/Va.-Bobby-Scott-630x420.jpg 630w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/Va.-Bobby-Scott.jpg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  WASHINGTON, DC &#8211; OCTOBER 15: Rep. Bobby Scott (D-VA) speaks during a news conference discussing the College Affordability Act on October 15, 2019 in Washington, DC. (Zach Gibson/Getty Images)</p></figure>
<p>But the legislation is highly unlikely to be passed in the Democratic-controlled Senate.</p>
<p>The Biden administration also strongly opposed the measure, saying in a <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAP-HR-3724.pdf" target="_blank">statement</a> this week that the legislation would “micromanage both public and private institutions, undermining their ability to recognize and promote diversity.”</p>
<p>The legislation “would go beyond Congress’s traditional role in higher education with a wide range of confusing and unprecedented new mandates,” the administration added.</p>
<p>Rep. Bobby Scott — ranking member of the U.S. House Committee on Education and the Workforce — called the measure a “baseless attempt to inject culture wars into an ever-important accreditation process” during the floor debate Thursday.</p>
<p>The Virginia Democrat said the legislation “attempts to circumvent the First Amendment to establish a whole new scheme to regulate speech and association rights on campus outside of established precedents and practices.”</p>
<p>The GOP measure also drew the ire of leading associations of colleges and universities, who opposed the legislation both individually and collectively.</p>
<p>In a joint letter this week to House Speaker Mike Johnson of Louisiana and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries of New York, <a href="https://www.aau.edu/sites/default/files/Letter-House-End-Woke-Higher-Education-Act-091724.pdf" target="_blank">six major associations</a> led by the American Council on Education took aim at Williams’ portion of the legislation, saying it “would undermine efforts to protect free speech on campus and provide safe learning environments free from discrimination.”</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. Education Department to open new financial aid form to more applicants</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/12/u-s-education-department-to-open-new-financial-aid-form-to-more-applicants/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 09:27:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fafsa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Application for Federal Student Aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student loans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Department of Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia colleges and universities]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40010</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The U.S. Department of Education named the first six organizations to participate in the phased rollout of the 2025-26 form to apply for federal financial student aid Wednesday, and opened up the interest form for high schools, school districts and other entities to get involved in its next three testing periods. In August, the department said it [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="800" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/student-loans-debt-money-roll-mortarboard-getty-1536x1200-1-1024x800.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/student-loans-debt-money-roll-mortarboard-getty-1536x1200-1-1024x800.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/student-loans-debt-money-roll-mortarboard-getty-1536x1200-1-300x234.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/student-loans-debt-money-roll-mortarboard-getty-1536x1200-1-768x600.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/student-loans-debt-money-roll-mortarboard-getty-1536x1200-1.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The U.S. Education Department will open up the phased rollout of the new federal financial aid form to high schools, districts and other organizations. (Photo by Catherine Lane/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — The U.S. Department of Education named the first six organizations to participate in the phased rollout of the <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-education-department-outlines-testing-period-phased-rollout-new-fafsa-form" target="_blank">2025-26 form to apply for federal financial student aid</a> Wednesday, and <a href="https://fsapartners.ed.gov/knowledge-center/library/electronic-announcements/2024-09-11/availability-2025-26-fafsa-betas-2-4-interest-form" target="_blank">opened up the interest form</a> for high schools, school districts and other entities to get involved in its next three testing periods.</p>
<p>In August, the department said it would <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/us-education-department-gradually-roll-out-new-fafsa-form-dec-1" target="_blank">take a staggered approach</a> to launching the application period for the <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/dont-give-fafsa-advocates-student-financial-aid-urge" target="_blank">Free Application for Federal Student Aid</a> — better known as FAFSA — in an effort to address any problems prior to the updated form opening up to everyone by Dec. 1.</p>
<p>The phased rollout will make the application fully available two months later than usual.</p>
<p>The first testing period beginning Oct. 1 will include six community-based organizations. The department on Wednesday said it selected Alabama Possible; Bridge 2 Life, in Florida; College AIM, in Georgia; Education is Freedom, in Texas; the Scholarship Foundation of Santa Barbara, in California; and the Scholarship Fund of Alexandria, in Virginia; to participate.</p>
<p>The six organizations will provide access to the new form to hundreds of participants in the first testing period. The form will gradually open up to tens of thousands of students in the subsequent testing stages.</p>
<p>“Each of these orgs have committed to recruit 100-plus students and contributors, which will allow us to test the FAFSA system end-to-end from the submissions process, to processing, to ingestion of the (Institutional Student Information Records) by colleges and possibly even state agencies,” FAFSA executive adviser Jeremy Singer said on a call with reporters Wednesday.</p>
<p>Singer said each of the community-based organizations will host an in-person FAFSA event over the first few days of October.</p>
<p>“We will send some of our team members to these sites to observe and learn from our experienced partners, seeing how students and families are interacting with the application, what’s working for them, what’s challenging, what’s clear, what’s less clear,” said Singer, who heads FAFSA strategy within the department’s Office of Federal Student Aid.</p>
<p><strong>Next phases</strong></p>
<p>Singer said the second testing period would launch in mid-October, with the third debuting in early November and the fourth period beginning in mid-November.</p>
<p>Community-based organizations, high schools, school districts and institutions of higher education have from Wednesday until Sept. 20 to submit an interest form to be part of the next three testing periods.</p>
<p>The department said it plans to notify those selected to participate in the second testing period by Sept. 24 and inform those chosen to take part in the third and fourth testing periods shortly afterward.</p>
<p>The department has also worked to close the gap in FAFSA submissions compared to the prior cycle. In March, the department said it received roughly 40% fewer FAFSA applications than the same time last year.</p>
<p>But as of this week, the gap had fallen to approximately 2.3%, the department said.</p>
<p>The department also said that as of early September, roughly 500,000 more FAFSA applicants are eligible for <a href="https://studentaid.gov/understand-aid/types/grants/pell" target="_blank">Pell Grants</a> compared to the same time in 2023.</p>
<p>The updates to the rollout of the 2025-26 form come as the department has worked to resolve the 2024-25 form’s multiple glitches and errors, which advocates voiced concerns over. The application got a makeover following the December 2020 passage of the FAFSA Simplification Act.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 things to know about the Harris-Trump presidential debate</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/09/5-things-to-know-about-the-harris-trump-presidential-debate/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 09:28:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2024 election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harris]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trump]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39927</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vice President Kamala Harris and former President Donald Trump will take the stage tomorrow, Sept. 10, in the only planned debate between the respective Democratic and GOP presidential candidates between now and November. It’s the first presidential debate since President Joe Biden bowed out of the race following his own disastrous debate performance in late [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/redandbluewhitehouse-scaled-1-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/redandbluewhitehouse-scaled-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/redandbluewhitehouse-scaled-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/redandbluewhitehouse-scaled-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/redandbluewhitehouse-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/redandbluewhitehouse-scaled-1-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Vice President Kamala Harris, the Democratic presidential nominee, and former President Donald Trump, the Republican nominee, will debate Sept. 10 in Philadelphia. (Getty Images)</p><p>Vice President Kamala Harris and former President Donald Trump will take the stage tomorrow, Sept. 10, in the only planned debate between the respective Democratic and GOP presidential candidates between now and November.</p>
<p>It’s the first presidential debate since President Joe Biden bowed out of the race following his own disastrous debate performance in late June against Trump. Biden, who faced mounting calls to resign, <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/pass-torch-biden-addresses-nation-why-he-wont-seek-second-term" target="_blank">passed the torch</a> to Harris back in July.</p>
<p>The veep has embarked on an unprecedented and expedited campaign as she and Trump vie for the Oval Office. The election is just two months away.</p>
<p>Though the Harris and Trump campaigns clashed over debate procedures in recent weeks, both candidates have agreed to the finalized rules. ABC News, host of the debate, released the rules Wednesday.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">When and where is the debate?</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>The debate will be Tuesday, Sept. 10, at 9 p.m. Eastern time at the National Constitution Center in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The debate will be 90 minutes long and include two commercial breaks, <a href="https://abc.com/news/5e38600c-4732-4cd2-a99c-3dedfa81beb0/category/1138628" target="_blank">according to ABC</a>.</p>
<p>The Keystone State — where both Harris and Trump have spent a lot of time campaigning — could determine the outcome of the presidential election. The battleground state has narrowly flip-flopped in recent elections, with Biden <a href="https://www.politico.com/2020-election/results/pennsylvania/" target="_blank">turning Pennsylvania blue</a> in 2020 after Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/2016-election/results/map/president/pennsylvania/" target="_blank">secured a red win</a> in 2016.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">How can I watch the debate? </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>The debate will air live on ABC News and will also be streaming on ABC News Live, Disney+ and Hulu.</p>
<p>ABC News’ David Muir and Linsey Davis will moderate the debate.</p>
<p>Harris and Trump will each have two minutes to answer questions and two minutes to give rebuttals. They will also be granted one additional minute to clarify or follow up on anything.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Will the mics be muted? </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>Microphones will be muted when it’s not a candidate’s turn to speak, just like the previous debate between Biden and Trump in June.</p>
<p>The candidates will not give opening statements. Trump won a coin flip to determine the order of closing statements and podium placement. Trump, who selected the statement order, will give the final closing statement.</p>
<p>Each closing statement will be two minutes long.</p>
<p>Harris and Trump are not allowed to bring any props or prewritten notes to the debate stage. They will each receive a pen, a pad of paper and a water bottle.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Will there be a live audience?</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>There will be no live audience at the National Constitution Center, as was the case in the last presidential debate.</p>
<p>Harris and Trump are not permitted to interact with their campaign staff during the two commercial breaks.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Trump slams ABC ahead of debate</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>Trump went on the attack over the details of the debate, telling <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/town-hall-no-questions-trump-grouses-about-polls-attacks-debate-host" target="_blank">Fox News’ Sean Hannity</a> during an interview Wednesday in Pennsylvania that “ABC is the worst network in terms of fairness” and “the most dishonest network, the meanest, the nastiest.”</p>
<p>He accused the network of releasing poor polls on purpose ahead of a previous election to drive down voter turnout.</p>
<p>Trump also claimed, without evidence, that Harris would get the questions in advance of the debate. ABC’s debate rules state that no candidates or campaigns will receive any topics or questions ahead of the event.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Democratic Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz and Ohio Republican Sen. J.D. Vance will battle it out at the <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/mark-your-calendar-vp-candidates-walz-and-vance-debate-oct-1" target="_blank">vice presidential debate</a> hosted by CBS News on Oct. 1 in New York City.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Biden’s newest student loan repayment plan temporarily blocked by Supreme Court</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/30/bidens-newest-student-loan-repayment-plan-temporarily-blocked-by-supreme-court/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 09:19:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President Joe Biden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student loan debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student loans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Supreme Court]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The U.S. Supreme Court on Wednesday slashed the Biden administration’s latest efforts to provide student debt relief to millions of borrowers to go forward while the appeals process unfolds. The Saving on a Valuable Education (SAVE) plan provided lower monthly loan payments for borrowers and lessened the time it takes to pay off [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/graduation-1-scaled-1-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/graduation-1-scaled-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/graduation-1-scaled-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/graduation-1-scaled-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/graduation-1-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/graduation-1-scaled-1-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Saving on a Valuable Education (SAVE) plan provided lower monthly loan payments for borrowers and lessened the time it takes to pay off their debt. (Spencer Platt/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — The U.S. Supreme Court on Wednesday slashed the Biden administration’s latest efforts to provide student debt relief to millions of borrowers to go forward while the appeals process unfolds.</p>
<p>The Saving on a Valuable Education (SAVE) plan provided lower monthly loan payments for borrowers and lessened the time it takes to pay off their debt. The program came shortly after <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/2023/06/supreme-court-strikes-down-biden-student-loan-forgiveness-program/" target="_blank">the Supreme Court struck down</a> an earlier student loan forgiveness plan from the administration in June 2023 that would have canceled more than $400 billion in debt.</p>
<p>But the SAVE plan was quickly met with a wave of legal challenges from a coalition of GOP-led states in two lawsuits stemming from Missouri and Kansas.</p>
<p>Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, North Dakota, Ohio and Oklahoma filed a <a href="https://missouriindependent.com/2024/04/09/missouri-attorney-general-leads-coalition-challenging-biden-student-debt-relief/" target="_blank">federal lawsuit</a> alongside Missouri in April against the administration over the plan.</p>
<p>The Supreme Court on Wednesday allowed an August ruling from the <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2024/08/09/politics/student-loan-repayment-plan-court-blocks/index.html" target="_blank">U.S. Court of Appeals for the 8th Circuit</a> that temporarily halted the plan to remain in effect. The appellate decision followed a federal judge in Missouri <a href="https://missouriindependent.com/2024/06/25/federal-rulings-out-of-kansas-missouri-put-biden-student-loan-forgiveness-on-hold/" target="_blank">issuing a preliminary injunction</a> blocking the plan in late June.</p>
<p>In its decision, the nation’s highest court said it expects the 8th Circuit to “render its decision with appropriate dispatch.”</p>
<p>Missouri Attorney General Andrew Bailey praised the Supreme Court’s decision in a <a href="https://ago.mo.gov/supreme-court-upholds-attorney-general-baileys-court-order-blocking-biden-harris-student-loan-scheme/" target="_blank">statement</a> Wednesday, calling it a “huge win for every American who still believes in paying their own way.”</p>
<p>On the other hand, a spokesperson for the U.S. Department of Education said “we are disappointed in this decision, particularly because lifting the injunction would have allowed for lower payments and other benefits for borrowers across the country,” per a statement shared with States Newsroom.</p>
<p>The spokesperson said the department “will work to minimize further harm and disruption to borrowers as we await a final decision from the Eighth Circuit,” adding that “the Biden-Harris Administration remains committed to supporting borrowers and will continue to fight for the most affordable repayment options for millions of people across the country.”</p>
<p>In a statement, Mike Pierce, executive director of the Student Borrower Protection Center, said “in rejecting this appeal, the Supreme Court perpetuates the 8th Circuit’s bogus legal fiction that pausing affordable payments is ‘preserving the status quo.’”</p>
<p>“This is ludicrous. Millions of people were repaying their student loans. Now they are in limbo,” Pierce added.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Kansas, Alabama, Alaska, Idaho, Iowa, Louisiana, Montana, Nebraska, South Carolina, Texas and Utah also <a href="https://kansasreflector.com/2024/03/28/kobach-files-lawsuit-challenging-bidens-latest-effort-to-diminish-college-student-loan-debt/" target="_blank">filed a lawsuit over the plan</a> in March.</p>
<p>A federal judge in Kansas dismissed eight of those states — allowing only Alaska, South Carolina and Texas to move forward with their challenge — and issued a preliminary injunction.</p>
<p>In late June, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 10th Circuit allowed parts of the SAVE plan to go forward — forcing Alaska, South Carolina and Texas to <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/24/24A11/316401/20240705173618326_Alaska%20v%20Cardona%20Application%20to%20Vacate%20Stay%20final.pdf" target="_blank">file an emergency request</a> to the Supreme Court to vacate the stay.</p>
<p>But the Supreme Court rejected this attempt from the states’ attorneys general on Wednesday, saying that “applicants represent that they do not require emergency relief from this Court as long as the Eighth Circuit’s injunction … is in place.”</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. House Dems ask OSHA to respond to reports that state agencies tipped off employers</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/08/21/u-s-house-dems-ask-osha-to-respond-to-reports-that-state-agencies-tipped-off-employers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 09:30:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Acting Labor Secretary Julie Su]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[House Committee on Education and the Workforce]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSHA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rep. Alma Adams]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US Rep. Bobby Scott]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39738</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — Leading Democrats on the House Committee on Education and the Workforce and its Workforce Protection Subcommittee demanded answers on Tuesday from Acting Labor Secretary Julie Su regarding allegations that certain state Occupational Safety and Health Administration agencies possibly misused federal funds and gave advance notice to employers of workplace safety inspections. The letter [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="680" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/labor-bldg-1024x680.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/labor-bldg-1024x680.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/labor-bldg-300x199.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/labor-bldg-768x510.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/labor-bldg.jpeg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Frances Perkins Building in Washington, D.C., the headquarters of the U.S. Department of Labor. (Official Department of Labor photograph)</p><p>WASHINGTON — Leading Democrats on the House Committee on Education and the Workforce and its Workforce Protection Subcommittee demanded answers on Tuesday from Acting Labor Secretary Julie Su regarding allegations that certain state <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/sen-jerry-moran-says-proposed-osha-rules-threaten-kansas-volunteer-fire-agencies" target="_blank">Occupational Safety and Health Administration</a> agencies possibly misused federal funds and gave advance notice to employers of workplace safety inspections.</p>
<figure id="attachment_39740" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:362px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=39740" rel="attachment wp-att-39740"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-39740" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Rep.-Bobby-Scott-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="362" height="241" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Rep.-Bobby-Scott-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Rep.-Bobby-Scott-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Rep.-Bobby-Scott-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Rep.-Bobby-Scott-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Rep.-Bobby-Scott-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 362px) 100vw, 362px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Rep. Bobby Scott (D-VA), ranking member of the House Committee on Education and Workforce. (Photo by Toya Sarno Jordan/Getty Images)</p></figure>
<p>The letter from the <a href="https://democrats-edworkforce.house.gov/imo/media/doc/osha_state_plan_letter_by_scott_adams.pdf" target="_blank">respective ranking members</a> of the committee and subcommittee — Reps. Bobby Scott of Virginia and Alma Adams of North Carolina — came in response to recent news reports over allegations surrounding the state OSHA agencies and employers in California and South Carolina.</p>
<p>“Workers deserve to be protected, not exploited,” Scott and Adams said in a statement Tuesday.</p>
<p>“If these allegations are true, it means that our federal funds, meant to ensure safe and fair workplaces, might be enabling exactly the opposite,” the two said, adding that it’s “crucial that we get to the bottom of this and hold those responsible accountable.”</p>
<p>Scott and Adams highlighted a February report from <a href="https://calmatters.org/politics/capitol/2024/02/california-farmworkers-safety/" target="_blank">Cal Matters</a> documenting allegations that staff from the California Division of Occupational Safety and Health might be tipping off employers about when inspections are going to occur.</p>
<p>Debra Lee, <a href="https://www.gov.ca.gov/2024/06/06/governor-newsom-announces-appointments-6-6-24/" target="_blank">chief of the state agency</a> who was acting chief at the time of the report, expressed concerns about these allegations and wanted the agency to be informed in order to take appropriate action, according to Cal Matters.</p>
<p>The lawmakers also underscored a series of reports from <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2023/12/14/us/roofing-children-immigrants.html?partner=slack&amp;smid=sl-share" target="_blank">The New York Times</a> on migrant children working dangerous jobs upon coming to the United States, including a story that sheds light on the dangers for those in roofing — <a href="https://www.dol.gov/sites/dolgov/files/WHD/legacy/files/CL_Roofing.pdf" target="_blank">a job that is illegal</a> under the age of 18.</p>
<p>Scott and Adams pointed to the Times’ interview with a crew boss who reportedly “admitted violations of not only federal child labor rules but also OSHA standards that are notionally enforced by South Carolina’s state plan agency.”</p>
<p>The two called this account “particularly alarming,” writing in their letter that “if the employer in this news account is to be believed, this story raises questions not only about South Carolina’s compliance with the OSH Act’s requirements for state plan enforcement but also about the possibility of federal funds being used to help employers evade detection for child labor trafficking and oppressive child labor violations.”</p>
<p>Holly Beeson, counsel to the Office of Communications and Governmental Affairs at the South Carolina Department of Labor, Licensing and Regulation, told States Newsroom that “whenever a hazard or lack of compliance with an OSHA standard is reported, SC OSHA vets the complaint to determine whether an inspection should follow.”</p>
<p>“Both state and federal law prohibit prior notification of this inspection to an employer, and SC OSHA strictly adheres to this legal mandate,” Beeson said.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Worker safety</h4>

	
<p>The Occupational Safety and Health Administration — part of the Department of Labor — was created through the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970. The agency is tasked with <a href="https://www.osha.gov/aboutosha" target="_blank">ensuring that workers</a> have “safe and healthful working conditions free from unlawful retaliation.”</p>
<p>Several states, including California and South Carolina, have their own <a href="https://www.osha.gov/stateplans" target="_blank">OSHA-approved state plan</a>.</p>
<p>As <a href="https://www.osha.gov/stateplans/faqs" target="_blank">the agency</a> notes, “OSHA covers most private sector employers and workers in all 50 states, the District of Columbia, and the other United States (U.S.) jurisdictions — either directly through OSHA or through an OSHA-approved State Plan.”</p>
<p>Scott and Adams are asking for a response from the Department of Labor by Sept. 20 regarding questions such as how they would address any allegations of unlawful advance notice of inspections and challenges facing the department when trying to monitor and enforce state plans’ compliance with the Occupational Safety and Health Act.</p>
<p>The Department of Labor’s Occupational Safety and Health Administration did not respond to a request for comment by time of publication on Tuesday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What to know about Vice President Kamala Harris, endorsed by Biden as his successor</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/07/22/what-to-know-about-vice-president-kamala-harris-endorsed-by-biden-as-his-successor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 09:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice President Kamala Harris]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39365</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — President Joe Biden on Sunday endorsed Vice President Kamala Harris to be the new Democratic presidential nominee, passing the torch to the California native who has helmed administration initiatives on reproductive rights and gun control. A former U.S. senator from California who vied for her party’s presidential nomination in the 2020 primaries, Harris, 59, would [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="682" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/KHarris-scaled-1-1024x682.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/KHarris-scaled-1-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/KHarris-scaled-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/KHarris-scaled-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/KHarris-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/KHarris-scaled-1-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">U.S. Vice President Kamala Harris attends a moderated conversation with former Trump administration national security official Olivia Troye and former Republican voter Amanda Stratton on July 17, 2024 in Kalamazoo, Michigan. (Photo by Chris duMond/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — President Joe Biden on Sunday endorsed <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/vice-president-kamala-harris-comes-philadelphia-court-asian-american-voters" target="_blank">Vice President Kamala Harris</a> to be the new Democratic presidential nominee, passing the torch to the California native who has helmed administration initiatives on reproductive rights and gun control.</p>
<p>A former U.S. senator from California who vied for her party’s presidential nomination in the 2020 primaries, Harris, 59, would represent a new generation at the top of the ticket after Biden, 81, withdrew from the race under pressure from Democratic leaders following a disastrous late June debate performance.</p>
<p>Harris, the nation’s first woman vice president, now has a chance to become the first woman president, depending on what Democrats decide. She is also the first Black vice president and first person of South Asian descent to serve as vice president.</p>
<p>Some in the party publicly floated her as a potential replacement for Biden following the debate. Biden initially refused to <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/democratic-calls-new-nominee-ramp-biden-camp-pledges-stay-course" target="_blank">end his reelection bid</a> despite a growing number of calls within the Democratic Party for him to step aside. He bowed out on Sunday.</p>
<p>“Today I want to offer my full support and endorsement for Kamala to be the nominee of our party this year. Democrats — it’s time to come together and beat Trump. Let’s do this,” Biden said in a Sunday post on <a href="https://x.com/JoeBiden/status/1815087772216303933" target="_blank">X</a>.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Policy initiatives </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>During her time as vice president, Harris became a leading voice in the administration’s fight for reproductive rights and abortion access — often seen as Democrats’ strongest issue since the U.S. Supreme Court overturned Roe v. Wade in June 2022, which ended nearly half a century of the federal constitutional right to abortion.</p>
<p>Harris launched a <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2023/12/19/vice-president-kamala-harris-launches-reproductive-freedoms-tour/" target="_blank">“Fight for Reproductive Freedoms”</a> tour in early 2024, bringing her to several swing states. And after touring a <a href="https://minnesotareformer.com/2024/03/14/vp-harris-promotes-abortion-access-in-historic-visit-to-minnesota-planned-parenthood/" target="_blank">Planned Parenthood</a> clinic in Minnesota, Harris was believed to be the first sitting president or vice president to tour an abortion clinic.</p>
<p>Harris has also focused on gun safety throughout her vice presidential tenure. She announced the launch of the National Extreme Risk Protection Order Resource Center in March to assist states, local governments and others in “optimizing the usage of red flag laws,” according to the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2024/03/23/fact-sheet-vice-president-harris-announces-gun-safety-solutions-while-continuing-efforts-to-keep-schools-safe-from-gun-violence/" target="_blank">White House</a>.</p>
<p>She also called on states to pass so-called red flag laws — which <a href="https://stateline.org/2022/06/27/states-want-to-make-it-easier-to-use-red-flag-laws/" target="_blank">enable law enforcement</a> to petition civil courts to take away firearms from those who could pose a danger to themselves or others — and use Bipartisan Safer Communities Act funding to “to help implement laws already enacted.”</p>
<p>The administration championed the <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/senate-bill/2938" target="_blank">Bipartisan Safer Communities Act</a>, which Biden signed into law in June 2022. The measure was regarded as the most comprehensive <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/congress-sends-biden-historic-gun-safety-legislation-gop-support%C2%A0" target="_blank">federal gun safety legislation</a> in almost 30 years.</p>
<p>She’s also been a sharp opponent, alongside Biden and other Democrats, of <a href="https://static.project2025.org/2025_MandateForLeadership_FULL.pdf" target="_blank">Project 2025</a> — the nearly 900-page document from the Heritage Foundation that proposes a sweeping conservative agenda if former President Donald J. Trump is elected. Though Trump has <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/article/project-2025.html" target="_blank">distanced himself from the platform</a>, some former members of his administration helped write it.</p>
<p>Harris has also <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/despite-poor-polling-numbers-kamala-harris-viewed-key-democrats-2024-0" target="_blank">drawn criticism</a> on both sides of the aisle for her efforts surrounding immigration. Biden <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2021/07/29/fact-sheet-strategy-to-address-the-root-causes-of-migration-in-central-america/" target="_blank">tapped her in 2021</a> to help address the “root causes” of migration in Central America.</p>
<p>She visited the <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/06/25/kamala-harris-texas-mexico-border-immigration/" target="_blank">U.S.-Mexico border</a> in June 2021 after making stops in Guatemala and Mexico earlier that month, the first international trip for her as vice president.</p>
<p>Republicans have repeatedly called her a “border czar” despite her focus being on migration’s “root causes” in Central American countries.</p>
<p>During the Republican National Convention in Milwaukee, Rep. Matt Gaetz of Florida was one of several speakers who dubbed her a “border czar,” adding the barb that “appointing Kamala Harris to oversee the border is like appointing Bernie Madoff to oversee your retirement plan.”</p>
<p>Harris also holds the record for the highest number of <a href="https://www.senate.gov/legislative/TieVotes.htm" target="_blank">tie-breaking votes</a> cast in the U.S. Senate.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Public polling and perception</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>Since the fallout from the June 27 debate, a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/07/09/biden-clinton-harris-democrat-poll-00166937" target="_blank">slew of polls</a> have offered mixed outcomes as to whether <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2024/07/11/poll-biden-drop-out-election/" target="_blank">voters would choose Harris</a> over Trump if the two were up against each other.</p>
<p>An <a href="https://d3nkl3psvxxpe9.cloudfront.net/documents/econTabReport_sPu9WiO.pdf" target="_blank">Economist/YouGov poll</a> conducted July 13-16 shows both <a href="https://today.yougov.com/politics/articles/50102-trump-lead-biden-age-harris-vance-conventions-july-13-16-2024-economist-yougov-poll" target="_blank">Harris and Biden</a> narrowly behind Trump, with Biden performing slightly better than Harris.</p>
<p>Only 39% said they would choose Harris, compared to 44% who would vote for Trump. Similarly, 41% said they would vote for Biden, compared to 43% choosing Trump.</p>
<p>As of mid-July, her <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/approval/kamala-harris/" target="_blank">approval ratings</a> also appeared dim, with 50.4% of Americans disapproving of her and 38.6% approving.</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">California background</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>Prior to serving as vice president, Harris was a U.S. senator from California from 2017 to 2021. With a long career in law enforcement, she served as the attorney general of California and was also the district attorney of San Francisco.</p>
<p>Harris vied for the Democratic nomination in the 2020 presidential election before ultimately withdrawing her candidacy months later and subsequently endorsing Biden. She dropped out prior to the Iowa caucuses, ending her bid in December 2019, despite being initially viewed as a top Democratic contender.</p>
<p>She was born in Oakland, California, in 1964 to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2020/08/11/kamala-harris-vp-background-bio-biden-running-mate-2020-393885" target="_blank">immigrant parents</a>. She is married to Doug Emhoff, who is the first Jewish spouse of either a U.S. president or vice president, according to the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/douglas-emhoff/" target="_blank">White House</a>. He’s also the first second gentleman in U.S. history. Harris is an alumna of <a href="https://thedig.howard.edu/featured-people/kamala-harris" target="_blank">Howard University</a>, a historically Black institution, and received her law degree from the University of California, Hastings.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GOP plan to reverse final Title IX rule passes U.S. House, but Biden says he’d veto  </title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/07/11/gop-plan-to-reverse-final-title-ix-rule-passes-u-s-house-but-biden-says-hed-veto/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 21:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39258</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The U.S. House on Thursday passed a measure to reverse an Education Department rule seeking to extend federal discrimination protections for LGBTQ students, though President Joe Biden has vowed to veto the legislation should it land on his desk. House passage of the resolution on a party-line vote, 210-205, is part of a [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/CapitolSteps-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/CapitolSteps-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/CapitolSteps-scaled-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/CapitolSteps-scaled-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/CapitolSteps-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/CapitolSteps-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The U.S. Capitol in Washington, D.C., is pictured on Thursday, March 14, 2024. (Photo by Jennifer Shutt)</p><p>WASHINGTON — The U.S. House on Thursday passed a measure to reverse an Education Department rule seeking to extend federal discrimination protections for LGBTQ students, though President Joe Biden has vowed to veto the legislation should it land on his desk.</p>
<p>House passage of the resolution on a party-line vote, <a href="https://clerk.house.gov/Votes/2024354?Page=2" target="_blank">210-205</a>, is part of a barrage of GOP pushback at the state and federal levels to the <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/house-speaker-johnson-betsy-devos-lead-attack-title-ix-rule-protects-lgbtq-kids" target="_blank">Biden administration’s final rule for Title IX</a> since its April release. For all schools that receive federal funding, the rule protects against discrimination for students based on “sex stereotypes, sexual orientation, gender identity, and sex characteristics.”</p>
<p>Twenty-six states with GOP attorneys general have <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/more-half-states-sue-block-biden-title-ix-rule-protecting-lgbtq-students" target="_blank">sued to block</a> the rule, and courts have temporarily blocked it from going into effect in 14 states on August 1.</p>
<p>The 14 states with temporary blocks are: Alaska, Idaho, Indiana, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Mississippi, Montana, Ohio, Tennessee, Utah, Virginia, West Virginia and Wyoming.</p>
<p>Illinois GOP Rep. Mary Miller <a href="https://www.newsfromthestates.com/article/biden-title-ix-regulation-targeted-republicans-congress" target="_blank">introduced the legislation</a> in early June. A week later, the Republican-controlled House Committee on Education and the Workforce approved it. Miller’s resolution seeks to reverse the rule through the <a href="https://crsreports.congress.gov/product/pdf/IF/IF10023" target="_blank">Congressional Review Act</a>, a procedural tool Congress can use to overturn certain actions from federal agencies.</p>
<p>In the Senate, Mississippi Republican Cindy Hyde-Smith <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/senate-joint-resolution/96" target="_blank">also introduced legislation</a> in June to try to block the final rule under the same tool. The Senate version has gathered over 30 Republican cosponsors.</p>
<p>Rep. Virginia Foxx — chairwoman of the House Committee on Education and the Workforce and a fierce opponent of the administration’s final rule — said during the floor debate Wednesday that she wanted to preserve Title IX, which helped equalize funding for women’s sports and education programs beginning in 1972.</p>
<p>“Title IX ushered in a golden era for women’s competition and education,” the North Carolina Republican said. “There is sanctity in the community and tradition of these memories, these spaces and these opportunities for young girls.”</p>
<p>Regardless of whether the attempt to roll back the measure is successful in the Democratic-controlled Senate, <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/SAP-HJRes-165.pdf" target="_blank">Biden</a>’s veto threat leaves virtually no possibility it could be adopted this year.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Democrats, LGBTQ advocates in opposition </h4>

	
<p>Democrats and LGBTQ advocates have described the effort to overturn the rule as motivated by misinformation and fear.</p>
<p>“Unfortunately, this resolution has been clouded by misinformation, unfounded fears and with some, just hatred of transgender individuals,” said Rep. Bobby Scott, a Virginia Democrat and ranking member of the House Committee on Education and the Workforce, during the debate.</p>
<p>Oregon’s Rep. Suzanne Bonamici — ranking member of the House Subcommittee on Early Childhood, Elementary, and Secondary Education — said the resolution was “another attempt to undercut this administration’s efforts to empower survivors and protect all Americans from discrimination.”</p>
<p>“If Republicans truly cared about protecting women and children, they would stop this prejudiced rhetoric and take action on bills that would actually protect women from discrimination and harassment and defend women’s reproductive health care, make child care more affordable, preserve opportunities in workplaces for all parents, especially women,” Bonamici said.</p>
<p>Scott called on the House to “reject these narratives and focus on real issues of safety and equity.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Final rule blocked in more states </h4>

	
<p>Meanwhile, challenges to the rule are playing out in a handful of federal courts.</p>
<p>Last week, Judge John Broomes of the U.S. District Court for the District of Kansas temporarily blocked the measure from taking effect in the Sunflower State, along with Alaska, Utah and Wyoming.</p>
<p>Broomes also halted the rule from taking effect in “the schools attended by the members of Young America’s Foundation or Female Athletes United, as well as the schools attended by the children of the members of Moms for Liberty,” all groups that sued alongside the four states, per the <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.ksd.152561/gov.uscourts.ksd.152561.53.0.pdf" target="_blank">order</a>.</p>
<p>Under Broomes’ order, the rule is also halted in an Oklahoma public school attended by a minor who is one of the plaintiffs.</p>
<p>In June, U.S. District Judge Terry Doughty of Louisiana <a href="https://lailluminator.com/2024/06/13/title-ix-transgender/" target="_blank">issued a temporary injunction</a> barring the final rule from taking effect there, along with Idaho, Mississippi and Montana.</p>
<p>In Kentucky federal court, Chief Judge Danny Reeves <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/2024/06/17/us-judge-in-kentucky-blocks-biden-title-ix-rules-says-sex-gender-identity-not-the-same-thing/" target="_blank">temporarily blocked the final rule</a> in the Bluegrass State, plus Tennessee, Ohio, Indiana, West Virginia and Virginia. Reeves rejected the department’s request for a partial stay of the injunction while its appeal plays out, per a <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.kyed.104801/gov.uscourts.kyed.104801.117.0.pdf" target="_blank">Wednesday court filing</a>.</p>
<p>The Education Department has confirmed it is appealing the other two rulings but did not have an update Wednesday on whether it is filing a notice of appeal on the most recent ruling in the Kansas federal court.</p>
<p>The spokesperson reiterated earlier this week that the agency has “asked the trial courts to allow the bulk of the final rule to take effect in these states as scheduled, on August 1, while the appeals are pending.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">LGBTQ advocacy groups push back on GOP effort</h4>

	
<p>Allen Morris, policy director for the advocacy group National LGBTQ Task Force, said the vote was part of a pattern of anti-LGBTQ policy measures.</p>
<p>“When you look at the rise in hatred and the rise in violence and the rise of young LGBTQ individuals not having the support that they need, where suicide rates are high, it is disappointing to see our opposition go against us with such a high level of intention,” he said.</p>
<p>Morris told States Newsroom that “a lot of what is happening with this extremism is not founded in truth.”</p>
<p>“It is founded in ways to spew hate and to spew fear. It is a lot of fear mongering, and it’s anything to make people feel like their backs are up against the wall, or as if they don’t have the power,” he said.</p>
<p>Echoing a previous statement, a spokesperson for the Department of Education said it “does not comment on pending legislation” and emphasized that all schools receiving federal funding are obligated to comply with the new regulations as a condition of receiving those funds.</p>
<p>The department has yet to finalize a separate rule establishing new criteria for transgender athletes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Don’t give up on the FAFSA, advocates for student financial aid urge</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/24/dont-give-up-on-the-fafsa-advocates-for-student-financial-aid-urge/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 09:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[college]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fafsa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US Department of Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia Alternative State Aid (VASA)]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39027</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — Though the new version of the form to apply for federal financial student aid has had its fair share of highly publicized hiccups, U.S. Under Secretary of Education James Kvaal says the department has made a lot of progress in the past couple of months. The Free Application for Federal Student Aid — [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/graduationcap-scaled-1-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/graduationcap-scaled-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/graduationcap-scaled-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/graduationcap-scaled-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/graduationcap-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/graduationcap-scaled-1-2048x1366.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The number of federal student financial aid forms filed by graduating high school seniors is down compared to last year, after glitches and technical errors plagued the process. (Photo by sdominick/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — Though the new version of the form to apply for federal financial student aid has had its fair share of highly publicized hiccups, U.S. Under Secretary of Education James Kvaal says the department has made a lot of progress in the past couple of months.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://studentaid.gov/help/fafsa" target="_blank">Free Application for Federal Student Aid</a> — better known as FAFSA — got a makeover after Congress passed the <a href="https://studentaid.gov/help-center/answers/article/fafsa-simplification-act" target="_blank">FAFSA Simplification Act</a> in late 2020. But users faced glitches and technical errors during the Dec. 30 soft launch and past the Jan. 8 official debut for the 2024-25 form, which covers the upcoming school year.</p>
<p>Advocates voiced concerns over the form’s failure to <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2024/01/24/politics/fafsa-inflation-fix-income/index.html" target="_blank">adjust for inflation</a>, its <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/miscalculation-in-fafsa-formula-is-another-unforced-error" target="_blank">formula miscalculation</a> and its <a href="https://fsapartners.ed.gov/knowledge-center/library/electronic-announcements/2024-04-01/update-tax-data-received-fa-ddx-and-manually-entered-information" target="_blank">tax data errors</a>, prompting processing delays the department has worked to fix. The federal agency has also taken steps to address major issues that prevented parents without Social Security numbers from completing the form.</p>
<p>“We’re fixing things at a rapid pace, and we’ve been keeping the community updated. We have an <a href="https://fsapartners.ed.gov/knowledge-center/topics/fafsa-simplification-information/2024-25-fafsa-issue-alerts" target="_blank">issues guide</a> on the website that lets people know the problems we’re aware of and what the potential solutions are. In almost every case now, there is a way for students to submit the form,” Kvaal told States Newsroom in an interview.</p>
<p>“It may be a customer service experience that is not what we originally designed, and so we’re gonna continue to try and make this process easier and faster for all students, including those whose parents may not have Social Security numbers, but it is possible now for everyone to submit a FAFSA,” Kvaal said.</p>
<p>He oversees higher education and financial aid, including the Office of Federal Student Aid, which is the largest student financial aid provider in the country.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">More than 11 million FAFSA submissions</h4>

	
<p>Kvaal said the department has already received more than 11 million FAFSA submissions for the 2024-25 school year.</p>
<p>Last week, the <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/us-department-education-announces-jeremy-singer-fafsa-executive-advisor-office-federal-student-aid" target="_blank">department said</a> it has made “significant progress” in closing the gap in FAFSA submissions to an 8% decrease compared to this time last year, down from a nearly 40% decrease in March.</p>
<p>For both undergraduate and graduate students, the FAFSA form is a key indicator for financial aid eligibility, which comes in the form of grants, loans, work-study funds and scholarships.</p>
<p>The form is also not exclusive to first-year college students, and those already enrolled <a href="https://studentaid.gov/apply-for-aid/fafsa/renew" target="_blank">must renew their application</a> each academic year.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">&#8216;It’s still not perfect for all applicants&#8217; </h4>

	
<p>Though the department has made progress to address major known issues, “the system, certainly six months after it opened, is still not a totally functioning system,” said MorraLee Keller, senior director of strategic programming at the National College Attainment Network, a nonprofit membership and advocacy organization.</p>
<p>“Right now, the form is working for a lot of applicants, but it’s still not perfect for all applicants,” she added.</p>
<p>The organization <a href="https://www.ncan.org/page/fafsatracker" target="_blank">monitors FAFSA completion</a> for graduating high school seniors nationally and compares those figures to the previous school year. Keller said “one thing that we’re seeing is the class of &#8217;24, at this point in time, is almost 13 percentage points behind in the rate at which the seniors have filed a FAFSA” this past academic year.</p>
<p>“We are significantly behind in the number of FAFSAs, particularly for our graduating seniors, so that is ultimately probably going to have an impact in enrollment because completing a FAFSA is a pretty good indicator about whether you plan to enroll in college this fall,” Keller said.</p>
<p>Tennessee, Louisiana, Illinois, Washington, D.C., and Texas have the highest percentages of high school seniors completing the FAFSA form, according to NCAN’s tracker. Nevada, Florida, Arizona, Utah and Alaska have the lowest percentages. In Virginia, 44% of seniors — or 45,850, down from 51,597 last year — have completed the FAFSA.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Kvaal said he thinks “it’s important to note that just about everybody can get their FAFSA through the process now.” He added that “there are some specific instructions that people in certain situations need to follow carefully” and encouraged applicants to pay careful attention to the instructions and help hints.</p>
<p>“The FAFSA is broadly available, and it’s not accurate to say that there are students who can’t get through them,” he said.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">New strategy</h4>

	
<p>In early May, the federal agency launched the <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/us-department-education-launches-next-phase-fafsa-support-strategy-boost-completion-rate-among-high-school-students" target="_blank">FAFSA Student Support Strategy</a>, which has now provided more than “$30 million in funding and counting and has reached more than 180 organizations across the country” in an attempt to get more students to complete the form, according to the <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/us-department-education-announces-jeremy-singer-fafsa-executive-advisor-office-federal-student-aid" target="_blank">department</a>.</p>
<p>The department also recently announced that Jeremy Singer, current president of the College Board, would serve as the new FAFSA executive adviser.</p>
<p>In late May, U.S. Education Secretary Miguel Cardona said the department has <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/secretary-cardona-outlines-steps-modernizing-office-federal-student-aid" target="_blank">taken steps</a> aimed at “modernizing” the Office of Federal Student Aid, including the department’s search for a new chief operating officer, per a <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/secretary-cardona-outlines-steps-modernizing-office-federal-student-aid" target="_blank">news release</a>. That person would replace <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/education/2024/04/26/richard-cordray-federal-student-aid/" target="_blank">Richard Cordray</a>, who, in the midst of backlash and criticism toward the department over the botched rollout, said in April he would depart.</p>
<p>Part of the department’s efforts, Cardona said, include conducting a “full-scale review” of the Office of Federal Student Aid’s “current and historical organization, management, staffing, workflow structures, business processes, and operations” and hiring an independent consulting firm.</p>
<p>The department is also reviewing “contracts and acquisition procedures” in an effort to hold vendors accountable, Cardona said.</p>
<p><strong>If I haven’t filled out the 2024-25 FAFSA form, what should I do? </strong></p>
<p>Though students have until <a href="https://studentaid.gov/apply-for-aid/fafsa/fafsa-deadlines" target="_blank">June 30, 2025,</a> to complete the 2024-25 FAFSA form, deadlines vary based on individual colleges and states. (Many colleges, including those in Virginia, have priority deadlines, meaning you&#8217;ll need to meet those to get the best chance at financial aid. Virginia students who are not eligible for FAFSA may qualify for <a tabindex="0" href="https://www.schev.edu/financial-aid/financial-aid/federal-state-financial-aid/vasa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Virginia Alternative State Aid, or VASA.)</a></p>
<p>Kvaal encouraged anyone considering college this fall to visit <a href="http://studentaid.gov" target="_blank">Studentaid.gov</a> and fill out the FAFSA as soon as possible.</p>
<p>“If you had been hearing that there were challenges with the form or people were encountering obstacles, we’ve made a lot of progress in making the form work in recent weeks, and most people, their form is getting through in one to three days, and we’re sending information to colleges that they need to make financial aid offers,” he said.</p>
<p>Keller also encouraged families to not give up on completing the form.</p>
<p>“The time is not gone — get your FAFSA filed this summer if you want to go to school this fall,” she said.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Extremely low pay’ cited at U.S. Senate hearing as prime reason for teacher shortage</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/06/20/extremely-low-pay-cited-at-u-s-senate-hearing-as-prime-reason-for-teacher-shortage/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 22:02:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blueprint for Marland's Future]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heritage Foundation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parents Defending Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[teacher pay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[teacher shortage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US Sen. Bernie Sanders]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=39013</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — The only reason John Arthur is able to be a public school teacher is because his wife makes much more money than he does. Arthur —  the 2021 Utah Teacher of the Year  — testified on Thursday at a hearing in the U.S. Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions on the [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="577" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/JohnArthur-1024x577.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/JohnArthur-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/JohnArthur-300x169.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/JohnArthur-768x433.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/JohnArthur-1536x866.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/JohnArthur-2048x1155.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">John Arthur, a teacher at Meadowlark Elementary in Salt Lake City, Utah, testified before the Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee in Washington, D.C., on Thursday, June 20, 2024. (Screenshot from committee webcast)</p><p>WASHINGTON — The only reason John Arthur is able to be a public school teacher is because his wife makes much more money than he does.</p>
<p>Arthur —  the 2021 Utah Teacher of the Year  — testified on Thursday at a hearing in the U.S. Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions on the challenges facing public school teachers.</p>
<p>Arthur, who is also a member of the National Education Association and holds National Board Certification, pointed to pay as the main reason for both teachers leaving the profession and parents not wanting their children to become teachers.</p>
<p>“The No. 1 solution to addressing the issues we face must be increasing teachers’ salaries,” said Arthur, who teaches at Meadowlark Elementary School in Salt Lake City, Utah.</p>
<p>Gemayel Keyes, a teacher at Gilbert Spruance Elementary School in Philadelphia, told the committee that even as an educator, he still has an additional part-time job.</p>
<p>The special education teacher spent most of his career in education as a paraprofessional. At the time he moved into that role, the starting annual salary was $16,000 and the maximum was $30,000.</p>
<p>“It’s still pretty much the same,” he said.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Minimum teacher salary </h4>

	
<p>Committee Chairman Bernie Sanders, a Vermont independent, <a href="https://www.sanders.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/03.09.23-Sanders-Pay-Teachers-Act-text.pdf" target="_blank">introduced a bill</a> in March 2023 that would set an <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/118th-congress/senate-bill/766/all-actions" target="_blank">annual base salary</a> of $60,000 for public elementary and secondary school teachers.</p>
<p>“We understand that the children, young people of this country, are our future and there is, in fact … nothing more important that we can do to provide a quality education to all of our young people, and yet, for decades, public school teachers have been overworked, underpaid, understaffed, and maybe most importantly, underappreciated,” Sanders said in his opening remarks.</p>
<p>“Compared to many other occupations, our public school teachers are more likely to experience high levels of anxiety, stress and burnout, which was only exacerbated by the pandemic,” he said.</p>
<p>Sanders said 44% of public school teachers are quitting their profession within five years, citing “the extremely low pay teachers receive” as one of the primary reasons for a massive U.S. teacher shortage.</p>
<p>For the 2023-24 school year, a whopping 86% of K-12 public schools in the country documented challenges in hiring teachers, according to an October report from the <a href="https://nces.ed.gov/whatsnew/press_releases/10_17_2023.asp" target="_blank">National Center for Education Statistics</a>.</p>
<p>In Virginia, where the <a href="https://www.nea.org/resource-library/educator-pay-and-student-spending-how-does-your-state-rank?utm_medium=paid-search&amp;utm_source=google&amp;utm_campaign=rankings-estimates-report&amp;utm_content=&amp;ms=ads-rankings-estimates-report-se&amp;gad_source=1&amp;gclid=Cj0KCQjw0MexBhD3ARIsAEI3WHLwd8Qv-rHoH2JAUdRK2yLx0JOW7PQuh_NVgkB-n_mqchU8BZSoYAAaAi8SEALw_wcB&amp;gclsrc=aw.ds" target="_blank">average teacher pay is $63,103</a>, there were roughly <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/01/17/legislation-to-bring-va-teacher-pay-to-national-average-gets-bipartisan-support/">3,600 vacancies in 2023</a>, according to Virginia Department of Education. The state&#8217;s new two-year budget provides for a 3% increase in teacher&#8217;s salaries.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Maryland sets $60,000 minimum </h4>

	
<p>But a minimum annual teacher salary of $60,000 is not far off for every state.</p>
<p>In Maryland, the <a href="https://marylandmatters.org/2024/06/03/blueprint-blues-local-leaders-cite-school-reform-plans-progress-problems/" target="_blank">Blueprint for Maryland’s Future</a> raises the starting salary for teachers to $60,000 a year by July 2026.</p>
<p>William E. Kirwan, vice chair of Maryland’s Accountability and Implementation Board, said the multi-year comprehensive plan, passed in 2021 in the Maryland General Assembly, “addresses all aspects of children’s education from birth to high school completion, including most especially, the recruitment, retention and compensation of high quality teachers.”</p>
<p>Kirwan said the “Blueprint’s principle for teacher compensation is that, as professionals, teachers should be compensated at the same level as other professionals requiring similar levels of education, such as architects and CPAs.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">An &#8216;allocation issue&#8217;</h4>

	
<p>Sen. Bill Cassidy, ranking member of the committee, dubbed Democrats’ solution of creating a federal minimum salary for teachers as a “laudable goal.”</p>
<p>But he noted that “the federal government dictating how states spend their money does not address the root cause of why teachers are struggling to teach in the classroom.”</p>
<p>“More mandates and funding cannot be the only answer we come up with. We must examine broken policies that got us here and find solutions to improve,” the Louisiana Republican said.</p>
<p>Nicole Neily, president and founder of Parents Defending Education, a parents’ rights group, argued that “schools don’t have a resource issue” but rather an “allocation issue.”</p>
<p>“There’s a saying: ‘Don’t tell me where your priorities are, show me where you spend your money, and I’ll tell you what they are.’ Education leaders routinely choose to spend money on programs and personnel that don’t directly benefit students,” said Neily.</p>
<p>Neily pointed to a 2021 report from the <a href="https://www.heritage.org/education/report/equity-elementary-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-staff-public-schools" target="_blank">Heritage Foundation</a>, which found that “standardized test results show that achievement gaps are growing wider over time in districts with (chief diversity officers).” Such staff members commonly encourage efforts at diversity, equity and inclusion in schools.</p>
<p>Robert Pondiscio, a senior fellow at the conservative-leaning American Enterprise Institute, said “higher pay does not ease the burden we place on teachers or add hours to their day.”</p>
<p>“By all means, raise teacher pay, but do not assume that it will solve teacher shortages or keep good teachers in the classroom. Poor training, deteriorating classroom conditions, shoddy curriculum and spiraling demands have made an already challenging job nearly impossible to do well and sustainably,” he added.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Funds for clean school buses coming to hundreds of districts, White House says</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/30/funds-for-clean-school-buses-coming-to-hundreds-of-districts-white-house-says/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 09:49:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Environmental Protection Agency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EPA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President Joe Biden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virginia schools]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=38806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — As part of its ongoing effort to replace diesel-fueled school buses, the Biden administration on Wednesday said it will provide approximately 530 school districts across nearly all states with almost $1 billion to help them purchase clean school buses. The initiative, part of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s Clean School Bus Program rebate [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/electricschoolbus-scaled-1-1024x683.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/electricschoolbus-scaled-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/electricschoolbus-scaled-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/electricschoolbus-scaled-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/electricschoolbus-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpeg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/electricschoolbus-scaled-1-2048x1366.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">The Biden administration on Wednesday said it will provide funding to help school districts purchase clean school buses, most of them electric. Shown is a yellow electric school bus plugged into a charging station. (Photo by TW Farlow/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — As part of its ongoing effort to replace diesel-fueled school buses, the Biden administration on Wednesday said it will provide approximately 530 school districts across nearly all states with almost $1 billion to help them purchase clean school buses.</p>
<p>The initiative, part of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s Clean School Bus Program rebate competition, will give funds to school districts in 47 states and the District of Columbia to help them buy over 3,400 clean school buses. Alaska, Hawaii and Nevada are not part of this round of funding.</p>
	<div class="newsroomSidebarContainer ">
	<div class="newsroomSidebar">
<div>In Virginia, 18 school districts will receive a total of $36,720,000 as part of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s Clean School Bus Program rebate competition, President Joe Biden announced May 29.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The designated school districts, found in every region of the state, will use the funds to purchase new school buses, most of them electric.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Here are the districts that will take part in the clean buses program, and their award amounts:</div>
<div>
<ul>
<li>Alexandria City Public Schools, $400,000</li>
<li>Arlington County Public Schools, $1,020,000.00</li>
<li>August County Public Schools, $400,000.00</li>
<li>Brunswick County Public Schools, $1,725,000.00</li>
<li>Charlottesville City Public Schools, $420,000.00</li>
<li>Culpeper County Public Schools, $800,000.00</li>
<li>Falls Church City Public Schools, $400,000.00</li>
<li>Fredericksburg City Public Schools, $3,490,000.00</li>
<li>Harrisonburg City Public Schools, $600,000.00</li>
<li>Henrico County Public Schools, $3,450,000.00</li>
<li>Loudoun County Public Schools, $3,975,000.00</li>
<li>Manassas County Public Schools, $1,200,000.00</li>
<li>Martinsville City Public Schools, $1,725,000.00</li>
<li>Northampton County Public Schools, $1,380,000.00</li>
<li>Virginia Beach Public Schools, $450,000.00</li>
<li>Westmoreland County Public Schools, $2,070,000.00</li>
<li>Wise County Public Schools, $1,725,000.00</div>
	</div>
	</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Nearly all of the clean school buses purchased will be electric, at 92%, according to the administration.</p>
<p>“This announcement is not just about clean school buses, it’s about the bigger picture,” EPA Administrator Michael S. Regan said during a call with reporters on Tuesday, prior to the announcement. “We are improving air quality for our children, reducing greenhouse gas pollution and expanding our nation’s leadership in developing the clean vehicles of the future.”</p>
<p>Low-income, rural and tribal communities — accounting for approximately 45% of the selected projects —  are slated to receive roughly 67% of the total funding, per the administration.</p>
<p>Regan noted how “low-income communities and communities of color have long felt the disproportionate impacts of air pollution leading to severe health outcomes that continue to impact these populations.”</p>
<p>As for business and economic opportunities, Regan pointed to the development of new, well-paying manufacturing jobs and investment in local businesses stemming from the increasing demand for these clean school buses.</p>
<p>“As more and more schools make the switch to electric buses, there will be a need for American-made batteries, charging stations and service providers to maintain the buses supercharging and reinvigorating local economies,” he added.</p>
<p>The Clean School Bus Program has now collectively awarded nearly $3 billion to fund approximately 8,500 electric and alternative fuel buses for over 1,000 communities across the United States, according to the administration.</p>
<p>The program started through the Bipartisan Infrastructure Law passed by Congress and signed by President Joe Biden, which includes $5 billion over five years to transform the country’s existing school buses with “zero-emission and low-emission models,” per the <a href="https://www.epa.gov/cleanschoolbus" target="_blank">EPA</a>.</p>
<p>Among many negative health and environmental effects, especially for communities of color, diesel exhaust exposure can lead to major health conditions such as asthma and respiratory illnesses, according to the <a href="https://www.epa.gov/dera/learn-about-impacts-diesel-exhaust-and-diesel-emissions-reduction-act-dera" target="_blank">EPA</a>.</p>
<p>Exposure to diesel exhaust can also “worsen existing heart and lung disease, especially in children and the elderly,” the agency said.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More than half of states sue to block Biden Title IX rule protecting LGBTQ+ students</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/21/more-than-half-of-states-including-virginia-sue-to-block-biden-title-ix-rule-protecting-lgbtq-students/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 09:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attorney General Jason Miyares]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education in virginia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LGBTQ+]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LGBTQ+ students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[title ix]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=38731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — Twenty-six GOP-led states, including Virginia, are suing the Biden administration over changes to Title IX aiming to protect LGBTQ+ students from discrimination in schools. Less than a month after the U.S. Department of Education released its final rule seeking to protect against discrimination “based on sex stereotypes, sexual orientation, gender identity, and sex characteristics,” a wave of [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Student_Walk_Out_4_Transgender-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Student_Walk_Out_4_Transgender-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Student_Walk_Out_4_Transgender-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Student_Walk_Out_4_Transgender-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Student_Walk_Out_4_Transgender-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Student_Walk_Out_4_Transgender-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">High school students across Virginia including those at McLean High School walked out in protest of the governor’s revised transgender student policies on Sept. 27, 2022. Pictured is a student holding a rainbow flag. (Nathaniel Cline/Virginia Mercury)</p><p>WASHINGTON — Twenty-six GOP-led states, including Virginia, are suing the Biden administration over changes to Title IX aiming to <a href="https://alabamareflector.com/2024/04/19/biden-administration-to-roll-back-the-betsy-devos-title-ix-rules/" target="_blank">protect LGBTQ+ students</a> from discrimination in schools.</p>
<p>Less than a month after the U.S. Department of Education released its final rule seeking to <a href="https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/us-department-education-releases-final-title-ix-regulations-providing-vital-protections-against-sex-discrimination/" target="_blank">protect against discrimination</a> “based on sex stereotypes, sexual orientation, gender identity, and sex characteristics,” a wave of Republican attorneys general scrambled to challenge the measure.</p>
<p>The revised rule, which will go into effect on Aug. 1, requires schools “to take prompt and effective action when notified of conduct that reasonably may constitute sex discrimination in their education programs or activities.”</p>
<p>The lawsuits hail from Alabama, Alaska, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Idaho, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Mississippi, Missouri, Montana, Nebraska, North Dakota, Ohio, Oklahoma, South Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Utah, Virginia, West Virginia and Wyoming.</p>
<p>All of the attorneys general in the 26 states suing over the final rule are part of the Republicans Attorneys General Association.</p>
<p>Various advocacy groups and school boards have also tacked onto the states’ legal actions. The lawsuits carry similar language and arguments in vehemently opposing the final rule. They say the new regulations raise First Amendment concerns and accuse the rule of violating the <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/administrative_procedure_act" target="_blank">Administrative Procedure Act</a>.</p>
<p>LGBTQ+ advocates say the revised rule offers students a needed protection and complies with existing law.</p>
<p>“Our kids’ experience in schools should be about learning, about making friends and growing as a young person. LGBTQ+ students deserve those same opportunities,” Sarah Warbelow, vice president of legal at the LGBTQ+ advocacy group Human Rights Campaign, said in an emailed statement. “In bringing these lawsuits, these state attorneys general are attempting to rob LGBTQ+ students of their rights, illustrating a complete disregard for the humanity of LGBTQ+ students.”</p>
<p><strong>GOP states band together against new regulations</strong></p>
<p>In the most recent effort, <a href="https://kansasreflector.com/2024/05/14/kansas-ag-sues-biden-administration-over-new-federal-protections-for-lgbtq-students/" target="_blank">Alaska, Kansas, Utah, and Wyoming</a> sued the <a href="https://ag.ks.gov/docs/default-source/documents/title-ix-complaint.pdf" target="_blank">Biden administration</a> on Tuesday, accusing the Department of Education of seeking to “politicize our country’s educational system to conform to the radical ideological views of the Biden administration and its allies.”</p>
<p>The lawsuit claims that under the updated regulations, teachers, coaches and administrators would have to “acknowledge, affirm, and validate students’ ‘gender identities’ regardless of the speakers’ own religious beliefs on the matter in violation of the First Amendment.”</p>
<p>In another lawsuit, a group of Southern states —  <a href="https://floridaphoenix.com/2024/04/30/fl-joins-gop-lawsuit-seeking-to-overturn-biden-administration-protections-for-transgender-students/" target="_blank">Alabama, Florida, Georgia and South Carolina</a> — sued the administration in <a href="https://www.alabamaag.gov/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Title-IX-Complaint.pdf" target="_blank">federal court</a> in Alabama over the new regulations.</p>
<p>Republican Alabama Attorney General Steve Marshall <a href="https://www.alabamaag.gov/attorney-general-steve-marshall-files-lawsuit-challenging-biden-rule-to-redefine-sex-as-gender-identity-in-americas-schools/" target="_blank">said</a> President Joe Biden “has brazenly attempted to use federal funding to force radical gender ideology onto states that reject it at the ballot box” since he took office.</p>
<p>“Now our schoolchildren are the target. The threat is that if Alabama’s public schools and universities do not conform, then the federal government will take away our funding,” Marshall said in a press release.</p>
<p>The lawsuit also drew praise from Republican Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, who said “Biden is abusing his constitutional authority to push an ideological agenda that harms women and girls and conflicts with the truth.” He added that the <a href="https://twitter.com/GovRonDeSantis/status/1785305760445935764" target="_blank">Sunshine State</a> will “not comply” and instead “fight back against Biden’s harmful agenda.”</p>
<p><strong>Individual states sue the administration </strong></p>
<p>Meanwhile, some states have opted to file individual lawsuits against the administration.</p>
<p>In Texas, Republican Attorney General Ken Paxton sued the Biden administration late last month in <a href="https://www.texasattorneygeneral.gov/sites/default/files/images/press/Title%20IX%20Complaint%20FIled.pdf" target="_blank">federal court</a> in Amarillo. Paxton filed an amended complaint earlier this week, with two new <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.txnd.389218/gov.uscourts.txnd.389218.12.0.pdf" target="_blank">plaintiffs</a> added.</p>
<p>In an <a href="https://www.texasattorneygeneral.gov/news/releases/attorney-general-ken-paxton-sues-biden-administration-unlawfully-using-title-ix-mandate-radical" target="_blank">April 29 press release</a>, Paxton said the Lone Star State “will not allow Joe Biden to rewrite Title IX at whim, destroying legal protections for women in furtherance of his radical obsession with gender ideology.”</p>
<p><a href="https://oklahomavoice.com/2024/05/06/oklahoma-ag-education-department-sue-biden-administration-over-title-ix-changes/" target="_blank">Oklahoma’s Republican Attorney General</a> Gentner Drummond <a href="https://www.oag.ok.gov/sites/g/files/gmc766/f/documents/2024/24-05-06_complaint_0.pdf" target="_blank">filed a lawsuit </a>against the Biden administration earlier this month in federal court in Oklahoma. The <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.okwd.126842/gov.uscourts.okwd.126842.1.0.pdf" target="_blank">state’s education department</a> also filed a separate suit against the Biden administration.</p>
<p><strong>A hodgepodge of states </strong></p>
<p>In late April, Republican attorneys general in <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/briefs/kentucky-attorney-general-leading-gop-effort-against-new-title-ix-rules-over-gender/" target="_blank">Indiana, Kentucky, Ohio, Tennessee, West Virginia and Virginia</a> filed a lawsuit against the <a href="https://content.govdelivery.com/attachments/INAG/2024/04/30/file_attachments/2863214/Complaint%20-%20FINAL,1.42.pdf" target="_blank">Biden administration</a> in federal court in Kentucky.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="oxhE0PhtXL"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/03/virginia-attorney-general-joins-efforts-to-fight-back-against-title-ix-changes/">Virginia attorney general joins efforts to fight back against Title IX changes</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Virginia attorney general joins efforts to fight back against Title IX changes&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/03/virginia-attorney-general-joins-efforts-to-fight-back-against-title-ix-changes/embed/#?secret=Y2cLINBg6L#?secret=oxhE0PhtXL" data-secret="oxhE0PhtXL" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>The states argued that the U.S. Education Department “has used rulemaking power to convert a law designed to equalize opportunities for both sexes into a far broader regime of its own making.”</p>
<p><a href="https://lailluminator.com/2024/04/29/louisiana-sues-biden-administration-over-title-ix-rules-that-protect-lgbtq-students/" target="_blank">Idaho, Louisiana, Mississippi and Montana</a> also sued the Biden administration in late April, echoing the language seen in the other related lawsuits. Seventeen local <a href="https://www.ag.state.la.us/Files/Article/13219/Documents/11-AmendedComplaint.pdf" target="_blank">school boards</a> in Louisiana also joined the states.</p>
<p>Earlier this month, <a href="https://arkansasadvocate.com/2024/05/07/arkansas-teen-attorney-general-file-federal-lawsuit-over-title-ix-transgender-protections/" target="_blank">Arkansas, Iowa, Missouri, Nebraska, North Dakota and South Dakota</a> also brought a collective <a href="https://arkansasag.gov/wp-content/uploads/2024-05-07-Arkansas-v.-US-Dept-of-Education-Filemarked.pdf" target="_blank">legal challenge</a> to the final rule.</p>
<p>A spokesperson for the Education Department said the department does not comment on pending litigation but noted that “as a condition of receiving federal funds, all federally-funded schools are obligated to comply with these final regulations.” They added that the department looks forward “to working with school communities all across the country to ensure the Title IX guarantee of nondiscrimination in school is every student’s experience.”</p>
<p>The department has yet to finalize a separate rule that establishes new criteria for transgender athletes. So far, 24 states have passed laws that ban transgender students from partaking in sports that align with their gender identity, according to the <a href="https://www.lgbtmap.org/equality-maps/youth/sports_participation_bans" target="_blank">Movement Advancement Project.</a></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Even as interest in women’s college sports rises, report finds big gap in participation</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/13/even-as-interest-in-womens-college-sports-rises-report-finds-big-gap-in-participation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shauneen Miranda]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>smiranda@statesnewsroom.com (Shauneen Miranda)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 09:58:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DC Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Caitlin Clark]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GAO Report]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[title ix]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. House Committee on Education and the Workforce]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.S. Rep. Bobby Scott]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US Department of Education]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=38658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WASHINGTON — A congressional watchdog in a new report called on the U.S. Department of Education’s Office for Civil Rights to improve its enforcement of Title IX compliance in college athletics. The U.S. Government Accountability Office in the report issued Thursday appeared critical of the OCR’s oversight in expanding opportunities for women in college athletics, [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="704" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/CaitlinClark-scaled-1-1024x704.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/CaitlinClark-scaled-1-1024x704.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/CaitlinClark-scaled-1-300x206.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/CaitlinClark-scaled-1-768x528.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/CaitlinClark-scaled-1-1536x1057.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/CaitlinClark-scaled-1-2048x1409.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Guard Caitlin Clark #22 of the Iowa Hawkeyes listens as the crowd cheers after breaking the NCAA women’s all-time scoring record during the game against the Michigan Wolverines at Carver-Hawkeye Arena on Feb. 15, 2024 in Iowa City, Iowa. Clark now plays in the WNBA. (Photo by Matthew Holst/Getty Images)</p><p>WASHINGTON — A congressional watchdog in a new report called on the U.S. Department of Education’s Office for Civil Rights to improve its enforcement of Title IX compliance in college athletics.</p>
<p>The U.S. Government Accountability Office in <a href="https://www.gao.gov/products/gao-24-105994" target="_blank">the report</a> issued Thursday appeared critical of the OCR’s oversight in expanding opportunities for women in college athletics, saying the office “conducts few proactive activities.” Women take part in college sports at lower rates than men, even though they enroll at higher rates, the report found.</p>
<p>The criticism also arrives at a time when women’s college sports, particularly basketball, have recently <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/08/womens-sports-could-bring-in-over-1-billion-in-2024-whats-driving-growth.html#:~:text=Deloitte%20forecasts%20that%20in%202024,in%20popularity%20of%20women's%20sports." target="_blank">gained more popularity</a> and viewership. The prominence of <a href="https://iowacapitaldispatch.com/2024/03/29/they-feel-seen-and-they-feel-validated/" target="_blank">Caitlin Clark</a>, the former guard for the University of Iowa women’s basketball team who became the <a href="https://www.ncaa.org/news/2024/3/3/features-caitlin-clark-joins-rare-company-to-hold-ncaa-records-across-mens-and-womens-basketball.aspx" target="_blank">NCAA</a> Division I’s all-time leading scorer across women’s and men’s basketball, has helped propel the momentum.</p>
<p>During the more than 50 years since its adoption, Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 has prohibited discrimination based on sex in activities or programs receiving federal funding. The <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/ocr-higher-ed-athletic-resource-202302.pdf" target="_blank">federal law</a> also mandates “schools to provide equal opportunity based on sex.” The department’s <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/tix_dis.html" target="_blank">OCR</a> is tasked with enforcing compliance of Title IX.</p>
<p>Virginia Democratic Rep. Bobby Scott, ranking member of the House Committee on Education and the Workforce, released the GAO report with U.S. Rep. Suzanne Bonamici, ranking member of the House Subcommittee on Early Childhood, Elementary, and Secondary Education.</p>
<p>“Every student who wants to play a sport in college should have a fair and equal opportunity to do so,” said Scott.</p>
<p>“Regrettably, today’s GAO report confirms that while female college enrollment numbers outpace male enrollment, opportunities for female athletes significantly lag behind their male counterparts,” he said.</p>
<p>Bonamici, a Democrat from Oregon, said the federal law “sets a standard of equal opportunity that too many schools have failed to meet.” She added that the GAO report “shows that women enroll in college at a higher rate than men but consistently participate in college athletics at a lower rate than men.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Gap in women’s and men’s sports participation </h4>

	
<p>The report highlighted the persistent gap in college sports participation between women and men. Approximately 93% of colleges saw lower athletic participation rates for women relative to their enrollment rate during the 2021-2022 academic year.</p>
<p>Title IX also requires schools receiving federal funding to have participation numbers of men and women in college sports to be “substantially proportionate to their overall enrollment,” according to the <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ocr/docs/interath.html" target="_blank">Department of Education</a>.</p>
<p>Yet, women’s overall athletic participation rate fell 14 percentage points behind their enrollment rate in the 2021-2022 academic year, the GAO found.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Communication delays</h4>

	
<p>The GAO noted that the OCR made “limited use of available data for oversight purposes” and did not “always communicate with colleges in a timely way during monitoring.”</p>
<p>On average, it took half a year for the OCR to respond to colleges after “they submitted their Title IX athletics monitoring reports,” per the GAO.</p>
<p>The congressional watchdog found “years-long delays in communication between OCR and some colleges.” In 10 of 26 cases, it took at least a year or longer for the OCR to communicate with a college. In one case, it took nearly seven years for the OCR to approve the college’s proposed methodology for assessing whether it complied with Title IX athletics requirements, the GAO said.</p>
<p>In response to the report, Catherine Lhamon, assistant secretary for civil rights at the department, said the department is “fully committed to work with GAO to ensure the recommendations are implemented, to the extent possible.”</p>
<p>The attention paid to women’s sports is on the rise, thanks in part to Clark’s popularity on the court. Clark now plays for the WNBA’s Indiana Fever.</p>
<p>In April, the women’s basketball championship garnered more viewers compared to the men’s championship game for the first time in NCAA history, according to <a href="https://www.nielsen.com/news-center/2024/womens-college-basketball-championship-draws-record-breaking-18-9-million-viewers/" target="_blank">Nielsen</a>, which measures media audiences.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
