<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Kevin Hardy, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<atom:link href="https://virginiamercury.com/author/kevinhardy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/kevinhardy/</link>
	<description>A new look at the Old Dominion</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 10:29:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cropped-virginiamercury-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Kevin Hardy, Author at Virginia Mercury</title>
	<link>https://virginiamercury.com/author/kevinhardy/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>‘Why not us?’ Nannies, housekeepers win labor protections in some states</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/12/26/why-not-us-nannies-housekeepers-win-labor-protections-in-some-states/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2024 10:28:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Children + Families]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[au pairs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[domestic labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nannies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[worker protections]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=41605</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When she first started working as an au pair, Edy Dominguez earned less than the minimum wage and went without paid sick time or overtime pay for extra-long weeks. That’s because domestic workers, including nannies, housekeepers and home health workers, have historically been excluded from the basic labor protections most workers enjoy. “There are standards [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="825" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers-300x242.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers-768x619.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">LAS VEGAS, NEVADA - AUGUST 25:  Babysitter Alana Milawski (L) helps Goolsby Elementary School kindergartner Vera Dweck, 5, as she works from a friend's home on the first week of distance learning for the Clark County School District amid the spread of the coronavirus (COVID-19) on August 25, 2020 in Las Vegas, Nevada. CCSD, the fifth-largest school district in the United States with more than 315,000 students, decided to start the school year with a full-time distance education instructional model as part of its Reopening Our Schools Plan due to health and safety concerns over the pandemic.  (Ethan Miller/Getty Images)</p><p>When she first started working as an au pair, Edy Dominguez earned less than the minimum wage and went without paid sick time or overtime pay for extra-long weeks.</p>
<p>That’s because domestic workers, including nannies, housekeepers and home health workers, have historically been excluded from the basic labor protections most workers enjoy.</p>
<p>“There are standards in every other industry,” she said. “Why not us?”</p>
<p>After a decade of domestic work, Dominguez became an organizer for the Fair Work Center, a labor advocacy group in Washington state that won a victory in 2019 when Seattle <a href="https://www.seattle.gov/documents/Departments/LaborStandards/OLS_QA_Domestic%20Workers_FINAL_10022020.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">implemented</a> an ordinance guaranteeing minimum wage, meal periods and paid rest breaks for domestic workers. Now, advocates are pushing for new statewide legislation that would ensure minimum wage and sick time and require written agreements between employers and workers.</p>
<p>“I know what it is to be unprotected and alone in this industry,” Dominguez said. “There’s no co-workers.”</p>
<div class="newsroomSidebarContainer ">
<div class="newsroomSidebar">
	<div class="newsroomSidebarContainer ">
	<div class="newsroomSidebar"><strong>States with domestic worker protections</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>California</li>
<li>Connecticut</li>
<li>Hawaii</li>
<li>Illinois</li>
<li>Massachusetts</li>
<li>New Jersey</li>
<li>New York</li>
<li>Nevada</li>
<li>New Mexico</li>
<li>Oregon</li>
<li>Virginia</li>
<li>Rhode Island</li>
</ul>
<p>Source: National Domestic Workers Alliance</div>
	</div>
	
</div>
</div>
<p>If advocates are successful, Washington would join a dozen Democratic-leaning states and several cities that have added new protections for domestic workers. Efforts in those places did not face widespread opposition, though they raised some concerns about privacy and overregulation of workers in private homes.</p>
<p>In 2010, <a href="https://labornotes.org/2010/07/domestic-workers-new-york-win-first-ever-job-protections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New York became the first state</a> to pass a Domestic Worker Bill of Rights, guaranteeing overtime pay, at least one day off per week and protections against racial and sexual harassment. Since then, 11 other states have passed similar laws, as have Philadelphia, Seattle and Washington, D.C., according to the National Domestic Workers Alliance.</p>
<p>Congress is unlikely to pass national standards anytime soon. President-elect Donald Trump has promised mass deportations of immigrants — who make up a disproportionate share of domestic workers — and he and the GOP-dominated Congress almost certainly would be cool to new regulations designed to protect them.</p>
<p>Federal labor laws for decades exempted domestic workers from many safeguards, including a minimum wage, civil rights protections and workplace safety standards. These exclusions were rooted in racism and sexism, said Zoë West, a senior researcher at The Worker Institute at Cornell University who has studied the industry and operated training programs to educate workers about their rights.</p>
<p>Historically, domestic work has largely been done by Black and immigrant women, West said, and that work — cleaning, child care and the like — has long been viewed as “women’s natural work.”</p>
<p>“There’s a very persistent, strong perception that this isn’t real work,” she said.</p>
<p>Some of the new state and local legislation has mandated that domestic workers are paid overtime and at least the state or city minimum wage, while other laws have gone further, ensuring protections such as paid time off.</p>
<p>But new laws are just the first step.</p>
<p>“[Y]ou still have this enforcement question,” West said. “Across all kinds of low-wage work — not just domestic work — there’s a lot of challenges in enforcing labor law.”</p>
<p>Many domestic workers are privately employed by families, making it difficult to educate both employers and workers about new protections. And domestic workers, who are sometimes paid cash without any formal work agreement, can be particularly vulnerable to retaliation.</p>
<p>In Philadelphia, which approved new domestic worker protections in 2019, some workers who pushed employers to honor newly won rights such as lunch breaks or contracts were fired, said Aurora Munoz, the Pennsylvania organizing manager for the National Domestic Workers Alliance.</p>
<p>The organization has since launched an anti-retaliation campaign and is pushing the Philadelphia City Council to approve new legislation next year to prevent retaliation and beef up enforcement.</p>
<p>Last year, <a href="https://www.phila.gov/media/20240122095349/Policy-and-Compliance-Report-2023.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philadelphia received six complaints </a>regarding domestic worker protections; five of those cases were closed. The city’s labor department could not be reached for comment.</p>
<p>“If we enforce it to the T, then it will be really amazing and beneficial for not just domestic workers, but a lot of low-wage workers,” Munoz said.</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">‘People are paying attention’</h4>

	</h4>
<p>For New Jersey state Sen. Britnee Timberlake, the story of domestic work is the story of her family.</p>
<p>Her grandmother worked as a so-called baby nurse and house cleaner. When she relocated to the Northeast from North Carolina, she found domestic jobs for other family members moving North.</p>
<p>Timberlake, a Democrat, sponsored legislation requiring meal breaks, protection from discrimination and the right to written contracts for domestic workers.</p>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" title="“Steep fines in Iowa set off state-federal showdown over child labor laws” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2024/07/23/steep-fines-in-iowa-set-off-state-federal-showdown-over-child-labor-laws/embed/#?secret=GDbSJQ7wtt#?secret=orLbWvTw9b" width="500" height="440" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="orLbWvTw9b" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>“One of my only regrets with the bill is that I did not name it after her,” she said of her grandmother. “This is something that is a part of my history and a part of my fabric.”</p>
<p>Timberlake said <a href="https://www.njleg.state.nj.us/bill-search/2022/S723" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the legislation</a>, introduced in 2022 and enacted earlier this year, aligns with broader efforts to provide protections for workers who aren’t in unions.</p>
<p><a href="https://newjerseymonitor.com/2024/01/09/domestic-workers-celebrate-passage-of-bill-granting-them-new-labor-protections/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Business groups opposed the bill</a>, saying it would unfairly overburden employers, the New Jersey Monitor reported.</p>
<p>The New Jersey Business &amp; Industry Association pushed for some amendments that were added to the bill, including removal of a provision that would have mandated an extra hour of pay in situations where the employer cannot provide a meal or rest period. <a href="https://njbia.org/lame-duck-review-how-nj-business-fared/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">In a legislative update on the group’s website,</a> Vice President of Government Affairs Elissa Frank said the changes “successfully strike a balance between providing flexibility for employers to manage their workforce according to business needs and ensuring certain protections for employees.”</p>
<p>Now, Garden State advocates are working to ensure both workers and employers know about the new law, said Evelyn Saz, the lead New Jersey organizer with the National Domestic Workers Alliance.</p>
<p>Saz came into domestic work <a href="https://19thnews.org/2023/10/domestic-workers-health-safety-protections/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">after fleeing war</a> in her native El Salvador for the United States, where she struggled to find work because she did not speak English and had a foreign university degree.</p>
<p>“I took any opportunity I could as a single mother to support my family,” she wrote in an email to Stateline translated into English by a co-worker at her alliance. “This work can’t stop now. We need to make sure that domestic workers are fully informed about their rights and are able to enforce them.”</p>
<p>Traditional labor organizing focuses on a single geographic location: a hotel or factory with a broad group of workers and a single employer. But that’s not possible with domestic workers, said Ben Fuller-Googins, deputy director of Carroll Gardens Association, a neighborhood organization in Brooklyn that advocates for affordable housing, worker rights and other issues.</p>
<figure id="attachment_41608" class="wp-caption alignleft" style="max-width:100%;width:225px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=41608" rel="attachment wp-att-41608"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="wp-image-41608 size-medium" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers-sign-768x1024-1-225x300.jpeg" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers-sign-768x1024-1-225x300.jpeg 225w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/domestic-workers-sign-768x1024-1.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  The Carroll Gardens Association celebrates International Domestic Workers Day in June 2024 in Brooklyn, N.Y. The neighborhood organization has been working to educate nannies and other domestic workers of their workplace rights. (Courtesy of Carroll Gardens Association)</p></figure>
<p>“You don’t know how many domestic workers there are, where they work,” he said. “There’s one employer per worker.”</p>
<p>That’s led his organization to aim to educate workers and employers across the entire Carroll Gardens neighborhood about the state’s protections for domestic workers.</p>
<p>“Our approach is that, generally, employers want to do the right thing but are not equipped with the resources and guidance they might need,” he said.</p>
<p>The New York State Department of Labor has conducted 840 investigations into potential violations of the law since 2010, when the law was enacted.</p>
<p>Kenya Williams, who’s been a nanny in New York for 26 years, said she was only recently informed of her rights when a member of the Carroll Gardens group approached her in a local park. Before that, she said, she generally took whatever pay and conditions were offered to her and didn’t know to ask about holiday or overtime pay.</p>
<p>“Things are slowly getting better,” she said. “I think we are making improvements in our industry and people are paying attention.”</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Is the home a workplace?</h4>

	</h4>
<p>By its nature, domestic work can be informal.</p>
<p>With no human resources department at hand, families will often ask friends what they pay their nannies or Google how to hire a housekeeper, said Stacy Kono, director of Hand in Hand, a national group representing employers of domestic workers.</p>
<p>“In many ways, the first barrier we often face is people don’t even realize they’re employers,” she said.</p>
<p>While some employers do not provide benefits or pay fair wages, Kono said many want to do the right thing for those who work in their homes.</p>
<p>“We haven’t seen organized employer opposition to the efforts,” she said of the new laws. “It’s generally been employers supporting the efforts.</p>
<p>“We want to shift the mindset so that people do recognize domestic work as protected labor that is work like any other work, and for that reason, the home is a workplace.”</p>
<p>Whether private homes should be considered a workplace has been an ongoing debate in California.</p>
<p>Democratic Gov. Gavin Newsom in 2020 <a href="https://www.gov.ca.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/SB-1257.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vetoed legislation</a> that would have required domestic employers to comply with occupational health and safety rules. In his veto message, the governor said he agreed with the sponsor’s intent.</p>
<p>“However, new laws in this area must recognize that the places where people live cannot be treated in the exact same manner as a traditional workplace or worksite from a regulatory perspective,” he wrote.</p>
<p>This September, <a href="https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billHistoryClient.xhtml?bill_id=202320240SB1350" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Newsom signed narrower legislation</a> extending safety standards for domestic workers employed by agencies.</p>
<p>“It isn’t everything we want. It doesn’t protect all of our base. But it is an important and historical step forward for California,” said Kimberly Alvarenga, director of the California Domestic Workers Coalition.</p>
<p>The University of California, Los Angeles estimates the state is home to more than <a href="https://losh.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/37/2020/06/Hidden-Work-Hidden-Pain.-Domestic-Workers-Report.-UCLA-LOSH-June-2020-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">350,000 domestic workers</a> employed in 2 million households. That includes an estimated 175,000 who work for agencies or services as opposed to private families, Alvarenga said.</p>
<p>California previously <a href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/DomesticWorkerBillOfRights.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">extended overtime pay</a> to most domestic workers, but they still were not given the same health and safety protections as many other workers.</p>
<p>While the organization would like to see safety standards extended to all workers, Alvarenga said it’s currently focused on enforcement and education around the new law.</p>
<p>“This work is not being valued. It’s not being recognized,” she said. “They’re not asking for something special. They’re just asking for basic protections.”</p>
<div class="donateContainer">
<div class="donateTextContainer"></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>When business is booming but daily living is a struggle </title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/25/when-business-is-booming-but-daily-living-is-a-struggle/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 14:30:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business + Economic Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[former President Donald Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Housing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inflation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice President Kamala Harris]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40171</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Editor’s note: This is part of a five-day series explores the priorities of voters in Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, Nevada, North Carolina, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin as they consider the upcoming presidential election. With the outcome expected to be close, these “swing states” may decide the future of the country.  ROCKY MOUNT, N.C. — The signs on [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="768" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-states-Kristie.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-states-Kristie.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-states-Kristie-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-states-Kristie-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Kristie Hilliard opened her new shop, Kristie Kandies, in downtown Rocky Mount, N.C., after getting tired of her factory job at the local Pfizer plant. She’s seen a steady flow of customers, but says she’s doesn’t think either Vice President Kamala Harris or former President Donald Trump would change her economic fortunes. (Kevin Hardy/Stateline)</p><p><em>Editor’s note: This is part of a five-day series explores the priorities of voters in Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, Nevada, North Carolina, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin as they consider the upcoming presidential election. With the outcome expected to be close, these “swing states” may decide the future of the country. </em></p>
<figure id="attachment_40173" class="wp-caption alignright" style="max-width:100%;width:329px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=40173" rel="attachment wp-att-40173"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-40173" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/The-Deciders-final-logo-300x183.png" alt="" width="329" height="200" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/The-Deciders-final-logo-300x183.png 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/The-Deciders-final-logo-1024x625.png 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/The-Deciders-final-logo-768x469.png 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/The-Deciders-final-logo-1536x937.png 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/The-Deciders-final-logo-2048x1250.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 329px) 100vw, 329px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  7 States + 5 Issues That Will Swing the 2024 Election</p></figure>
<p>ROCKY MOUNT, N.C. — The signs on the empty historic buildings envision an urban utopia of sorts, complete with street cafes, bustling bike lanes and a grocery co-op.</p>
<p>“IMAGINE What Could Be Here,” gushes one sign outside the empty, Neoclassical post office. “IMAGINE! A Vibrant Downtown,” reads another mounted on the glass front of a long-ago closed drug store.</p>
<p>In a place like Rocky Mount, North Carolina, it’s not such a stretch: Just across the street, white-collar workers peck away at laptops and sip lattes at a bright coffee bar lined with dozens of potted tropical plants. A few blocks away, a mammoth events center routinely brings in thousands of visitors from across the country. And alongside a quiet river nearby, a meticulously redeveloped cotton mill would be the envy of any American city, with its modern breweries, restaurants and loft living.</p>
<p>An industrial community long in decline, Rocky Mount is slowly building itself back. But in this city of about 54,000, sharply divided by race and class, many residents struggle to cover the basic costs of groceries, housing and child care.</p>
<p>North Carolina reflects the duality of the American economy: Unemployment is low, jobs are increasing and businesses are opening new factories. But high housing and food costs have squeezed middle-class residents despite the gains of rising wages.</p>
<p>“The economy stinks,” said Tameika Horne, who owns an ice cream and dessert shop in Rocky Mount.</p>
<p>Her ingredient prices have skyrocketed, she said, but she can’t continuously raise prices on ice cream cones or funnel cakes. She said last month was her slowest ever, with only $2,000 in sales.</p>
<p>It’s not just the slow sales at her store: Only a few years ago, she paid $700 a month to rent a three-bedroom apartment. Now, her similarly sized rental home costs her $1,350 a month.</p>
<p>Aside from the ice cream shop, Horne also runs a cleaning business with her family and just started a job delivering packages for FedEx.</p>
<p>“It’s just hard right now,” she said.</p>
<p>The economy, a top issue for voters during any election, is particularly important this presidential cycle: Prices of necessities such as groceries aren’t rising as fast as they were, but years of post-pandemic inflation have soured voter attitudes.</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">Nobody is immune from what’s going on</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– Cassandra Conover, a former Virginia prosecutor who leads the Nash County Democratic Party</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>And across the country, millions of families are struggling with rising housing costs. In four of the seven swing states — Arizona, Georgia, Michigan and Nevada — more than half of tenant families <a href="https://stateline.org/2024/09/12/rent-is-eating-up-a-greater-share-of-tenants-income-in-almost-every-state/" target="_blank">spend</a> 30% or more of their income on rent and utilities, according to the 2023 American Community Survey.</p>
<p>In North Carolina, voter anxiety about the soaring rents and grocery bills could tip the scales.</p>
<p>“In terms of its political influence, it’s not actually your personal financial situation that is important, it’s your vision of the national economy,” said Matt Grossmann, a political science professor at Michigan State University. “So if I get a raise, I tend to credit myself. If I see higher prices, I tend to blame the government or the current situation.”</p>
<p>Around the corner from Horne’s ice cream store in downtown Rocky Mount, Kristie Hilliard greets a steady flow of customers to her new shop, Kristie Kandies. An armed cop, a nurse in scrubs and waist-high kids trickle in to grab a sweet treat.</p>
<p>After getting tired of her manufacturing job at the local Pfizer plant, Hilliard started making confections at home. As her following grew, she got a concession trailer and now has a storefront selling candied grapes, plums, kiwis and pickles.</p>
<p>Hilliard’s treats have attracted attention on social media, causing some buyers to drive in from as far away as Pennsylvania, she said.</p>
<p>A Democrat, she said she still hadn’t made up her mind on the presidential race. But she doesn’t believe either a Harris or a Trump administration would drastically change much for her business.</p>
<p>“They ain’t doing nothing for me now,” she said. “So, what would change?”</p>
<figure id="attachment_40174" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="max-width:100%;width:1024px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=40174" rel="attachment wp-att-40174"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-40174 size-full" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-tower.jpg" alt="" width="1024" height="768" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-tower.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-tower-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-tower-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  A former cotton mill built and once operated by slave labor, Rocky Mount Mills closed in 1996, reopened in 2015 and is now home to breweries, restaurants and dozens of high-end apartments. (Kevin Hardy/Stateline)</p></figure>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">A community divided looks to the future</h4>

	
<p>About 60 miles northeast of the state capital, Rocky Mount lies between the prosperous Research Triangle area and North Carolina’s scenic beach communities.</p>
<p>Railroad tracks and a county line slice through the middle of downtown. On the one side is the majority Black and lower-income Edgecombe County. On the other, the more prosperous and whiter Nash County.</p>
<p>While some officials say long-standing attitudes centered on division are fading, the county line has for decades provided a clear delineation of class, race and politics.</p>
<p>Edgecombe County is a Democratic stronghold, but the more populous Nash County is a bellwether of sorts. It was among the <a href="https://www.oldnorthstatepolitics.com/2024/04/counties-to-watch-in-2024-north.html" target="_blank">10 closest</a> of North Carolina’s 100 counties in the last presidential election, and one being closely watched this cycle. With 51,774 <a href="https://www.politico.com/2020-election/results/north-carolina/" target="_blank">ballots cast</a>, President Joe Biden took Nash County by 120 votes.</p>
<p>Around Rocky Mount’s downtown area, stately red brick churches and banks line the wide streets. But just a few blocks away, weeds overtake vacant lots, glass is smashed out of abandoned buildings, and razor wire tops the fencing of no-credit-needed car lots and used tire shops.</p>
<p>While the nearby Raleigh metro area has experienced explosive suburban growth, Rocky Mount Mayor Sandy Roberson said his community has seen an erosion of its middle class with the loss of corporate headquarters and factory jobs.</p>
<p>But he’s optimistic.</p>
<p>Young business owners are investing in downtown. Industries with operations in the Raleigh area are moving east. And both Republicans and Democrats just celebrated the news that Natron Energy plans to build a $1.4 billion electric vehicle battery plant nearby that will employ more than 1,000 people.</p>
<p>“We’ve got a lot of great things that are happening,” the mayor said. “But the key is, how do you build and retain a middle class? Because that’s who does the living and the dying and the investing in a community.”</p>
<p>The mayor’s position is nonpartisan, but Roberson is a Republican who in 2022 ran in the Republican primary for a congressional seat here. This election, however, is a difficult one for him.</p>
<p>Roberson said the economy and his financial position were unquestionably better during former President Donald Trump’s term, but the Jan. 6, 2021, insurrection and the chaos of the last Trump presidency make him hard to support. At the same time, Roberson worries about Democratic presidential nominee Vice President Kamala Harris’ economic policies; he believes the current administration has accelerated inflation by pumping too much money into the economy.</p>
<p>“At some levels, it feels like I’m voting for somebody who wants to either be a dictator or somebody who wants to create a socialist state,” Roberson said. “And I’m not in either place.”</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">‘Nobody is immune’</h4>

	
<p>In North Carolina and other swing states, Trump’s television ads hammer the vice president over high prices and “Bidenomics.”</p>
<p>Nash County Republican Party volunteer Yvonne McLeod said the economy, along with immigration, are the top concerns locally. Businesses still struggle to hire, rents have soared and food prices are still up, she said.</p>
<p>“Economically, we’re hurting,” she said.</p>
<p>Democrats must be honest about the financial pressures facing voters, said Cassandra Conover, a former Virginia prosecutor who now leads the Nash County Democratic Party. She noted that Harris ads running in North Carolina speak directly to middle-class concerns.</p>
<p>“Nobody is immune from what’s going on,” Conover said. “She’s telling all of us who are hurting, ‘I know, and we’re working for you.’”</p>
<p>Polling has shown voters are sour on the economy, with <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/4870214-poll-us-economy-wrong-track/" target="_blank">63%</a> saying the economy was on the wrong track in a Harvard-CAPS-Harris poll released this month. Republicans take a far dimmer view than Democrats.</p>
<p>“From past experience, we would expect Harris to inherit some of the blame or credit for the current economy, but so far in the polls, I would say there has been a surprising willingness of voters to not extend the blame for inflation that they had for Joe Biden onto Kamala Harris,” said Grossmann, the Michigan State University professor.</p>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Housing anxiety</h4>

	
<p>Housing costs have <a href="https://home.treasury.gov/news/featured-stories/rent-house-prices-and-demographics" target="_blank">outstripped</a> income gains in the past two decades, but those challenges have intensified since the COVID-19 pandemic, when demand increased, construction costs soared and interest rates spiked.</p>
<p>“It doesn’t matter if you’re a buyer or a renter,” said Molly Boesel, an economist at CoreLogic, a financial services information company. “You’re seeing your housing costs increase.”</p>
<p>Affordability is “the No. 1 issue” among voters in Nevada this year, said Mario Arias, the Nevada director of the Forward Party, a centrist political party founded by former Democratic presidential hopeful Andrew Yang.</p>
<p>A resident of the Las Vegas area, 30-year-old Arias said housing is his biggest financial concern. Throngs of Californians have moved into Nevada to lower their housing costs, but it’s driven up costs for everyone else, he said.</p>
<p>“If you want to get out of being a renter, you have to be in not just a good financial situation, but in a very stable financial situation,” he said.</p>
<p>The Federal Reserve cut interest rates last week for the first time in four years, which could open the housing market to more homebuyers as mortgage rates ease in the coming months.</p>
<p>The Biden administration has <a href="https://penncapital-star.com/uncategorized/a-look-at-how-federal-plans-could-make-the-costs-of-housing-more-affordable/" target="_blank">proposed</a> several housing-related policies, including incentives to loosen zoning regulations and capping rent increases from corporate landlords. Harris has announced a proposal to provide up to $25,000 in housing assistance for a down payment to some potential first-time homeowners and promised tax incentives that she say’s would lead to 3 million more housing units by the end of her first term, if she’s elected.</p>
<p>Trump has not waded far into the details of how he would address the affordability issue in a second term. He has <a href="https://www.wsj.com/real-estate/trump-says-he-would-ban-mortgages-for-undocumented-immigrants-3dbbbb94" target="_blank">said</a> he plans to bring down prices by barring immigrants in the country without legal authorization from getting mortgages. But his proposed <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2024/09/06/business/undocumented-immigrants-trump-mortgage-ban/index.html" target="_blank">immigration policies</a> could further reduce the labor force for building homes. Previously, Trump’s administration talked about trying to cut state and local housing regulations, and it suspended federal regulations on fair housing.</p>
<p>In North Carolina, more than a quarter of the state’s households are cost burdened, meaning they spend more than 30% of their income on housing costs. It’s particularly challenging for renters, nearly half of which are cost burdened, according to the North Carolina Housing Coalition, a nonprofit affordable housing organization.</p>
<p>Stephanie Watkins-Cruz, housing policy director at the coalition, noted that the federal government’s calculation of fair market rent in North Carolina has shot up 14% in just one year — and 38% over the past five years.</p>
<p>“So unless everybody and their mama’s getting 14 to 20 to 38% raises, the math begins to not math,” she said.</p>
<p>It’s a familiar challenge in every swing state.</p>
<p>Wendy Winston, a middle school math teacher in Grand Rapids Michigan, said that though no one political candidate is responsible for the state of the economy, the cost of groceries and housing is hard to ignore.</p>
<p>“I don’t think the economy is terrible. It is sometimes difficult to make ends meet,” Winston said. “I don’t believe that it’s the fault of the government or policies of the government. I feel like it’s the individual corporations trying to make profit off the backs of the middle class.”</p>
<p>The average rent for a two-bedroom apartment in Grand Rapids is about $1,550 a month, according to rental site Apartments.com. Though Michigan ranks fairly average compared with other states for rent prices, the state saw some of the steepest rent increases in the country in recent years, and wages have not kept up. Residents unable to rent new, “luxury” apartments find themselves short of options for places they can afford.</p>
<p>“It’s not just cost, it’s availability,” Winston said. “There are a lot of new housing developments. Apartments and condos and things are being built, but I’m priced out of them. And I have a college degree, so I don’t think that’s helping our families.”</p>
<figure id="attachment_40176" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="max-width:100%;width:1024px;"><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/?attachment_id=40176" rel="attachment wp-att-40176"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="wp-image-40176 size-full" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-furniture.jpg" alt="" width="1024" height="768" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-furniture.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-furniture-300x225.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/swing-state-economy-furniture-768x576.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text"><i class="fas fa-camera"></i>  Melanie Davis, the co-owner of Davis Furniture Company in Rocky Mount, N.C., says business has been good lately, though she believes customers are anxious about the presidential election. She’s excited about downtown’s future. (Kevin Hardy/Stateline)</p></figure>
    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Hoping for revival</h4>

	
<p>Back in North Carolina, near the banks of the Tar River, Rocky Mount Mills has a healthy waiting list for the apartments and the revamped homes it rents.</p>
<p>A former cotton mill <a href="https://www.dncr.nc.gov/blog/2023/12/12/rocky-mount-mills-e-7" target="_blank">built and once operated</a> by slave labor, the campus closed in 1996, reopened in 2015 after a $75 million renovation, and is now home to breweries, restaurants and dozens of high-end apartments.</p>
<p>Chapel Hill native and entrepreneur Cameron Schulz never had Rocky Mount on his radar. But the development’s brewery incubator helped him launch HopFly Brewing Co., now one of the state’s largest self-distributing breweries.</p>
<p>After outgrowing its original space, HopFly relocated to Charlotte, but still operates a taproom in Rocky Mount. The Mills project has reinvigorated the city, Schulz said.</p>
<p>“Rocky Mount’s got one of the most beautiful, quintessential downtown strips that I’ve ever seen anywhere,” he said. “We’ve just got to fill it up with cool places to go, and people to go into those places.”</p>
<p>Main Street suffered for decades after the arrival of malls and a highway bypass. Over at Davis Furniture Company, two employees keep watch over an empty storeroom of sofas, beds and home decor.</p>
<p>Co-owner Melanie Davis said business has been good, though she believes customers are anxious about the presidential election.<strong> </strong>Pointing down the sidewalk to new restaurants and some loft apartments overlooking the railroad tracks, Davis said she’s bullish on the trajectory of downtown.</p>
<p>“I do feel like we’re on an upswing,” she said.</p>
<p><em><strong>Michigan Advance’s Anna Liz Nichols contributed reporting</strong>.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Deciders: The issues and states that will determine who wins the White House</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/09/23/the-deciders-the-issues-and-states-that-will-determine-who-wins-the-white-house/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 20:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elections and Voting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deciders 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electoral College]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[former President Donald Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trend – Election 2024]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice President Kamala Harris]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=40139</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Editor’s note: This five-day series explores the priorities of voters in Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, Nevada, North Carolina, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin as they consider the upcoming presidential election. With the outcome expected to be close, these “swing states” may decide the future of the country. It’s been a wild few months in the presidential race: President [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Harris-Trump-1.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Harris-Trump-1.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Harris-Trump-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Harris-Trump-1-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">Former President Donald Trump and Vice President Kamala Harris debate for the first time during the presidential election campaign at The National Constitution Center on Sept. 10 in Philadelphia. A handful of issues and groups of voters in battleground states could decide the race. (Photo by Alex Wong/Getty Images)</p><p><strong><em>Editor’s note: </em></strong><em>This five-day series explores the priorities of voters in Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, Nevada, North Carolina, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin as they consider the upcoming presidential election. With the outcome expected to be close, these “swing states” may decide the future of the country.</em></p>
<p>It’s been a wild few months in the presidential race: President Joe Biden dropped out and Vice President Kamala Harris captured the Democratic nomination. Former President Donald Trump survived an assassination attempt in Pennsylvania and was targeted again at his golf club in West Palm Beach, Florida.</p>
<p>Despite the historic lead-up to Election Day, the race has now settled into familiar territory: Much like 2020’s contest, top political strategists on both sides of the aisle expect control of the White House could come down to just a few thousand votes in a handful of battleground states.</p>
<p>“This is not going to be an election where you will see a landslide. It’s going to be won in the margins in six to seven swing states,” Democratic strategist Donna Brazile told a crowd of state lawmakers from across the country last month.</p>
<p>Brazile, who ran Al Gore’s 2000 presidential campaign, shared the stage with Republican strategist Kellyanne Conway, who managed Trump’s 2016 campaign and advised him in the White House.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, the pair disagreed on much.</p>
<p>But while speaking at the National Conference of State Legislatures in Kentucky, the two senior strategists framed the race similarly to the 2020 contest, when <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/11/25/937248659/president-elect-biden-hits-80-million-votes-in-year-of-record-turnout" target="_blank">fewer than 50,000 votes</a> in Arizona, Georgia and Wisconsin separated Biden and Trump from an Electoral College tie.</p>
<p>“It is a different race. It has turned in very short time, but the issue set hasn’t changed at all,” Conway said. “And I think that’s what’s important here.”</p>
<p>Like last cycle, the two campaigns are pouring millions into Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, Nevada, North Carolina, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin.</p>
<p>In “The Deciders” series, States Newsroom, the nation’s largest state-focused nonprofit news organization, explores the political issues and groups of voters that could make the difference in those seven states and, consequentially, in the race for the White House.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, economic issues <sub>—</sub> namely, stubbornly high prices — are proving central for many voters across the swing states. But voters also are concerned about immigration, abortion access and the future of the Supreme Court.</p>
<p>In states such as Michigan and Nevada, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin, labor unions could prove instrumental for Harris after years of significant gains by organized labor.</p>
<p>In Georgia and North Carolina, Black voter turnout could make the difference, while Latino voters are closely divided in Nevada after helping propel Biden to victory there four years ago. In every swing state, campaigns are focused on all-important suburban voters.</p>
<p>The election’s outcome also could be shaped by the work of officials who have been debating who can vote and which votes should count since the mayhem of the last presidential contest.</p>
<p>Four years ago, a false narrative that questioned the security and integrity of elections took hold in some legislatures. New laws changed ballot-counting practices and made it more difficult to vote in many states, including swing states. In states such as Michigan and Wisconsin, there is broad concern that despite the checks and balances built into the voting system, local Republicans tasked with certifying elections will be driven by conspiracy theories and refuse to fulfill their duties if Trump loses again.</p>
<p>Fears that these efforts could sow chaos and delay results is not unfounded: Over the past four years, county officials in the swing states of Arizona, Georgia, Michigan, Nevada and Pennsylvania have refused to certify certain local elections.</p>
<p>With such a close race, voter turnout and motivation will be key in all the battleground states.</p>
<p>As in other swing states, North Carolina’s 16 Electoral College votes could hinge on how political independents vote, said Carter Wrenn, a longtime Republican strategist who has worked on many campaigns.</p>
<p>And those independents can be unpredictable in North Carolina: Their votes helped both Democratic Gov. Roy Cooper and Trump carry the state in the last two general elections.</p>
<p>“It’s the independents that are up for grabs, and they don’t mind splitting a ticket at all,” Wrenn said. “Ultimately, in the general election, that’s the key group.”</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">The economy</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>In every state this year, the economy is a central issue.</p>
<p>As Trump tries to fault Harris and Biden for the high costs of everyday living, polling shows voters blame Harris less for the situation than they did Biden — though likely voters profess more confidence in Trump’s ability to manage the economy.</p>
<p>For her part, Harris has unveiled plans to <a href="https://nebraskaexaminer.com/2024/08/16/harris-unveils-plan-to-curb-price-gouging-boost-child-tax-credit-tackle-rent-hikes/" target="_blank">lower prices of rent, homebuying and groceries, </a>arguing she will remain focused on the middle class from Day One, contrasting her ideas with what she characterizes as Trump’s catering to billionaires.</p>
<p>In Georgia, Republicans and Democrats alike have found success in recent statewide campaigns by highlighting similar kitchen table issues. After attending a Harris rally in Savannah last month, Georgia voter Sarah Damato said she doesn’t believe Trump will fight for the middle class.</p>
<p>At the event, the vice president told listeners she would lower costs by fighting corporate price-fixing and touted her proposal for a “care economy,” a set of progressive proposals including benefits for parents of newborns and credits for first-time homebuyers.</p>
<p>“Kamala Harris made it very evident today that the American family is the most important thing on her mind these days, and she’s going to make it easier for each one of us to have a brighter future,” Damato said.</p>
<p>In Kenosha, Wisconsin, meanwhile, Republican Party volunteer Sharon Buege said she supports the GOP ticket because she sees the race as a matter of “good versus evil.” Speaking outside a news conference by Trump running mate J.D. Vance, Buege said she opposed “the whole left agenda,” adding that her top issues in the race were border security, the economy, human trafficking, homelessness and “indoctrination” in public schools.</p>
<p>At that same news conference, a man who would only give his name as “John” said the economy and inflation mattered most: “I don’t need a reminder of why to support Trump. I can get that every time I go to the gas station or grocery store.”</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Groups of voters</h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>With Republicans looking to run up margins in rural parts of the battleground states and Democrats banking on big leads in cities, the suburbs remain pivotal.</p>
<p>In Georgia, diverse and growing suburbs have helped move the state from reliably red to purple.</p>
<p>In the state’s two largest suburban counties of Cobb and Gwinnett, Biden picked up more than 137,000 votes in 2020 over 2016 Democratic nominee Hillary Clinton, according to data from the Georgia Secretary of State’s office. The same year, Trump boosted his total by just under 32,000 votes over his 2016 performance.</p>
<p>The Trump campaign boasts a mighty in-state operation: nearly 15,000 volunteers signing up between mid-July and the end of August, nearly 300 events scheduled for September, and 4,000 neighborhood organizers and canvassers — known as Trump Force Captains — joining the cause in July and August.</p>
<p>But Team Harris says they are running the largest Georgia operation of any Democratic presidential campaign cycle, with more than 200 campaign staff in 28 offices. Harris’ recent visit to the more conservative south side of the state marked her 16th trip to Georgia since becoming vice president and her seventh trip this year.</p>
<p>Harris is hoping to fire up the young, diverse Democratic base, but her team also is hoping she can hang onto or expand on Biden’s coalition of older, affluent, educated and largely white suburbanites.</p>
<p>“Those are the people who are actually kind of pivotal and who will modify or change their behavior,” said University of Georgia political science professor Charles Bullock.</p>
<p>“These people are largely Republicans, but they can’t bring themselves to vote for Donald Trump or for Republicans who are closely associated with him,” Bullock said.</p>
<p>Larry Ceisler, a Philadelphia public affairs executive and political analyst, said the four suburban Philadelphia counties surrounding Pennsylvania’s largest city are key to winning that state. Once a Republican bastion, the so-called collar counties of Bucks, Chester, Delaware and Montgomery have swung strongly in the other direction since 2016.</p>
<p>That complicates messaging for both campaigns, Ceisler said. Trump’s anti-abortion stance and Harris’ effort to back away from her earlier statements against fracking — both positions that appeal to rural and western Pennsylvania voters — are potential liabilities in suburbs.</p>
<p>Democrats have a 343,000-voter registration advantage over Republicans in Pennsylvania. But the state has been decided by narrow margins in the last two presidential elections.</p>
<p>Daniel Mallinson, an associate professor of public policy and administration at Penn State Harrisburg, noted that the Trump campaign has paid attention to Black and Latino voters.</p>
<p>“One of the weaknesses that Biden had as a candidate was he had weakening support among African American voters. And then Trump has actually done fairly well, particularly in some other states, like in Florida, with Latino voters,” Mallinson said, adding that Harris’ nomination changes the equation somewhat.</p>
<p>After Democrats seemingly all but wrote off Arizona for Biden, the contest there is proving more winnable for Harris. Biden narrowly won Arizona in 2020, but he had been hemorrhaging Latino support this year.</p>
<p>In the manufacturing-heavy upper Midwest, labor unions could prove consequential in not only persuading voters but also motivating them to the polls.</p>
<p>Biden was the first sitting president to visit a picket line when the United Auto Workers last year took on the “Big Three” Detroit automakers — Ford, General Motors and Stellantis — by going on strike. That effort led to significant increases in pay and benefits for workers.</p>
<p>The UAW, which in August announced <a href="https://www.freep.com/story/news/politics/2024/08/14/uaw-kamala-harrris-campaign-money/74799278007/" target="_blank">a national campaign</a> to motivate its 1 million active and retired members to vote for Harris, says its membership accounted for 9.2% of Biden’s 2020 votes in Michigan alone.</p>
<p>“To me, this election is real simple,” UAW president Shawn Fain <a href="https://michiganadvance.com/2024/08/08/in-detroit-harris-and-walz-talk-about-the-midwest-the-middle-class-and-voters-in-the-middle/" target="_blank">told a crowd</a> of about 15,000 people last month at a rally in Detroit for Harris and her running mate, Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz. “It’s about one question. It’s a question we made famous in the labor movement: Which side are you on?”</p>
<p><strong>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Political weaknesses </h4>

	</strong></p>
<p>While Democrats are more motivated than when Biden was the presumptive nominee, they still face internal conflicts, the most high-profile of which has been about the Israel-Hamas war in Gaza.</p>
<p>Dee Sull, a Las Vegas attorney who works in immigration and family law, is a registered Democrat who said she would never vote for Trump. Yet she doesn’t really want to vote for Harris, leaving her “very torn” this election.</p>
<p>“I believe our foreign policy in Gaza is completely ridiculous. I’m very disturbed,” she said of U.S. military aid to Israel. “If we’re going to spend money, I want it spent on my kids here — on my neighbors’ kids here.”</p>
<p>Sull said both parties have silenced the voices of those who protest the death and destruction in Gaza. And she was irritated that Palestinian American activists were not allowed to speak at the Democratic National Convention last month.</p>
<p>Sull won’t sit out the election, but said she would prefer to vote for a third candidate with a viable shot at winning.</p>
<p>“Probably like a lot of Americans would if they had that opportunity,” she said.</p>
<p>For Trump, voters’ overwhelming support for abortion rights could prove a huge liability in swing states.</p>
<p>While Trump has wobbled in recent months on whether he would veto a national abortion ban, the Supreme Court justices he appointed dismantled abortion access across the country in 2022 — an unpopular position even in red states such as Kansas, Kentucky and Ohio that since have voted to expand abortion rights.</p>
<p>In Wisconsin, Planned Parenthood stopped offering abortions at its health clinics after the court’s Dobbs decision because of an 1849 “trigger” state law that immediately took effect. Wisconsin women lost all abortion services there for a year and a half, until a court re-interpreted the state law.</p>
<p>This summer’s shakeup has reset the race, said Amy Walter, publisher of The Cook Political Report, an independent, nonpartisan newsletter that analyzes elections. So far, likely voters in the swing states view Harris more favorably than Biden, she said. But with Trump benefiting from an electorate skeptical of the state of the economy, the newsletter characterized the race as “a battle of inches.”</p>
<p>The campaigns both face a lot of voters who are disenchanted with politics altogether, or else unhappy with their options.</p>
<p>Amy Tarkanian, a conservative television commentator who once lauded Trump to national audiences and was chair of the Nevada State Republican Party in 2011-12, said she’s at “a complete loss” this year. She remains a Republican, even after the state party heavily criticized her when, two years ago, she endorsed a pair of Democratic candidates for state offices.</p>
<p>“I’m not happy, or necessarily sold on Kamala,” Tarkanian said. “… But I absolutely do not want to vote for Donald Trump.”</p>
<p><em><strong>Arizona Mirror’s Jim Small, Michigan Advance’s Anna Liz Nichols and Jon King, Nevada Current’s Hugh Jackson, NC Newsline’s Galen Bacharier, Pennsylvania Capital-Star’s Peter Hall and John Cole, Georgia Recorder’s Ross Williams, and Wisconsin Examiner’s Ruth Conniff and Henry Redman contributed reporting.</strong></em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>States rethink data centers as ‘electricity hogs’ strain the grid</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2024/05/01/states-rethink-data-centers-as-electricity-hogs-strain-the-grid/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 10:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business + Economic Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy + Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Data Center Alley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data centers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electric grid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[electricity demand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Northern Virginia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://virginiamercury.com/?p=38548</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[State Sen. Norm Needleman championed the 2021 legislation designed to lure major data centers to Connecticut. The Democratic lawmaker hoped to better compete with nearby states, bring in a growing industry, and provide paychecks for workers tasked with building the sprawling server farms. But this legislative session, he’s wondering if those tax breaks are appropriate for all [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/data-centers-Loudoun-County-VA_Ted-Shaffrey-Associated-Press.jpeg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/data-centers-Loudoun-County-VA_Ted-Shaffrey-Associated-Press.jpeg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/data-centers-Loudoun-County-VA_Ted-Shaffrey-Associated-Press-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/data-centers-Loudoun-County-VA_Ted-Shaffrey-Associated-Press-768x512.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">High-voltage transmission lines provide electricity to data centers in Ashburn in Loudon County, Virginia, on Sunday, July 16, 2023. The centers house the computer servers and hardware required to support modern internet use, including artificial intelligence. The county is home to the world's largest concentration of data centers. Tech companies like to place the centers here, partly because the region's proximity to the nation's traditional internet backbone allows the servers in those data centers to save nanoseconds crucial to support financial transactions, gaming technology and other time-sensitive applications. (AP Photo/Ted Shaffrey)</p><p>State Sen. Norm Needleman championed the 2021 legislation designed to lure major data centers to Connecticut.</p>
<p>The Democratic lawmaker hoped to better compete with nearby states, bring in a growing industry, and provide paychecks for workers tasked with building the sprawling server farms.</p>
<p>But this legislative session, he’s wondering if <a href="https://portal.ct.gov/decd/content/business-development/data-infrastructure-administration-and-security/office-of-data-infrastructure-administration-and-security/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">those tax breaks </a>are appropriate for all data centers, especially those with the potential to disrupt the state’s clean energy supply.</p>
<p>Particularly concerning to him are plans for a mega data center on the site of the state’s only nuclear power plant. The developer is proposing an arrangement that would give it priority access to electricity generated at the plant, which would mean less carbon-free power for other users.</p>
<p>“That affects our climate goals,” he said. “It’s additional demand of renewable energy that we would have to replace.”</p>
<p>Needleman, co-chair of the Senate Energy and Technology Committee, is now reconsidering details of the state incentive program as he works on <a href="https://www.cga.ct.gov/2024/TOB/S/PDF/2024SB-00299-R00-SB.PDF" target="_blank" rel="noopener">legislation to study</a> the impact of data centers on the state’s electric grid. Mistakes now, he said, could lead to “a real crisis.”</p>
<p>Compared with other employers that states compete for, such as automotive plants, data centers hire relatively few workers. Still, states have offered massive subsidies to lure data centers — both for their enormous up-front capital investment and the cachet of bringing in big tech names such as Apple and Facebook. But as the cost of these subsidy programs balloons and data centers proliferate coast to coast, lawmakers in several states are rethinking their posture as they consider how to cope with the growing electricity demand.</p>
<p>From the outside, data centers can resemble ordinary warehouses. But inside, the windowless structures can house acres of computer servers used to power everything from social media to banking. The centers suck up massive amounts of energy to keep data moving and water to keep servers from overheating.</p>
<p>Data centers are the backbone of the increasingly digital world, and they consume a growing share of the nation’s electricity, with no signs of slowing down. The global consultancy McKinsey &amp; Company predicts these operations will <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/industries/technology-media-and-telecommunications/our-insights/investing-in-the-rising-data-center-economy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">double their U.S. electric demands</a> from 17 gigawatts in 2022 to 35 gigawatts by 2030 — enough electricity to power more than 26 million average homes.</p>
<p>Some states, including Maryland and Mississippi, continue to pursue incentives to land new data centers. But in other states, the growth of the industry is raising alarms over the reliability and affordability of local electric grids, and fears that utilities will meet the demand by leaning more heavily on fossil fuel generation rather than renewables.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" title="“‘Panicked rush to gas’ could hike energy costs, report warns regulators” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2024/04/16/panicked-rush-to-gas-could-hike-energy-costs-report-warns-regulators/embed/#?secret=qt6dctGLwP#?secret=ZL1P9KbfvQ" width="500" height="461" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="ZL1P9KbfvQ" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>In South Carolina, lawmakers have started to question whether these massive power users should continue to receive tax breaks and preferential electric rates.</p>
<p>In Virginia, home to the world’s largest concentration of data centers, a legislative study is underway to learn more about how those operations are affecting electric reliability and affordability.</p>
<p>And Georgia lawmakers just passed <a href="https://www.legis.ga.gov/api/legislation/document/20232024/223348" target="_blank" rel="noopener">legislation</a> that would halt the state’s tax incentives for new data centers for two years. Georgia is home to more than 50 data centers, including those supporting AT&amp;T, Google and UPS, <a href="https://www.georgia.org/data-centers-georgia" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to the state commerce department</a>.</p>
<p>Georgia Republican state Sen. John Albers, a sponsor of the Senate bill, said the significant growth of data centers in his state has helped communities and schools by boosting property tax revenues. But, considering factors such as water and electric use, he said the return on the state’s investment “is not there” and that “initial findings do not support credits from the state level.”</p>
<p>Nationwide, data center subsidies were costing state and local governments about $2 million per job created, according to a <a href="https://goodjobsfirst.org/wp-content/uploads/docs/pdf/datacenters.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2016 study</a> by Good Jobs First, a nonprofit watchdog group that tracks economic development incentives. That figure has certainly ballooned in recent years, said Kasia Tarczynska, the organization’s senior research analyst, who authored the report.</p>
<p>The Georgia bill now sits on the desk of Republican Gov. Brian Kemp, whose office did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
<p>The Data Center Coalition, a trade group representing tech giants including Amazon, Google and Meta, is urging a veto.</p>
<p>Josh Levi, president of the organization, said data center companies are investing billions in new Georgia data centers, making metro Atlanta one of the nation’s biggest industry hubs.</p>
<p>Levi noted that lawmakers in 2022 <a href="https://www.legis.ga.gov/legislation/61909" target="_blank" rel="noopener">extended</a> the state’s tax credit program through 2031.</p>
<p>“The abrupt suspension of an incentive that not only has been on the books, but that was extended two years ago, I think signals tremendous uncertainty, not just for the data center industry, but more broadly,” he said.</p>
<p>Levi said the data center industry has been at the forefront of pushing clean energy. As of last year, data center providers and customers accounted for two-thirds of American wind and solar contracts, according to an S&amp;P Global Market Intelligence <a href="https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/research/datacenter-companies-continue-renewable-buying-spree-surpassing-40-gw-in-us" target="_blank" rel="noopener">report</a>.</p>
<p>“Fundamentally, data is now the lifeblood of our modern economy,” he said. “Everything that we do in our personal and professional lives really points back to data generation, processing and storage.”</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">‘Electricity hogs’</h4>

	</h4>
<p>In fast-growing South Carolina, lawmakers have pointed to data centers as a major factor in rising electricity demand.</p>
<p>As part of <a href="https://www.scstatehouse.gov/sess125_2023-2024/bills/5118.htm#:~:text=SECTION%2039.%20An,operation%20of%20electronic%20equipment" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a broader energy bill</a>, the legislature considered a measure that would prevent data centers from receiving discounted power rates.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" title="“Tech breakthrough could boost states’ use of geothermal power” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2023/08/04/geothermal-energy/embed/#?secret=g9QTLyaoFj#?secret=h1Zi4cU2EJ" width="500" height="473" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="h1Zi4cU2EJ" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>Republican state Rep. Jay West said inducements such as reduced power rates are appropriate for major, transformational endeavors. He pointed to the <a href="https://www.bmwgroup-werke.com/spartanburg/en.html#:~:text=Welcome%20to%20BMW%20GROUP%20Plant,eight%20million%20square%2Dfoot%20campus." target="_blank" rel="noopener">BMW factory in Spartanburg</a>, which employs 11,000 people, draws in major suppliers and pumps millions into the state economy.</p>
<p>While data centers boost local property taxes receipts, they don’t do much for the state, he said, and shouldn’t receive preferential rates. And they are being built faster than new energy generation can be added.</p>
<p>“I do not speak for my caucus or the [legislative] body in saying this,” he said, “but I don’t think South Carolina can handle more data centers.”</p>
<p>The House provision on data center utility rates was quickly struck in a Senate committee, the South Carolina Daily Gazette <a href="https://scdailygazette.com/2024/04/15/data-centers-need-massive-amounts-of-energy-what-does-that-mean-for-sc/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported</a>.</p>
<p>Lynn Teague, vice president of the League of Women Voters of South Carolina, said that change was made with no public discussion.</p>
<p>Teague, who lobbies the legislature, said South Carolinians, including more than 700,000 people living in poverty, shouldn’t have to pick up the tab for tax or utility breaks for major data center firms.</p>
<p>“We have companies like Google with over $300 billion in revenues a year wanting these folks to subsidize their profit margin at the same time that they’re putting intense pressure on not just our energy, but our water,” she said.</p>
<p>Lawmakers saw data centers as a possible successor to South Carolina’s declining textile industry when they approved the data center incentives in 2012, <a href="https://www.thestate.com/news/politics-government/article14403305.html#storylink=cpy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The State reported at the time</a>. One Republican bill sponsor, then-state Rep. Phyllis Henderson, also cited North Carolina’s success with data center incentives, saying South Carolina was “just losing projects right and left to them.”</p>
<p>But on the Senate floor earlier this month, Senate Majority Leader Shane Massey, a Republican, described data centers as “electricity hogs that aren’t really providing a whole lot of jobs.”</p>
<h4 class="editorialSubhed">    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">‘Rippling effects’</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Virginia has been a hub for data centers for decades, touting its proximity to the nation’s capital, inexpensive energy, a robust fiber network and low risk of natural disasters. Now, Virginia lawmakers are increasingly scrutinizing the industry.</p>
<p>That’s in part because data centers have moved into traditionally residential areas, said Republican state Del. Ian Lovejoy, who represents a Northern Virginia district.</p>
<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer ">
<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">
<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">There’s no way to power the data center inventory that’s being proposed and is likely to be built without substantial increases to the power infrastructure and power generation.</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– Virginia Republican state Del. Ian Lovejoy</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
</div>
</div>
<p>He sponsored two pieces of legislation this year affecting data center land use issues. One would have <a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?241+sum+HB1010" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prevented</a> data centers from building too close to parks, schools or neighborhoods; another would have altered land use disclosure rules for developers.</p>
<p>“There’s no way to power the data center inventory that’s being proposed and is likely to be built without substantial increases to the power infrastructure and power generation,” he said. “And that’s going to have rippling effects far away from where the data centers are being sited.”</p>
<p>Aaron Ruby, spokesperson for Dominion Energy in Virginia, the state’s predominant electric provider, said data centers, like other classes of customers, pay for the costs of their electric generation and transmission.</p>
<p>He said the company forecasts consumers’ monthly bills to grow by less than 3% annually over the next 15 years. That increase, he said, is due to the company’s significant investment in renewable energy projects. While Dominion is “all in” on renewables, Ruby said it doesn’t foresee being able to meet increasing demand with only renewables.</p>
<p>“That’s just not physically possible,” he said.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" title="“States Debate Whether to Restrict — Or Invite — Crypto Mining” — Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2023/03/21/states-debate-whether-to-restrict-or-invite-crypto-mining/embed/#?secret=znSlKgNOQl#?secret=x842mBlDM1" width="500" height="610" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" sandbox="allow-scripts" data-secret="x842mBlDM1" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p>
<p>Dominion has pointed to data center growth as a key driver of its increasing electricity demand. In <a href="https://cdn-dominionenergy-prd-001.azureedge.net/-/media/pdfs/global/company/2023-va-integrated-resource-plan.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">one state filing,</a> the company said Virginia’s data centers had a peak load of almost 2.8 gigawatts in 2022.That was 1.5 times the capacity of the company’s <a href="https://www.dominionenergy.com/projects-and-facilities/nuclear-facilities/north-anna-power-station" target="_blank" rel="noopener">North Anna nuclear plant,</a> which powers about 450,000 homes.</p>
<p>“It is heart-stopping — just the scale at which these things are growing and the power they’re sucking up,” said Kendl Kobbervig, the advocacy and communications director at Clean Virginia, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2023/11/01/virginia-michael-bills-clean-energy-democratic-donor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a well-funded advocacy group</a> pushing for renewable energy, campaign finance reform and greater oversight of utilities.</p>
<p>She said the state must address how data centers could undercut its clean energy goals and how the industry is affecting the utility bills of everyday households and small businesses.</p>
<p>Over the past two years, Clean Virginia has tracked more than 40 proposed bills related to data centers.</p>
<p>Most of those efforts stalled this session as some lawmakers elected to wait on the results of <a href="https://jlarc.virginia.gov/pdfs/resolutions/2024_Data%20centers_JLARC.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a study announced in December </a>by the state’s Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission.</p>
<p>The lack of action frustrated many lawmakers and residents.</p>
<p>“I don’t know exactly what the study is going to say that we don’t already know,” said Democratic state Sen. Suhas Subramanyam, who <a href="https://lis.virginia.gov/cgi-bin/legp604.exe?241+sum+SB192" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sponsored a bill</a> that would have required data centers to meet certain energy efficiency and clean energy standards to be eligible for the state’s lucrative sales tax exemptions.</p>
<p>“I think we already know that data centers take up a lot of power and present a lot of challenges to our grid.”</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>This land is our land: States crack down on foreign-owned farm fields</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/12/05/this-land-is-our-land-states-crack-down-on-foreign-owned-farm-fields/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 05:03:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business + Economic Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chinese farm ownership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[farmland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[foreign ownership]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=37135</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Andy Gipson gets concerned even when American allies such as the Netherlands and Germany invest in large swaths of Mississippi’s farmland. “It just bothers me at a gut level,” he said. For Gipson, Mississippi’s commissioner of agriculture and commerce, the growing trend of foreign ownership could threaten what he views as the state’s most valuable [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Mississippi_ag-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Mississippi_ag-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Mississippi_ag-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Mississippi_ag-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Mississippi_ag.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;"> A farm tractor rolls along outside a Silver City, Miss., neighborhood in May. Mississippi lawmakers want the state to join the growing list of those regulating foreign ownership of agricultural land next year. (Rogelio V. Solis/Associated Press)</p><p>Andy Gipson gets concerned even when American allies such as the Netherlands and Germany invest in large swaths of Mississippi’s farmland.</p>
<p>“It just bothers me at a gut level,” he said.</p>
<p>For Gipson, Mississippi’s commissioner of agriculture and commerce, the growing trend of foreign ownership could threaten what he views as the state’s most valuable asset: the land that grows its forests, rice and cotton.</p>
<p>“It is our ability as a country, as a state to produce our own food, our own fiber and our own shelter,” he told Stateline. “And I think every acre that’s sold to anybody outside of this country is one less acre that we have to rely on for our own self-interest, our own national food security.”</p>
<p>Gipson has spent recent months studying the growing amount of his state’s farmland being bought up by foreign interests. He chaired a study committee that just <a href="https://www.mdac.ms.gov/wp-content/uploads/Official-Findings-of-the-Mississippi-Study-Committee-on-Foreign-Purchase-of-Farmland_FINAL-REPORT.pdf" target="_blank">issued a 363-page report on the issue</a> requested by the legislature after a lawmaker had offered a bill to completely ban foreign purchases.</p>
<p>Since its constitution was approved in 1890, the state has had provisions restricting land ownership by “nonresident aliens,” the report noted. But the committee concluded current state law “lacks a clear, workable enforcement mechanism.” The U.S. Department of Agriculture reports that foreign interests held some 757,000 acres of Mississippi’s agricultural land, about 2.5% of the total. Gipson hopes the Republican-led legislature will stiffen the law in the upcoming session.</p>
<p>“I think the time is going to be right in 2024 for the legislature to tighten these laws up,” he said.</p>
<p>If the legislature acts, Mississippi will join a growing group of states seeking to ban or further restrict foreign ownership of farmland. Lawmakers are targeting nations considered hostile to U.S. interests, such as China and Russia, and looking for new enforcement measures. Many see Arkansas as leading the latter push; officials there invoked a new law in October that bans certain foreign owners and ordered a Chinese seed company to divest its land.</p>
<p>Nearly half the states have <a href="https://nationalaglawcenter.org/state-compilations/aglandownership/" target="_blank">some restrictions</a> on the books, some of them dating back to the 1700s.</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">Every acre that’s sold to anybody outside of this country is one less acre that we have to rely on for our own self-interest, our own national food security.</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– Andy Gipson, Mississippi commissioner of agriculture and commerce</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>While the debate is as old as the nation itself, the issue has been reinvigorated in recent years after Chinese firms purchased land near military installments in North Dakota and in Texas, said Micah Brown, an attorney at the National Agricultural Law Center at the University of Arkansas who tracks the issue.</p>
<p>Brown said lawmakers in 36 states proposed some sort of legislation on the issue this year, ranging from caps to bans to targets on certain countries, with measures passing in about a dozen of them. More bills are expected in upcoming sessions.</p>
<p>Some lawmakers and experts warn that such laws could go too far, making it difficult for some farmers to sell their land, discouraging economic development, or even leading to discrimination against certain groups of people such as Asian Americans.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="Et0J7C3HVn"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/09/29/foreign-ownership-of-u-s-farmland-probed-at-u-s-senate-hearing/">Foreign ownership of U.S. farmland probed at U.S. Senate hearing</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Foreign ownership of U.S. farmland probed at U.S. Senate hearing&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/09/29/foreign-ownership-of-u-s-farmland-probed-at-u-s-senate-hearing/embed/#?secret=VK8xtDrGpY#?secret=Et0J7C3HVn" data-secret="Et0J7C3HVn" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Foreigners held an interest in about 40 million acres of U.S. agricultural land at the end of 2021, <a href="https://www.fsa.usda.gov/Assets/USDA-FSA-Public/usdafiles/EPAS/PDF/2021_afida_annual_report_through_12_31_2021.pdf" target="_blank">according to the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</a> Canadian investors own the largest share of that acreage, followed by investors from the United Kingdom and Europe. Foreign ownership represents only about 3.1% of all privately held U.S. agricultural land. But the number is quickly rising: Foreign ownership has increased more than 50% in the past decade, Brown said.</p>
<p>But USDA data shows Chinese ownership is still relatively rare: Chinese interests own less than 1% of the nation’s foreign-held agricultural acreage.</p>
<p>Federal law currently does not regulate foreign ownership of land beyond <a href="https://www.fsa.usda.gov/programs-and-services/economic-and-policy-analysis/afida/index" target="_blank">requiring foreign buyers to register with the USDA</a>. But there is bipartisan interest in Congress in tighter restrictions and reporting on foreign ownership.</p>
<p>At the state level, much of the legislation has been proposed by Republicans, though Brown said it’s largely enjoyed bipartisan support — particularly when bills target ownership by nations considered hostile to American interests.</p>
<p>“It’d be pretty difficult for someone to step out and say, ‘Hey, I don’t think we should restrict North Korea.’ … That’s kind of where some of the politics comes into this. It looks like you’re achieving something. There’s been a lot of bipartisan support on these efforts.”</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Arkansas leads on enforcement</h4>

	</h4>
<p>In October, Arkansas Republican Gov. Sarah Huckabee Sanders invoked the war between Israel and Hamas as she announced her state was taking its first action against foreign ownership of agricultural land.</p>
<p>Sanders described America’s “enemies,” naming not just Hamas, but also China, Iran and Russia as “on the march.”</p>
<p>“Yet for too long in the name of tolerance we’ve let these dangerous governments infiltrate our country,” she said. “Arkansas will tolerate them no longer.”</p>
<p>The state ordered seed and pesticide maker Syngenta to sell 160 acres of land it owns in Northeast Arkansas and uses for research. Legislation passed during the 2023 <a href="https://www.arkleg.state.ar.us/Acts/Search?tbType=&amp;ddBienniumSession=2023%2F2023S1&amp;hdnSessions=b2023%2Cz2023R%2Cz2023S1%2C&amp;ddChamber=A&amp;tbActNumber=636&amp;tbBillNumber=&amp;ddSponsor=&amp;tbAllWords=&amp;tbExactPhrase=&amp;tbOneWord=&amp;tbWithoutWords=&amp;ddExclusivity=Only" target="_blank">session</a> barred certain foreign countries from owning farmland and enabled the state to seek judicial foreclosure for those found in violation. The attorney general’s office said it was to date the only known property covered by the new law.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="iyD8aBNFbd"><p><a href="https://stateline.org/2023/03/14/china-owns-little-us-farmland-but-many-lawmakers-are-worried/" target="_blank">China Owns Little US Farmland, But Many Lawmakers Are Worried</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;China Owns Little US Farmland, But Many Lawmakers Are Worried&#8221; &#8212; Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2023/03/14/china-owns-little-us-farmland-but-many-lawmakers-are-worried/embed/#?secret=1GO2UU4QUi#?secret=iyD8aBNFbd" data-secret="iyD8aBNFbd" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Syngenta, which was given two years to sell its property, did not respond to a Stateline request for comment. The company previously <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/arkansas-orders-chinese-owned-seed-producer-syngenta-sell-us-farmland-2023-10-17/" target="_blank">criticized the Arkansas action as “shortsighted.”</a></p>
<p>Last month, Arkansas Attorney General Tim Griffin, a Republican, announced that Syngenta had paid a $280,000 civil penalty for failing to register with the state as required <a href="https://www.arkleg.state.ar.us/Home/FTPDocument?path=%2FACTS%2F2021R%2FPublic%2FACT1046.pdf" target="_blank">under legislation passed in 2021</a>.</p>
<p>“This serves as a warning to all other Chinese state-owned companies operating in Arkansas — I am investigating these types of properties throughout the state and will exercise all powers afforded to my office under the law,” <a href="https://arkansasag.gov/news_releases/attorney-general-griffin-collects-280000-fine-payment-from-chinese-state-owned-syngenta-seeds-llc/#:~:text=On%20that%20same%20day%2C%20Griffin,160%20acres%20in%20Craighead%20County." target="_blank">he said in a statement last month. </a></p>
<p>Based in Switzerland, Syngenta was bought by ChemChina, a state-owned entity, in 2017.</p>
<p>Republican state Sen. Blake Johnson said he was unaware of Syngenta’s acquisition when he sponsored both pieces of legislation. He said the laws were broadly aimed at protecting national security.</p>
<p>“Our food safety is paramount to the national defense, in my opinion: feeding, clothing ourselves and our military if need be in the future,” he said. “That can be done by our own land. We don’t need to outsource that to our enemies.”</p>
<p>Johnson said he was careful to target the legislation at unfriendly nations. It applies to the same countries named in the International Traffic in Arms Regulations, federal rules that restrict weapons from certain adversarial nations. He noted that friendly nations are exempt: Canada, for instance, owns large swaths of timberland in southern Arkansas.</p>
<p>“That’s not a problem under this law,” he said.</p>
<p>The Arkansas action was closely watched by officials in neighboring Mississippi.</p>
<p>“To date, Arkansas is the only state that has actually enforced a law like this,” said Gipson, the Mississippi agriculture commissioner. “I like the way they did it.”</p>
<p>But he said there are plenty of complications.</p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/donate/?oa_referrer=midstorybox" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="donateContainer">
            <div class="donateTextContainer">
                <p>YOU MAKE OUR WORK POSSIBLE.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="donateButtonContainer">
                <button>SUPPORT</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
<p>Mississippi doesn’t want to hinder important agricultural research, Gipson said. Nor does it want to dissuade investments such as Japanese-based Nissan’s giant assembly plant in Canton.</p>
<p>“Some of the states have had unintended consequences and we don’t want to have those, obviously,” he said.</p>
<p>Republican state Rep. Bill Pigott, who also served on the study committee, said he’s working on legislation that he thinks will pass in 2024.</p>
<p>A farmer who raises peanuts, corn and cattle, Pigott said he has not heard from other farmers about the issue, though he said many constituents are concerned.</p>
<p>“People who listen to the news and watch TV — they seem to be more concerned about it than actually the farmers themselves,” he said. “I do get people ask if we are doing anything.”</p>
<p>Pigott said the legislation will aim to target hostile nations such as China and Russia. Currently, investors from the Netherlands are the largest foreign owners in Mississippi, followed by Germany.</p>
<p>“Almost nobody has any concern with that,” he said. “It is the hostile nations, and No. 1 on that list is China.”</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Striking a balance</h4>

	</h4>
<p>In opening <a href="https://www.agriculture.senate.gov/hearings/foreign-ownership-in-us-agriculture" target="_blank">a U.S. Senate hearing in September,</a> Michigan Democratic Sen. Debbie Stabenow acknowledged that the nation’s food system is an integral component of national security.</p>
<p>With more foreign entities buying up land, she said, the issue deserves scrutiny. But she offered a warning:</p>
<p>“We must also be cautious of our history of barring immigrants from owning land in our country and ensure efforts to protect our national and economic security do not encourage discrimination,” she said.</p>
<p>During<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qoqb1iJpxpI" target="_blank"> hearings on foreign-owned agricultural land</a> in Topeka, Kansas, state Rep. Rui Xi, a Democrat and the only Chinese American in the state House, in September warned about rhetoric casting suspicion on Asian Americans such as grad students lawfully admitted to the United States.</p>
<p>“If we want to take a look at foreign investment in ag land and it’s narrow, that’s great,” Xi said. “If you try to cast a shadow and it continues to cast suspicion on people who are here innocently who are just trying to learn, who are trying to attend our universities, I think that’s where we really, really need to urge caution.”</p>
<p>While more American agricultural land is being bought up by foreign interests, it’s generally not governments that own it, said David Ortega, a food economist at Michigan State University. Syngenta garnered plenty of attention in Arkansas, but it’s more common for foreign individuals and firms to buy land as investments, he said.</p>
<p>So far, Ortega said, there’s no evidence that foreign purchases have raised ag prices or pose any threat to American food security.</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">I don’t think that the root cause of lawmakers’ concerns over this issue is rooted in xenophobia. But I am worried that the way this issue is talked about can lead to xenophobia and those types of issues. And that’s why I and others are urging caution.</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– David Ortega, a food economist at Michigan State University</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>Ortega said policymakers should consider carefully the potential effects of new laws on the broader agricultural economy. China, for instance, is often targeted by legislators. But it’s also the largest buyer of American agricultural exports and could retaliate against American farmers.</p>
<p>“It’s far easier for China to find a new source to buy [from] than it is for us to find new export markets,” he said in an interview.</p>
<p>Ortega said there are specific, local concerns about foreign ownership worth addressing. And while there are many good-faith debates occurring, he does worry that the conversation could lead to discrimination against groups such as Chinese Americans.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="1Azzvc7MFo"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/01/12/youngkin-halted-ford-battery-plant-plans-in-virginia-over-concerns-about-china/">Youngkin halted Ford battery plant efforts in Virginia over concerns about China</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Youngkin halted Ford battery plant efforts in Virginia over concerns about China&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/01/12/youngkin-halted-ford-battery-plant-plans-in-virginia-over-concerns-about-china/embed/#?secret=ebVYspuQYW#?secret=1Azzvc7MFo" data-secret="1Azzvc7MFo" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>“I don’t think that the root cause of lawmakers’ concerns over this issue is rooted in xenophobia,” he said. “But I am worried that the way this issue is talked about can lead to xenophobia and those types of issues. And that’s why I and others are urging caution.”</p>
<p>Since Congress has not enacted any legislation, state lawmakers say they are willing to act.</p>
<p>“While I would prefer we send one message from our Congress to address this issue, that’s beyond the scope of what I can do,” said Georgia state Rep. Clay Pirkle, a Republican. “What I can do is formulate a state response to this issue.”</p>
<p>Pirkle grows cotton, peanuts, rice and butterbeans on about 1,000 acres in southern Georgia. Earlier this year, <a href="https://legiscan.com/GA/text/HB452/id/2705367" target="_blank">he introduced legislation in Atlanta</a> that would prevent nonresident aliens from purchasing farmland near military bases if they were from nations deemed adversarial by the U.S. Department of Commerce — <a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-15/subtitle-A/part-7/subpart-A/section-7.4" target="_blank">a list that currently includes</a> China, Cuba, Iran, North Korea and Russia. The bill didn’t progress, but Pirkle plans to pursue it again next session.</p>
<p>He said crafting legislation on the matter is complicated because he does not want Georgia to dissuade purchases from people who have fled other countries for the United States.</p>
<p>“I really made every effort to avoid unintentional consequences of folks from these countries that have come to the United States because they really desire liberty and freedom,” he said. “And I wanted to make sure that I did not unduly burden them.”</p>
<p>But Pirkle believes something needs to be done. American agricultural land is not a renewable resource. And developers continue to encroach on farmland for the development of new housing and industry.</p>
<p>“The land that we have that we grow crops on to feed the world is the land that we have in ag production,” he said. “We’re not making any more, and it is a scarce resource.”</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Virginia Mercury within States Newsroom, a nonprofit news network supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott S. Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Worries over secrecy grow as state officials shield records from the public</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/11/24/worries-over-secrecy-grow-as-state-officials-shield-records-from-the-public/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 05:03:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Transparency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Arkansas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Florida]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FOIA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[North Carolina]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transparency]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=37060</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just weeks after lawmakers in Little Rock passed legislation shielding certain state records from public disclosure, opponents launched an effort to amend the Arkansas Constitution to protect access to government documents. “The coalition that’s coming together on this is about as broadly bipartisan as you could get — from the extreme, extreme right to the [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="1024" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-1024x1024.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-300x300.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-150x150.jpg 150w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-768x768.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/File-cabinet-2048x2048.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">File cabinets. (Getty Images)</p><p>Just weeks after lawmakers in Little Rock passed legislation shielding certain state records from public disclosure, opponents launched an effort to amend the Arkansas Constitution to protect access to government documents.</p>
<p>“The coalition that’s coming together on this is about as broadly bipartisan as you could get — from the extreme, extreme right to the hard, hard left and all the way in between,” said Nate Bell, a Republican-turned-independent and member of Arkansas Citizens for Transparency, which is pushing the constitutional amendment. “Folks who’ve been bitter political enemies for decades have joined together on this.”</p>
<p>Arkansas is one of several states this year that made more information secret by altering public records laws, often known as Freedom of Information Acts, or FOIAs. State officials say they are being overwhelmed with records requests, sometimes meant to harass lawmakers.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="MgCwaXuQ2T"><p><a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/11/17/foia-friday-a-damning-report-on-richmonds-graduation-shooting-and-orange-county-nondisclosures/">FOIA Friday: A ‘damning’ report on Richmond graduation shooting and Orange nondisclosures</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;FOIA Friday: A ‘damning’ report on Richmond graduation shooting and Orange nondisclosures&#8221; &#8212; Virginia Mercury" src="https://virginiamercury.com/2023/11/17/foia-friday-a-damning-report-on-richmonds-graduation-shooting-and-orange-county-nondisclosures/embed/#?secret=JpSS4ws3kz#?secret=MgCwaXuQ2T" data-secret="MgCwaXuQ2T" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>But the changes have alarmed press freedom and open government activists. Such exemptions to open records provisions can hamper journalists’ efforts to reveal the cost and behind-the-scenes details of governing decisions and make it harder for constituents to hold state officials to account.</p>
<p>Travel records can reveal who has influence with top leaders. Emails and text messages among government officials can reveal candid motivations for policy changes, political hypocrisy and even corruption.</p>
<p>Reviewing early drafts of proposed legislation allows reporters to track how politicians and lobbyists shape the law. And accessing police records, including body camera footage, provides tangible evidence of incidents such as police shootings — which can contradict official characterization of events.</p>
<p>Florida this year enacted a new law exempting the past and future travel records of the governor and other leaders from public disclosure. Arizona increased the price of providing certain police records and made it easier to close legislative records. And North Carolina legislators made rule changes that critics say will allow them to disclose or hide records at their own whims.</p>
<p>Arkansas Republican Gov. Sarah Huckabee Sanders signed her state’s new law in September; it exempts from public disclosure records and communications concerning the security of the governor and other elected leaders.</p>
<p>She sought the change after an <a href="https://apnews.com/article/huckabee-sanders-public-records-lawsuit-14b8a55528cfb8d06e17d6963628f8be" target="_blank">Arkansas blogger sued the state for being denied</a> records he sought on the security of the governor, her use of a state plane and a trade mission to Europe earlier this year. <a href="https://arkansasadvocate.com/2023/09/14/arkansas-officials-security-records-shielded-from-public-under-altered-foia-law/" target="_blank">Critics said it went too far</a> by cutting off access to documents such as receipts and reimbursements that would not risk the governor’s personal safety.</p>
<p>Initially, Sanders also sought to shield communications between the governor’s office and cabinet secretaries as well as documents “revealing the deliberative process” of state agencies. Sanders characterized this year’s legislation as “a great starting place” and <a href="https://arkansasadvocate.com/2023/09/14/arkansas-officials-security-records-shielded-from-public-under-altered-foia-law/" target="_blank">“just the beginning.”</a></p>
<p>Those comments motivated people including Bell, a former Arkansas lawmaker who is a lead organizer of the Arkansas group that is aiming to put an amendment on the 2024 ballot. The measure, which is still being drafted, would enshrine the Arkansas Freedom of Information Act into the constitution and require a public vote for future changes.</p>
<p>“Government of, by and for the people is utterly dependent upon the people knowing what’s happening,” Bell said, “not just knowing what’s been done, but knowing how it’s being done, with whom it’s being done, and the process whereby it’s being done.”</p>
<p>But Arkansas Republican state Sen. Bart Hester said his legislation to protect security records was aimed at ensuring officials’ safety, arguing that bad actors can rely on past behaviors to anticipate future behaviors.</p>
<p>“So, it’s not reasonable or rational — in fact, I’d say it’s crazy for someone to ask for her security detail plans,” he said.</p>
<p>With state agencies overwhelmed with records requests, Hester said he’s interested in new legislation limiting the numbers of requests agencies must handle at any given time — rather than requiring them to respond within a certain number of days. He said a cap would allow school districts and state departments to focus on their core responsibilities, while still requiring them to eventually respond to requests.</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">Government of, by and for the people is utterly dependent upon the people knowing what’s happening, not just knowing what’s been done, but knowing how it’s being done, with whom it’s being done, and the process whereby it’s being done.</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– Former Arkansas lawmaker Nate Bell</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>The governor’s office did not say what kind of future changes Sanders would pursue with the state’s records law. In a statement, spokesperson Alexa Henning said Sanders was “proud that the legislature passed a law with bipartisan support to ensure the sources and methods used by law enforcement to protect constitutional officers and her family are protected.” Two Democrats, one in the House and one in the Senate, voted for the final bill.</p>
<p>Aside from changes in state laws, open government advocates on both sides of the aisle say it’s becoming more difficult to access government documents. Agencies can sometimes charge exorbitant fees for records production or resist outright, pushing disputes to the courts.</p>
<p>“Whether you are a Liberty Mom, or an election denier, or an everyday citizen who’s upset about how much your county board is spending on gravel or a reporter or a lawyer or a Black Lives Matter activist — whatever your motive, that should not matter under the law,” said Nebraska Democratic state Sen. Danielle Conrad. “Citizens have a right to know what their government is doing in their name and with their money.”</p>
<p><a href="https://nebraskaexaminer.com/2023/03/02/conrad-bill-pushes-to-ensure-nebraskans-have-the-greatest-possible-access-to-public-records/" target="_blank">She introduced legislation this year</a> aiming to further open access to public records. Her legislation did not advance but will be considered again next year. It would reduce fees for records, offer a waiver of fees for certain requests and make police body camera footage public following grand jury proceedings.</p>
<p>Conrad said the problems span from the governor’s office to local school boards. She’s worried that agencies that resist records requests are only fostering skepticism in government and democracy itself.</p>
<p>“I’ve heard from just countless citizens about their frustration with these processes,” she said.</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Legislatures protect themselves</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Arizona Republican state Sen. John Kavanagh acknowledged the vital role of Arizona’s open records laws. But he said they’re subject to “horrible abuse” because people rain requests on local governments and state agencies — sometimes to harass officials, other times just undertaking “fishing expeditions.”</p>
<p>“That’s the price you pay for open government,” he said. “The problem is: Where do you draw the line?”</p>
<p>At the same time, the proliferation of police body cameras has increased requests for recordings of high-profile shootings and incidents, Kavanagh said.</p>
<p>He introduced <a href="https://apps.azleg.gov/BillStatus/BillOverview/78750" target="_blank">legislation that passed earlier this year</a> allowing agencies to charge up to $46 per hour for the review, redaction and distribution of police videos. Kavanagh said reviewing those videos has become “unbelievably labor intensive.” Incidents that involve multiple officers require hours of review time as officials redact certain elements like faces of witnesses.</p>
<p>In another new law, the Arizona legislature allowed state officials to shield information such as home addresses from public disclosure, which Kavanagh said stemmed from growing safety concerns.</p>
<p>Early in the session, Republicans <a href="https://www.azcentral.com/story/news/politics/legislature/2023/01/26/arizona-legislature-to-eliminate-public-records-faster-under-republican-plan/69842493007/" target="_blank">voted to change rules in both legislative chambers</a> allowing legislators to delete their emails every 90 days and text messages at any time if members believe the “reference value has been served,” <a href="https://azcapitoltimes.com/news/2023/11/03/legislature-chips-away-at-government-transparency/" target="_blank">the Arizona Capitol Times reported</a>.</p>
<p>North Carolina lawmakers ended their session with a similar move.</p>
<p><a href="https://apnews.com/article/north-carolina-public-records-budget-exempt-2e7c514af722fd0850fd704b64e8ced4" target="_blank">Tucked more than 500 pages deep in a 625-page budget bill</a> was a new provision allowing lawmakers to exempt legislative records from public release. Legislators decide which documents are released — and which are withheld, destroyed or sold, according to<a href="https://www.ncleg.gov/Sessions/2023/Bills/House/PDF/H259v7.pdf" target="_blank"> the legislation</a>.</p>
<p>A last-minute addition, the measure has sparked bipartisan backlash in North Carolina.</p>
<p>“I don’t really know anybody outside the legislature who thinks this is a good idea,” said Andy Jackson, director of the Civitas Center for Public Integrity at the conservative John Locke Foundation.</p>
<p>House Speaker Tim Moore, a Republican, did not respond to request for comment. But last month, he defended the move, telling reporters that members of the General Assembly were overwhelmed with requests designed “to add to cost and harassment.”</p>
<p>“It’s a massive change,” said Brooks Fuller, executive director of the North Carolina Open Government Coalition. “It undermines the public access to any document that touches the hands of an individual legislator.”</p>
<p>Fuller, who is also an assistant professor of journalism at Elon University, said the move has sparked widespread confusion among lawmakers. Some have publicly committed to following previous practice of releasing most records, but the new rules have not been widely tested.</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Protecting governors’ records</h4>

	</h4>
<p>Like Arkansas, Florida this year closed access to some gubernatorial records.</p>
<p>The Sunshine State, which has long touted one of the nation’s most liberal public records laws, created one of the most significant records exemptions in decades by blocking access to the publicly funded travel records of Republican Gov. Ron DeSantis, who is running for president.</p>
<p>“That would be bad enough — travel records — but they made it retroactive,” said Barbara Petersen, executive director of the Florida Center for Government Accountability. “So we can’t get any records now, even for travel that took place three years ago or travel that [former Republican Gov.] Charlie Crist did as governor.”</p>
<p>Republicans said the change in Florida law was a matter of protecting public officials. But Petersen, whose organization supports local reporting and access to public records, said it is far too broad.</p>
<p>Aside from travel plans or costs, Petersen said, the law prevents disclosure of who the governor travels with, and who visits the governor’s office and the governor’s mansion. In September, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2023/09/14/ron-desantis-private-flights/" target="_blank">The Washington Post reported on undisclosed trips</a> DeSantis took on private jets, revealing “his proclivity for luxury travel and leisure time with wealthy donors.”</p>
<p>“There’s no accountability there,” Petersen said. “We don’t know who’s paying for the plane. We don’t know what the plane costs.”</p>
<p>Florida Republican state Sen. Jonathan Martin, who authored the legislation, did not respond to a request for comment. A DeSantis spokesperson did not answer questions but pointed to the governor’s comments at a May news conference, where <a href="https://thefloridachannel.org/videos/5-5-23-governors-press-conference-on-legislative-sine-die/" target="_blank">he said the issue was one of security.</a></p>
<p>“You’re in a situation, unfortunately, where these movements are watched,” he said.</p>
<p>Even with a strong law on paper, access to public records has greatly diminished under DeSantis in practice, Petersen said. Citizens and reporters wait months, even years for responses — or have to undertake costly lawsuits to secure public information.</p>
<p>“The ability to access public records in Florida has significantly declined,” she said. “There are reporters who have waited nine, 10, 14 months for a public record. I can only think that’s by design.”</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Virginia Mercury within States Newsroom, a nonprofit news network supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott S. Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a>. </em></p>
        <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/subscribe" style="text-decoration:none;">
        <div class="subscribeShortcodeContainer">
            <div class="subscribeTextContainer">
                <i class="fas fa-envelope"></i>
                <p>GET THE MORNING HEADLINES.</p>
            </div>
            <div class="subscribeButtonContainer">
                <button>SUBSCRIBE</button>
            </div>
        </div>
        </a>
        
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Who’s going to work there?’: Lawmakers grapple with labor shortages</title>
		<link>https://virginiamercury.com/2023/08/28/whos-going-to-work-there-lawmakers-grapple-with-labor-shortages/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kevin Hardy]]></dc:creator>

        <dc:contributor>khardy@stateline.org (Kevin Hardy)</dc:contributor>

		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 04:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business + Economic Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government + Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[child care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[child care affordability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[housing affordability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[housing shortages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigrant workers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor demand]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.virginiamercury.com/?p=36107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[INDIANAPOLIS — For years, Indiana’s GOP-controlled legislature has focused on creating a business-friendly climate by pushing favorable tax rates and regulations, aiming to foster the creation of good-paying jobs across the state. The way Republican state Sen. Michael Crider sees it, those moves have worked: Companies such as Amazon and Walmart have built new warehouses and [&#8230;]]]></description>
																						<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img width="1024" height="683" src="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/helpwanted_hiring-1024x683.jpg" class="attachment-large size-large wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/helpwanted_hiring-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/helpwanted_hiring-300x200.jpg 300w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/helpwanted_hiring-768x512.jpg 768w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/helpwanted_hiring-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://virginiamercury.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/helpwanted_hiring-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p style="font-size:12px;">A company advertises a help wanted sign on April 09, 2021 in Pawtucket, Rhode Island. (Photo by Spencer Platt/Getty Images) </p><p>INDIANAPOLIS — For years, Indiana’s GOP-controlled legislature has focused on creating a business-friendly climate by pushing favorable tax rates and regulations, aiming to foster the creation of good-paying jobs across the state.</p>
<p>The way Republican state Sen. Michael Crider sees it, those moves have worked: Companies such as Amazon and Walmart have built new warehouses and fulfillment centers in his district just east of Indianapolis.</p>
<p>But it didn’t take long for him to realize how all those new private-sector jobs could further strain short-handed local governments, particularly school systems, by luring away bus drivers and teachers’ aides.</p>
<p>“That is a general theme in almost every conversation: An able-bodied person that desires to work can find a job just about anywhere in Indiana right now,” said Crider, the Senate majority whip. “And it’s reached the point where I think in some areas, businesses are saying we can’t expand, we would like to expand, we would expand, but we cannot because we don’t have enough workers.”</p>
<p>State legislators from across the country point to the labor shortage as a major concern. While they have been pushing job training and career readiness programs, they increasingly are addressing other factors that can keep people from joining the workforce, such as a lack of child care, affordable housing or mental health services. Some want to attract more immigrants.</p>
<p>The national worker shortage and those indirect solutions came up time and again during the annual summit of the National Conference of State Legislatures, which brought hundreds of lawmakers, policy experts and lobbyists together at the Indiana Convention Center.</p>
<p>Crider, for example, said a persistent lack of mental health resources has limited the work potential of some people in his state.</p>
<p>“It not only keeps people out of the workforce, but it also affects people’s attendance and focus on the task at hand when somebody in their family is struggling,” he said. “And so that’s one of the things I think we talked about quite a bit.”</p>
<p>Research from Indiana’s behavioral health commission in 2022 found that mental illness was <a href="https://indianactsi.org/news_/untreated-mental-illness-is-costing-indiana-more-than-4-billion-per-year/" target="_blank">costing the state more than $4 billion</a> in lost productivity and health care costs each year. The potential to improve worker productivity was one reason the legislature earlier this year near-unanimously approved Crider’s legislation that <a href="https://indianacapitalchronicle.com/2023/07/10/game-changer-bill-aims-to-revolutionize-mental-healthcare-system/" target="_blank">overhauled the state’s antiquated mental health system</a> and aims to infuse $130 million more per year into services.</p>
<p>Crider said the workforce shortage requires a comprehensive set of solutions. Quality of life is as important as job opportunities — and that is especially true for remote workers who can live anywhere.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="GxZlITny2f"><p><a href="https://stateline.org/2023/07/10/despite-pandemic-pay-boost-low-wage-workers-still-cant-afford-basic-needs/" target="_blank">Despite pandemic pay boost, low-wage workers still can&#8217;t afford basic needs</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;Despite pandemic pay boost, low-wage workers still can&#8217;t afford basic needs&#8221; &#8212; Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2023/07/10/despite-pandemic-pay-boost-low-wage-workers-still-cant-afford-basic-needs/embed/#?secret=hkcht4jqyv#?secret=GxZlITny2f" data-secret="GxZlITny2f" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>Doug Howard, senior vice president of human services at government services provider Maximus, said employers across the country have had to get creative to fill job openings: Some have lured retirees back into the workforce or targeted young people for part-time work.</p>
<p>“The punchline here is that we don’t have enough people,” he told a group of lawmakers at the summit.</p>
<p>Howard cited <a href="https://www.bls.gov/news.release/jolts.nr0.htm" target="_blank">federal labor data showing there are nearly 10 million unfilled jobs</a> across the country, but just under 6 million people seeking jobs. The nation’s labor force participation rate, which measures the percentage of the civilian population in the workforce, has not returned to its pre-pandemic rate, which even then had steadily been falling for decades. (In July, the national rate was 62.6% compared with 66.2% in July 2003.)</p>
<p>“Those all equal a math problem,” he said.</p>
<p>Those challenges are only exacerbated by state efforts to recruit new employers. A new factory doesn’t just need workers on the assembly line, Howard noted. Contractors need workers to build the plant. Those workers need housing. And both permanent and temporary workers need child care.</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">States target housing and child care</h4>

	</h4>
<p>While the labor market has been squeezed since the pandemic recovery, experts say things could still get worse.</p>
<p>In Indianapolis, several labor experts said three massive federal spending bills will heighten the need for workers: the Bipartisan Infrastructure Bill, the Inflation Reduction Act and the CHIPS and Science Act. The infrastructure bill alone is expected to spend $1.2 trillion on bridges, ports and mass transit systems.</p>
<p>“That is a lot of money for projects at a time when the U.S. is facing a very tight labor market,” Suzanne Hultin, the director of the National Conference of State Legislatures’ employment, labor and retirement program, said during one panel in Indianapolis.</p>
<p>New Hampshire Democratic state Rep. Brian Sullivan said the impending federal investments weren’t on his radar before the conference — but definitely are now.</p>
<p>“If we can’t fill the jobs we’ve got now and we start building more manufacturing plants and that sort of thing, who’s going to work there?” he said.</p>
<p>The ranking member of the New Hampshire House Labor, Industrial and Rehabilitative Services Committee, Sullivan said he views housing as a major driver of workforce challenges in his state.</p>
<p>He pointed to Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center, New Hampshire’s only academic medical center and an employer of more than 8,000 people.</p>
<p>“They are having huge problems being able to attract workers who then can find some place to live,” Sullivan said in an interview with Stateline. “They’re not bad jobs. But the cost of housing is so high that a lot of these people will say, ‘I can’t work here, I’ve got to go live somewhere where I can afford housing.’”</p>
<p>Sullivan said two recently launched bipartisan special committees — one on workforce housing and one on child care — should help tackle labor challenges. He expects legislation soon from those efforts, though <a href="https://www.seacoastonline.com/restricted/?return=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.seacoastonline.com%2Fstory%2Fopinion%2Fcolumns%2F2023%2F07%2F23%2Fcommentary-nh-has-made-great-strides-to-benefit-children-families%2F70441806007%2F" target="_blank">the legislature has already added $60 million for child care services</a>.</p>

<div class=" newsroomBlockQuoteContainer  ">
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteSVGContainer">
		<svg id="Layer_1" data-name="Layer 1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 12.81 9">
			<g>
				<path d="M2.7,0A3,3,0,0,0,.7.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0,0,2.7,2.14,2.14,0,0,0,.8,4.4a2.84,2.84,0,0,0,1.7.7,1.45,1.45,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A3.47,3.47,0,0,1,3,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6A5.06,5.06,0,0,0,6,3.7a3.92,3.92,0,0,0-.9-2.6A3.19,3.19,0,0,0,2.7,0Z"/>
				<path d="M11.8,1.1A2.84,2.84,0,0,0,9.5,0a2.79,2.79,0,0,0-2,.8,2.64,2.64,0,0,0-.7,1.9,2.06,2.06,0,0,0,.7,1.7,2.41,2.41,0,0,0,1.8.7,1.85,1.85,0,0,0,.7-.2,1.45,1.45,0,0,1,.7-.2q.3,0,.3.6A2.94,2.94,0,0,1,9.8,7.6a4.21,4.21,0,0,1-2.6,1V9a5.51,5.51,0,0,0,4-1.6,4.6,4.6,0,0,0,1.6-3.8A3.47,3.47,0,0,0,11.8,1.1Z"/>
			</g>
		</svg>
	</div>
	<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteQuoteContainer">
		<p class="newsroomBlockQuote ">There are so many workers who cannot work unpredictable schedules because they do not have reliable child care. Well, hospitality has unpredictable schedules and so does health care. And those kinds of systemic problems are just running up against each other.</p>
	</div>
		<div class="newsroomBlockQuoteAuthorContainer">
		<p style="font-size:13px"><b>– Washington state Sen. Karen Keiser</b></p>
	</div>
	</div>

	
<p>“I don’t know if it’s the best way,” Sullivan said. “But it’s the way the legislature can contribute. I think employers are going to have to contribute and I think it’s got to be a communitywide effort.”</p>
<p><i></i>In Washington state, a lack of child care is a major driver of the labor shortage, said Democratic state Sen. Karen Keiser. While all industries have struggled to hire, she said hospitality and health care employers are especially hard pressed in Washington.</p>
<p>“There are so many workers who cannot work unpredictable schedules because they do not have reliable child care,” she said. “Well, hospitality has unpredictable schedules and so does health care. And those kinds of systemic problems are just running up against each other.”</p>
<p>In 2021, Washington state <a href="https://www.dcyf.wa.gov/about/government-affairs/fair-start-for-kids-act" target="_blank">approved a $1.1 billion plan</a> to make child care and early learning programs more affordable and accessible. This year, the legislature added <a href="https://washingtonstatestandard.com/2023/05/10/the-states-child-care-gap-proves-tough-to-solve/" target="_blank">more than $400 million in new funds</a> to raise child care provider pay and increase subsidies for families over the next two years.</p>
<p>Keiser, president pro tempore of the state Senate, said the ongoing labor shortage does provide workers more leverage, even if it’s a pain for employers.</p>
<p>“And that’s good,” she said, “because they have seen pay stagnation for the last 20 years. … At the same time, we do need to get to work. We need the economy to grow.”</p>
<h4>    <h4 class="editorialSubhed">Immigration, education efforts</h4>

	</h4>
<p>North Dakota Republican state Rep. Karen Karls sees it in the grocery stores.</p>
<p>She used to encounter mostly young people running registers and bagging groceries in the capital city of Bismarck. Now, many of those workers are older adults.</p>
<p>“That’s a little scary,” said Karls, a 17-year veteran of the legislature. “Their work ethic is fabulous, but I just think we need younger workers.”</p>
<p>She said the problem in North Dakota is complex: She blames the pandemic for getting people “used to not working.” For others, it instilled a strong preference for remote work, a challenge for many employers demanding on-site attendance, she said.</p>
<p>North Dakota has more than 20,000 job openings — a huge number for a state of just over 770,000 people. The state has 0.3 unemployed people per job opening, per the federal Bureau of Labor Statistics.</p>
<p>“We’re just not having enough babies,” Karls said.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="7zO4AFlhi3"><p><a href="https://stateline.org/2023/07/19/a-she-cession-no-more-after-covid-dip-womens-employment-hits-all-time-high/" target="_blank">A ‘she-cession’ no more: After COVID dip, women’s employment hits all-time high</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted"  title="&#8220;A ‘she-cession’ no more: After COVID dip, women’s employment hits all-time high&#8221; &#8212; Stateline" src="https://stateline.org/2023/07/19/a-she-cession-no-more-after-covid-dip-womens-employment-hits-all-time-high/embed/#?secret=o90jbXAnTh#?secret=7zO4AFlhi3" data-secret="7zO4AFlhi3" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></p>
<p>The state is examining immigration as a potential solution.</p>
<p>In April, Republican Gov. Doug Burgum signed bipartisan legislation <a href="https://www.governor.nd.gov/news/burgum-signs-bill-creating-office-legal-immigration-help-address-north-dakotas-workforce" target="_blank">creating the Office of Legal Immigration</a> within the state’s Department of Commerce to help businesses recruit and retain foreign labor.</p>
<p>And Brent Sanford, a former GOP lieutenant governor, is leading a pilot program called <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ukraine-refugee-russia-war-biden-humanitarian-parole-1a57fb5f59d150380a6a1f3e7a5ef093" target="_blank">Uniting for Ukraine</a>. Run by the North Dakota Petroleum Council, the program brings refugees and migrants from Ukraine to work in the state’s Bakken oil fields. Karls said jobs in that remote portion of the state pay very well, but because the oil patch is surrounded by very small towns, housing is a major struggle for workers.</p>
<p>Not all lawmakers agree state government should help private companies.</p>
<p>“I think it’s more of a free market issue,” said Texas Democratic state Rep. Penny Morales Shaw. “Employers have to figure out a way to retain people, they’ve got to figure out a way to attract people.”</p>
<p>In Arkansas, the state government has focused on building up careers in the trades.</p>
<p>Arkansas state Rep. Stephen Meeks, a Republican, pointed to the state’s <a href="https://www.beprobeproudar.org/" target="_blank">Be Pro Be Proud </a>campaign. An initiative led by the Associated Industries of Arkansas Foundation, it encourages young people to enter fields such as construction, railroading and manufacturing.</p>
<p>State leaders even hold a Draft Day, pairing graduating seniors enrolled in career and technical education courses with employers ready to hire them.</p>
<p>Meeks said the state has also had a difficult time filling public school teaching positions.</p>
<p>That was part of the motivation behind the state’s <a href="https://www.arkansasonline.com/news/2023/mar/10/what-you-need-to-know-about-arkansas-learns/" target="_blank">LEARNS Act,</a> which passed earlier this year. In addition to a new school voucher program, Republican Gov. Sarah Huckabee Sanders’ signature education bill also raised minimum teacher pay to $50,000 across the state.</p>
<p>Meeks said some Arkansas teachers were making as little as $36,000 per year before that legislation, making it difficult for the state to retain teachers whose degrees could command a higher salary in the private sector.</p>
<p>“I think that’ll definitely help,” he said, “especially in the rural areas of our state.”</p>
<p><em><a href="https://stateline.org" target="_blank">Stateline</a> is a sister publication of the Virginia Mercury within States Newsroom, a nonprofit news network supported by grants and a coalition of donors as a 501c(3) public charity. Stateline maintains editorial independence. Contact Editor Scott S. Greenberger for questions: <a href="mailto:info@stateline.org">info@stateline.org</a>. Follow Stateline on <a href="https://facebook.com/statelinenewsroom" target="_blank">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/stateline_news" target="_blank">Twitter</a>.</em></p>
<div class="donateContainer">
<div class="donateTextContainer"></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
